<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
	<name>Swordmage</name>
	<subname>Spellblade</subname>
	<role>Defender</role>
	<source>Arcane</source>
	<shortfluff>You apply the arcane arts to melee combat, using your magic to enhance your combat skills so that your blade bites not only with steel, but also with fire, lightning and other arcane forces</shortfluff>
	<keyability>Intelligence</keyability>
	<keyability>Strength</keyability>
	<keyability>Constitution</keyability>
	
	<proficiency>
		<type>Armor</type>
		<name>Cloth</name>
        <name>Leather</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Weapon</type>
		<name>Simple melee</name>
		<name>Simple ranged</name>
        <name>Military light blade</name>
        <name>Military heavy blade</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Implement</type>
		<name>Light blade</name>
		<name>Heavy blade</name>
	</proficiency>
	
	<defense>
		<name>Will</name>
		<value>+2</value>
	</defense>
	
	<hpbase>15</hpbase>
	<hpgain>6</hpgain>
	<surgebase>8</surgebase>
	
	<skills>
		<trained>Arcana</trained>
		<number>3</number>
	</skills>
	
	<fluff>A Swordmage studies and practices for years to master his or her skills, mastering the fundamentals of arcane magic and combining the academic study with endless hours of physical training.</fluff>
	<fluff>Magical barriers of force swirl around a Spellblade, protecting him or her from harm and the weapon each carries is an extension of his or her being, both body and mind. The weapon pulses with eldritch energy as a Spellblade prepares to both defend allies and to unleash magical fury against foes.</fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Arcane Aegis</name>
		<benefit>A Swordmage can place a magical warding upon a foe, allowing him or her to respond when the foe attacks an ally.</benefit>
		<benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>arcane aegis</i>]]> class utility. As your specialized response, choose either Aegis of Assault, Aegis of Ensnarement, or Aegis of Shielding.</benefit>
		
		<power>
			<title>Arcane Aegis</title>
			<class>Swordmage</class> <category>Utility</category>
			<fluff>You create an arcane link between yourself and a foe</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
				<keyword>Arcane</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Close</type> <range>burst 2</range>
				<section>
					<indent>2</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text><![CDATA[<b>Close</b>]]> burst 3</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>2</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text><![CDATA[<b>Close</b>]]> burst 5</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>One creature you can see in the burst</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You mark the target. The target remains marked until you use this power against another target.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>If you mark other creatures using other powers or effecs, the target is still marked by this power. A new mark supersedes a mark that was already in place.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>If a marked creature makes an attack that doesn't include you as a target, it takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls with that attack.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
			
		<subfeature>
			<name>Aegis of Assault</name>
			<benefit>The Aegis of Assault embodies an aggressive method of combat and is favoured by Spellblades that fling their opponents across the battlefield or move from foe to foe.</benefit>
			<benefit>When a Swordmage power allows you to teleport, you can increase the distance by 1 square.</benefit>
			<benefit>Also, when you use an arcane power to push an enemy, you increase the forced movement by 1 square.</benefit>
			<benefit>In addition, you gain the <![CDATA[<i>aegis of assault</i>]]> power.</benefit>
			
			<power>
				<title>Aegis of Assault</title>
				<class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category>
				<fluff>Your aegis allows you to instantly respond the the marked foe's attack with a counterassault</fluff>
				<part>
					<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
					<keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
					<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
					<type>Personal</type>
					<section>
						<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
						<text>The enemy marked by your <![CDATA[<i>arcane aegis</i>]]> makes an attack that doesn't include you as a target and is within 10 squares of you</text>
					</section>
					<section>
						<shade>true</shade>
						<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
						<text>You teleport to a space adjacent to the triggering enemy. If no unnoccupied space exists adjacent to the enemy, you can't use this power.</text>
					</section>
					<section>
						<shade>true</shade>
						<text>You make a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> against the triggering enemy. If you make the attack using your bonded weapon, the attack deals additional damage equal to your Strength modifier.</text>
					</section>
				</part>
			</power>
			
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Aegis of Ensnarement</name>
			<benefit>Spellblades favouring the Aegis of Ensnarement are sly hunters who close in on prey, hounding it until it is vanguished.</benefit>
			<benefit>When you have combat advantage against the enemy marked by your <![CDATA[<i>arcane aegis</i>]]>, you gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls against it.</benefit>
			<benefit>Also, when you use an arcane power to teleport an enemy to hazardous terrain and the enemy succeeds in its saving throw to negate that teleport, you instead teleport it to the space that is closest to the original destination and is safe for the enemy.</benefit>
			<benefit>In addition, you gain the <![CDATA[<i>aegis of ensnarement</i>]]> power.</benefit>
			
			<power>
				<title>Aegis of Ensnarement</title>
				<class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category>
				<fluff>Your aegis allows you to draw to draw the enemy back to you</fluff>
				<part>
					<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
					<keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
					<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
					<type>Close</type> <range>burst 10</range>
					<section>
						<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
						<text>The enemy marked by your <![CDATA[<i>arcane aegis</i>]]> makes an attack that doesn't include you as a target and is within 10 squares of you</text>
					</section>
					<section>
						<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
						<text>The triggering enemy</text>
					</section>
					<section>
						<shade>true</shade>
						<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
						<text>You teleport the target to a space adjacent to you. If no unnoccupied space exists adjacent to you, you can't use this power.</text>
					</section>
					<section>
						<shade>true</shade>
						<text>The target grants combat advantage to all creatures until the start of its next turn.</text>
					</section>
				</part>
			</power>
			
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Aegis of Shielding</name>
			<benefit>Specializing in Aegis of Shielding allows a Spellblade to protect his or her allies with magical shields of force, and to keep enemies away from said allies.</benefit>
			<benefit>When you use a Swordmage power that grants resistance, increase that resistance by 2. Starting at 11th level, you instead increase the resistance by 3, and at 21st level you increase the resistance by 5.</benefit>
			<benefit>Also, when you use an arcane power to teleport an ally, you can increase the distance of that teleport by 1 square and can target the ally from 1 square further.</benefit>
			<benefit>In addition, you gain the <![CDATA[<i>aegis of shielding</i>]]> power.</benefit>
			
			<power>
				<title>Aegis of Shielding</title>
				<class>Swordmage</class> <category>Utility</category>
				<fluff>Your aegis allows you blunt the foe's attacks against your allies</fluff>
				<part>
					<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
					<keyword>Arcane</keyword>
					<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
					<type>Special</type>
					<section>
						<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
						<text>The enemy marked by your <![CDATA[<i>arcane aegis</i>]]> makes an attack that doesn't include you as a target and is within 10 squares of you</text>
					</section>
					<section>
						<shade>true</shade>
						<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
						<text>You reduce the damage dealt by the triggering attack against any one target of the attack. The reduction equals one-half your level + your Constitution modifier.</text>
					</section>
				</part>
			</power>
			
		</subfeature>
		
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Swordbond</name>
		<benefit>Though they are masters of many weapons, for a given Swordmage there is always one weapon that he or she considers special. Through an arcane rite, the weapon becomes bound to the Swordmage and grants him or her additional capabilities.</benefit>
		<benefit>You can spend 1 hour of meditation to bond with one weapon that you can use as an implement (normally, a light blade or a heavy blade). You can have only one bonded weapon; performing the meditation with a different weapon dissipates the bond from the previous one.</benefit>
		<benefit>You can call your bonded weapon to your hand from up to 10 squares away as a standard action.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
</class>
