<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <collection>Swordmage Lvl 6 Utility Spells</collection>

   <power>
      <title>Clap of Thunder</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>Raising your blade, you send out a clap of thunder that sends your foes sprawling as noise cascades over them</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Implement</keyword> <keyword>Thunder</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Close</type> <range>burst 1</range>
         <type2>Close</type2> <range2>wave 2</range2>
         <target>Each creature in the burst or wave</target>
         Intelligence vs. Fortitude
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit:</name>
         3d6 + Intelligence modifier thunder damage, and you knock the target prone.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Miss:</name>
         Half damage if the target is marked by your <i>arcane aegis</i> class power.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Dazing Rebuke</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
      <fluff>Your sword swing unleashes a barrage of nettling darts of force that punish a foe for attacking your allies</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Force</keyword> <keyword>Implement</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Aegis of Shielding:</name>
         You can use this power as an immediate interrupt. The target can finish the triggering attack on a hit, even though it becomes dazed and might be out of actions.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Trigger:</name>
         An enemy within 5 squares of you hits or misses an ally
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Ranged</type> <range>5</range>
         <target>the triggering enemy</target>
         Intelligence vs. Will
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit:</name>
         1d8 + Intelligence modifier force damage, and the target is dazed until the start of the currently acting creature's next turn.
      </section>
      <section shade="" indent="1">
         <name>Aegis of Shielding:</name>
         The target also takes a penalty to all damage rolls while it remains dazed. The penalty equals 3 + your Constitution modifier.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Miss:</name>
         If the target is marked by you, it takes force damage equal to your Intelligence modifier + your implement's enhancement bonus, and cannot make <i>reactive strikes</i> until the start of the currently acting creature's next turn.
      </section>
      <section indent="1">
         <name>Aegis of Shielding:</name>
         The target takes half the penalty to damage rolls. If the target is marked by you, it cannot make any triggered attacks instead of only <i>reactive strikes</i>.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Echoes of Sword Magic</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Free</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>You tap into the magic of your failed strike to unleash a mighty barrage of thunder</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Implement</keyword> <keyword>Thunder</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Requirement:</name>
         You must have used a Swordmage attack power this turn and missed all targets with it.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Close</type> <range>wave 3</range>
         <target>each creature in the burst</target>
         Intelligence vs. Fortitude
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit:</name>
         2d8 + Intelligence modifier thunder damage.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         The target counts as being marked by your <i>arcane aegis</i> until the end of your next turn.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Miss:</name>
         If you used a Swordmage Lightning attack power this turn, you deal thunder damage equal to your 2 + your Intelligence modifier + your implement's enhancement bonus.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Electrified Lash</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>You point your sword into the air, and cruel talons of white lightning reach out toward your foes</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Implement</keyword> <keyword>Lightning</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Close</type> <range>burst 2</range>
         <target>each enemy in the burst</target>
         Intelligence vs. Reflex
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit:</name>
         3d6 + Intelligence modifier lightning damage.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Miss:</name>
         If the target is marked by you, it takes lightning damage equal to 2 + your Intelligence modifier + your implement's enhancement bonus.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Evoker's Summons</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>You violoently summon a foe to your side</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Force</keyword> <keyword>Implement</keyword> <keyword>Teleportation</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Close</type> <range>burst 3</range>
         <target>each enemy in the burst</target>
         Intelligence vs. Will
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit:</name>
         2d6 + Intelligence modifier force damage, and you teleport the target to a space adjacent to you. If there is not enough space adjacent to you, you teleport the target as close to you as possible instead.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Miss:</name>
         You teleport the target 1 square towards you, as if you had pulled it.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Fettering Aegis</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
      <fluff>The magic of your aegis creates an invisiblew tether between you and your enemy, preventing it from escaping</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Force</keyword> <keyword>Implement</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Trigger:</name>
         An enemy that you can see and that is marked by your <i>arcane aegis</i> willingly moves away from you
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
         <target>the triggering enemy</target>
         Intelligence vs. Fortitude
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit:</name>
         2d8 + Intelligence modifier force damage, and you pull the target up to 8 squares. You must pull the target to a space adjacent to you if you can.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         The target stops moving, though it can resume moving if it has further actions remaining.
      </section>
      <section shade="" indent="1">
         <name>Aegis of Ensnarement:</name>
         The target is immobilized until the end of its next turn.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Miss:</name>
         You pull the target half the distance, and it can resume moving after the pull.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Flamewall Strike</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>With a mighty sweep of your blade, dancing tongues of arcane fire rise from the ground at the feet of your foes</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Fire</keyword> <keyword>Implement</keyword> <keyword>Zone</keyword>
      <section auto="no-opportunity"/>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Effect:</name>
         <type>Area</type> <range>wall 5 within 1 square</range>
         The wall creates a zone of leaping flames until the end of your next turn. The origin square of the wall does not need to be within 1 square as long as at least one square is. The wall is 1 square high.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         Any creature that enters the wall's space or ends its turn there takes fire damage equal to 2 + your Intelligence modifier + your implement's enhancement bonus. A creature can take this damage only once per turn.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Rejuvenating Strike</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>Your attack draws life from your foe's injury and instills you with renewed energy</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range>
         <target>one creature</target>
         Intelligence vs. AC and Fortitude
      </section>
      <section auto="smage-both"/>
      <section auto="" indent="1">You can choose in which order you want to resolve the hits</section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit (AC):</name>
         3[W] + Intelligence modifier damage.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Hit: (Fortitude):</name>
         You can expend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your recovery value.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Miss:</name>
         You can expend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to half your recovery value.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Effect:</name>
         If you expended a healing surge, you gain a benefit depending on your Arcane Aegis class feature choice:
      </section>
      <section indent="1">
         <name>Aegis of Assault:</name>
         The attack you make as part of your <i>aegis of assault</i> class power deals additional damage until the end of your next turn. The additional damage equals one-half the number of healing surges you have expended (minimum +1).
      </section>
      <section indent="1">
         <name>Aegis of Ensnarement:</name>
         You gain a bonus to attack rolls against the target for attacks the target triggers by willingly moving before the end of your next turn. The bonus equals one-half the number of healing surges you have expended (minimum +1).
      </section>
      <section indent="1">
         <name>Aegis of Shielding:</name>
         Your <i>aegis of shielding</i> class power reduces additional damage until the end of your next turn. The additional reduction equals one-half the number of healing surges you have expended (minimum 1).
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Shatterblade</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>In the blink of an eye, your bonded weapon shatters into thousands of fragments that cut into your foes, and the weapon the reforms in your hand</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Weapon</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Requirement:</name>
         You must make this attack using your bonded weapon.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range>
         <target>one creature</target>
         Intelligence vs. AC and Reflex
      </section>
      <section auto="smage-both"/>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit (AC):</name>
         3[W] + Intelligence modifier damage.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Hit (Reflex):</name>
         Each creature adjacent to the target (other than you) takes damage equal to 2 + your Intelligence modifier + your weapon's enhancement bonus.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Miss (Both):</name>
         2 + your Intelligence modifier + your weapon's enhancement bonus damage.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Spikes of Agony</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>Your strike leaves shards of pure force piercing your enemy's flesh, rending it if it moves</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Force</keyword> <keyword>Weapon</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range>
         <target>one creature</target>
         Intelligence vs. AC and Fortitude
      </section>
      <section auto="smage-both"/>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit (AC):</name>
         3[W] force damage, or 3[W] + Intelligence modifier force damage if you also hit the target's Fortitude defense.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Hit (Fortitude):</name>
         2 + your Intelligence modifier + your weapon's enhancement bonus force damage if you didn't hit the target's AC.
      </section>
      <section>
         The first time the target moves before the start of your next turn, it takes force damage equal to 5 + your [Strength or Constitution] modifier + your weapon's enhancement bonus, or half this amount if the movement was forced movement.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Miss (Fortitude):</name>
         The first time the target willingly moves before the start of your next turn, it takes half the force damage.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Special (Aegis of Assault):</name>
         When you use your <i>aegis of assault</i> class power, you can use this attack in place of the <i>melee basic attack</i>.
      </section>
      <section>
         If you do, the damage when you hit AC is reduced by -1[W] and the force damage from movement happens the first time the target moves before the start of the currently acting creature's next turn.
      </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Watchful Strike</title>
      <class>Swordmage</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>As you strike your foe, you palce another foe under your aegis</fluff>
      <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Weapon</keyword>
      <section>
         <name>Prerequisite:</name>
         You must have the <i>arcane aegis</i> class power.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Attack:</name>
         <type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range>
         <target>one creature</target>
         Intelligence vs. AC
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Hit:</name>
         3[W] + Intelligence modifier damage.
      </section>
      <section>
         <name>Miss:</name>
         2 + your Intelligence modifier + your weapon's enhancement bonus damage if the target is marked by you.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         <name>Effect:</name>
         Choose one enemy within 5 squares of you other than the target. If the target is marked by your <i>arcane aegis</i>, you can choose one enemy within 10 squares instead.
      </section>
      <section shade="">
         The chosen enemy counts as being marked by your <i>arcane aegis</i> class power until the end of your next turn.
      </section>
   </power>

</catalog>
