<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
   <name>Artificer</name>
   <subname>Tinkerer</subname>
   <role>Leader</role>
   <source>Arcane</source>
   <shortfluff>Through the use of cryptic magical formulas and complex alchemical recipes, you channel arcane power into items that empower your allies and hinder your enemies</shortfluff>
   <keyability>Intelligence</keyability>
   <keyability>Constitution</keyability>
   <keyability>Wisdom</keyability>
   
   <proficiency>
      <type>Armor</type>
      <name>Cloth</name>
      <name>Leather</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Weapon</type>
      <name>Simple melee</name>
      <name>Simple ranged</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Implement</type>
      <name>Rod</name>
      <name>Staff</name>
      <name>Wand</name>
   </proficiency>
   
   <defense>
      <name>Fortitude</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
   <defense>
      <name>Will</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
   
   <hpbase>12</hpbase>
   <hpgain>5</hpgain>
   <surgebase>6</surgebase>
   
   <skills>
      <trained>Arcana</trained>
      <number>4</number>
   </skills>
   
   <fluff>Artificers treat mastery of magic like a technical skill. They see patterns in energy and matter, and they understand how to manipulate the flow of magic in and around objects and creatures. Artificers channel energy into items using magical components, diagrams, and complex chains of sigils. Their skills let them assemble a magic device for any situation.</fluff>
   <fluff>A Tinkerer, might be a formal student of magic who became interested in artifacts and arcane items or, alternatively, someone who devised magic tools in a musty basement. Or perhaps an explorer who found arcane knowledge in the forgotten places of the world. Whatever the source of his or her talents, a passion for the technical components of magic drives a Tinkerer to perfect his or her art.</fluff>
   <fluff>With a bandolier slung across his or her chest, an Artificer carries an arsenal of alchemical compounds, magic implements, mundane materials, and tools. His or her weapons, implements, and other gear are inscribed with runes and mystic patterns. A Tinkerer mixes reagents, drinks potions, and crafts items. Through the use of knowledge, an Artificer infuses himself or herself and his or her allies with arcane power. And one day, his or her magical skills will carry a Tinkerer into legend.</fluff>
   
   <feature>
      <title>Arcane Empowerment</title>
      <benefit>The study of magic has given Tinkerers the ability to manipulate the arcane energies contained within magical items. He or she can either make them strike true or to recharge their expended energy.</benefit>
      <benefit>When you finish an extended rest, you gain the ability to empower one item, and you gain an additional use of this ability each time you finish an encounter.</benefit>
   </feature>
</class>
