<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>

<catalog>
	<collection>Barbarian Lvl 1 Daily Attack Evocations</collection>

	<power>
		<title>Always Falling Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>The fury of the waterfall and the relentless push of water propels you past any defenses</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Always Falling Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You shift one-half your speed. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type><range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>2[W] + Strength modifier damage, and you knock the target prone. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
      <section shade="" auto="charge-special">When you do, you can shift up to one-half your speed instead of moving your speed as part of the charge. If you chose the alternative benefit, you can shift up to your speed.</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Always Falling Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you can use an opportunity reaction to shift 2 squares when an ally hits an enemy adjacent to you. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Additionally, on your turn you gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls against targets that were further away from you at the start of your turn than when you make the attack, and you knock such targets prone on a critical hit. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Bloodhunt Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>Your rage surges up from the depths of your pain to bring pain to the wounded</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Bloodhunt Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>If you or the target is bloodied, you reroll any 1s on your damage roll for this power until the result is something other than a 1. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type><range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>3[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 If the target is bloodied, you deal additional damage equal to your Constitution modifier. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Bloodhunt Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you gain a bonus equal to your Constitution modifier to the damage rolls of melee and close attacks with the <key>Weapon</key> keyword if either you or the target is bloodied. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 This stacks with the additional damage this power deals against a bloodied target. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Bloodseeker Drake Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>As you strike, flashes of spectral teeth and blood-red scales reveal the bloodseeker drake's spirit that inspires your rage</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Bloodseeker Drake Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>The attack roll bonus against a bloodied target is +4 instead of +2. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<indent>1</indent> <name/>
				 You gain a +2 bonus to attack if the target is bloodied 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>3[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Bloodseeker Drake Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls against bloodied targets. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, you can use an immediate interrupt to make a barbarian at-will attack against a bloodied enemy that shifts or provokes a <i>reactive strike</i>. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Blood Bear Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>You strike, then call on the spirit of the blood bear, drawing on its great strength and crushing grip to destroy your foes</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Blood Bear Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>The target takes 5 + your Strength modifier damage at the start of its turn if it is still grabbed by you. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type><range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>2[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Effect:</name>You grab the target and can maintain the grab with your weapon instead of a free hand if you wish. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Blood Bear Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you gain a +4 bonus to <i>grab</i> attack rolls and to checks and defenses against escape attempts. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Also, if an enemy starts its turn grabbed by you, it takes damage equal to 5 + your Strength modifier. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, you can use an immediate interrupt to negate forced movement against a creature you are grabbing or against you when you are grabbing a creature. You cannot do this if both you and the creature you are grabbing are subject to the same forced movement. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Fearsome Tyrant Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>Your blow is a prelude to a furious roar that turns your visage to that of unbridled berserker fury, causing your foes to recoil in terror</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Fear, Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Fearsome Tyrant Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You give each enemy adjacent to you a -2 penalty to attack rolls against you until the start of your next turn. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type><range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>2[W] + Strength modifier damage, and the target is dazed (save ends). 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage, and the target is dazed until the end of its next turn. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Fearsome Tyrant Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you can use the Fearsome Tyrant Roar action once per turn. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
		<aspect>
			<name>Fearsome Tyrant Roar</name>
			<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
			<keyword>Fear, Primal</keyword>
			<action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<name>Roar Target:</name><type>Close</type> <range>burst 1</range><target>each enemy in the burst</target>
			</section>
			<section shade="">
				<name>Effect:</name>
				 You push the target 1 square, and it takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls against you until the start of your next turn. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Life Thane Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>As you strike, raging energy boils out of you, healing you and invigorating your allies</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Life Thane Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You grant all allies within 3 squares of you temporary hit points equal to 3 + your Charisma modifier.  
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>2[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
			<section shade="">
				 <name>Effect:</name>You can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your healing surge value. 
			</section>
			<section shade="">
				 If you are bloodied, you regain additional hit points equal to your Charisma modifier. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Life Thane Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you activate an Aura 3 (<key>Primal</key>). 
         </section>
         <section shade="">
             Bloodied allies who start their turn in the aura gain temporary hit points equal to your Charisma modifier. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, you can use the Life Thane Recovery action. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
		<aspect>
			<name>Life Thane Recovery</name>
			<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
			<keyword>Healing, Primal</keyword>
			<action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
			<section auto="req-bloodied"/>
			<section personal=""/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Effect:</name>You spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your healing surge value. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Allies within the aura regain hit points equal to your Charisma modifier. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Macetail Behemoth Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>You knock your enemy to the ground with a slam like the behemoth's heavy tail, and the rage of the macetail fills you, refreshing you with every blow of your weapon</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Macetail Behemoth Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You knock all targets prone even on a miss. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Close</type> <range>weapon burst</range><target>each enemy in the burst you can see</target>
				 Strength vs. Reflex 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>1[W] + Strength modifier damage, and you knock the target prone. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Macetail Behemoth Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, when a barbarian attack allows you to push a target, you can halve the distance to knock the target prone. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, you gain temporary hit points equal to your Strength modifier each time you hit with a barbarian attack power. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 You gain an additional 5 temporary hit points if the target was already prone or was knocked prone by the attack. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Rage Drake Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>You slam your weapon into your wounded foe, and the rage drake's spirit fills you, causing you to erupt in violence and swing furiously at a new foe as soon as the last one falters</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Rage Drake Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You make a <i>melee basic attack</i> against a different target after resolving this power. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature, or two bloodied creatures</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>2[W] + Strength modifier damage, or 3[W] + Strength modifier damage if you targeted only one bloodied creature. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Rage Drake Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, once per turn when you bloody or reduce an enemy to 0 hit points or less, you can make a <i>melee basic attack</i> against a different target as a free reaction. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Savage Juggernaut Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>Your blow triggers an inner wrath that grows more and more unstoppable with each enemy you fell</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Savage Juggernaut Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You deal an additional +1[W] damage with this power. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>3[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Savage Juggernaut Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you gain a +1 bonus to damage. This bonus increases by +1 for each enemy you reduce to 0 hit points or less.  
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, you gain a +1 power bonus to attack rolls. This bonus increases by +1 for each nonminion enemy you reduce to 0 hit points or less. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Skulltaker Spirit Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>The ancient berserker spirit that drives this rage doesn't care that its presence tears you apart, just as long as it can crush the skulls of your enemies as they hide behind their cowardly defenses</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Skulltaker Spirit Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You ignore any cover or concealment the target has for this attack 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>3[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Skulltaker Spirit Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you take damage equal to your level at the start of each of your turns. This damage cannot be resisted or negated. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 You are immune to being marked. If you start your turn suffering from a condition or effect that prevents you from taking actions or from making an attack against any creatures, you take damage equal to your level and end any such effects on you. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, you gain a +2 bonus to all attack and damage rolls. You also ignore cover and concealment, including total concealment but not total cover, when using barbarian attack powers. 
			</section>
      <section shade="">If you hit a creature with a barbarian attack, until the end of your next turn, that creature can not gain combat advantage against you for hiding or flanking, or for being invisible.</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Stampeding Hooves Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>You hammer your enemy with a heavy blow as the spirits of stampeding beasts fill you with their strength</fluff>
			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Stampeding Hooves Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You move one-half your speed, including through enemies' spaces. You gain a +4 bonus to attack rolls until the end of your turn against enemies whose space you moved through. If you used this attack when charging, you gain a +2 bonus to speed for the charge instead of moving one-half your speed. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>3[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
			<section shade="" auto="charge-special">When you do, you can choose to move through the target's space as part of the charge even though this does not bring you closer to the target.</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Stampeding Hooves Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you can move through your enemies' spaces, though the movement provokes <i>reactive strikes</i> normally. If you charge, you can choose to move through the target's space as part of the charge even though this does not bring you closer to the target. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, you gain a +4 bonus to your first attack roll against enemies whose space you have moved through on the same turn. 
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

	<power>
		<title>Swift Panther Rage</title>
		<class>Barbarian</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
		<fluff>You slash your foe with fury as the spirit of the swift panther grants you its speed and agility</fluff>

			<frequency>Daily</frequency>
			<keyword>Primal, Rage, Weapon</keyword>
			<action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Rage:</name>You enter Swift Panther Rage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Alternative:</name>You shift 4 squares instead of 2 squares. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Effect:</name>You shift up to 2 squares. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
				 Strength vs. AC 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Hit:</name>3[W] + Strength modifier damage. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Miss:</name>Half damage. 
			</section>
		<aspect>
			<name>Swift Panther Rage</name>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 Until the rage ends or you change to a different rage, you gain a +2 bonus to speed and can shift up to 2 squares as a move action. 
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				 In addition, when a barbarian power allows you to move or shift, you can move or shift 1 additional square. This stacks with the bonus to speed when a power allows you to move or shift your speed.  
			</section>
		</aspect>
	</power>

</catalog>
