<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<name>Fighter</name>
	<subname>Weaponmaster</subname>
	<role>Defender</role>
	<source>Martial</source>
	<shortfluff>Tough and resilient, you use tactical cunning and battle prowess to contain the enemy and protect your allies.</shortfluff>
	<keyability>Strength</keyability>
	<keyability>Constitution</keyability>
	<keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
	<keyability>Wisdom</keyability>
	
	<proficiency>
		<type>Armor</type>
		<name>Cloth</name>
		<name>Leather</name>
		<name>Hide</name>
		<name>Chainmail</name>
		<name>Scale</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Shield</type>
		<name>Heavy</name>
		<name>Light</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Weapon</type>
		<name>Simple melee</name>
		<name>Military melee</name>
		<name>Simple ranged</name>
		<name>Military ranged</name>
	</proficiency>
	
	<defense>
		<name>Fortitude</name>
		<value>+2</value>
	</defense>
	
	<hpbase>15</hpbase>
	<hpgain>6</hpgain>
	<surgebase>9</surgebase>
	
	<skills>
		<trained>Acrobatics, Athletics or Endurance</trained>
		<number>3</number>
	</skills>
	
	<fluff>Into the blackest pits beneath the mountains, bent on vengeance and glory, goes the weaponmaster. These warriors form the iron core of any legion. They crash into the teeth of enemy forces, armed with cold steel and grim purpose. They are mercenaries loitering in taverns between expeditions, the guards who cast a watchful eye over their charges, the weapon masters who elevate fighting styles to lethal arts. The weaponmaster is a fearless warrior, ready to meet any challenge.</fluff>
	<fluff>Weaponmasters can be found just about anywhere and among any sort of people. A few are gallant warriors fighting for noble causes, while others are calculating mercenaries who draw their weapons only when the pay is right. All weaponmasters, however, are adventurers, ready to face any challenge, to go where glory, plunder, or honor leads them.</fluff>
	<fluff>Specialized combat maneuvers, or exploits, combined with a dedicated focus on a fighting style set weaponmasters apart from other fighters. A weaponmaster can slam his or her weapon through one enemy to crunch into another or carve a bloody path through enemies in a whirlwind of destruction. Weapons are crucial too, since weaponmasters know how to coax every advantage they can from their tools, and those who use axes fight differently from those who favor heavy blades.</fluff>
	<fluff>Weaponmasters develop their combat prowess in many different ways. Most have some elementary training to expose them to different weapons and armor. These trainees are often squires, militia, students, and soldiers. Once they're cut free, they grow their ability through practice and observation. Each battle proves instructive, giving the weaponmaster new insights that might develop into full-blown techniques.</fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Approach to Opportunities</name>
		<benefit>A weaponmaster is always ready to take advantage of any opportunities their enemies give. Depending on your style, you can choose to focus on either personal mobility or on stopping your enemies in their tracks.</benefit>
		<benefit>You gain your choice of either <![CDATA[<i>combat agility</i>]]> or <![CDATA[<i>combat superiority</i>]]>.</benefit>
		<include
			xlink:type="simple"
			xlink:href="FighterFeatures.xml#xpointer(title('Combat Agility'))"
			xlink:show="embed">
			Combat Agility
		</include>
		<!-- <include>
			<type>power</type>
			<file>FighterFeatures.xml</file>
			<title>Combat Superiority</title>
		</include> -->
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Combat Challenge</name>
		<benefit>In combat, it is dangerous to ignore a fighter. Every time you attack an enemy, whether the attack hits or misses, you can choose to mark that target until the end of your next turn.</benefit>
		<benefit>While the target is marked, it takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls of attacks that do not include you as a target. A creature can be subject to only one mark at a time, with a new mark superseding a mark that was already in place.</benefit>
		<benefit>In addition, you gain the <![CDATA[<i>enforce challenge</i>]]> power. If you are an eladrin, you can choose to gain the <![CDATA[<i>feywild enforcement</i>]]> power instead.</benefit>
		<!-- <include>
			<type>power</type>
			<file>FighterFeatures.xml</file>
			<title>Enforce Challenge</title>
		</include>
		<include>
			<type>power</type>
			<file>FighterFeatures.xml</file>
			<title>Feywild Enforcement</title>
		</include> -->
	</feature>
	
</class>
