<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <collection>Ranger Lvl 2 Utility Exploits</collection>

   <power>
      <title>Archer's Handholds</title>
      <class>Ranger</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>A line of arrows sticks to the wall where you point your bow</fluff>
      <keyword>Martial</keyword> <keyword>Weapon</keyword>
      <section><name>Requirement:</name>You must be wielding a Bow or Crossbow.</section>
      <section personal=""/>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>Choose up to 5 contiguous squares of a vertical surface within your weapon range. You expend two pieces of ammunition for each square chosen.</section>
      <section shade="">Until the end of the encounter, the DC to climb the chosen squares is reduced by your Dexterity modifier + your weapon's enhancement bonus. If the DC is reduced to less then 0, a character climbing the chosen squares automatically succeeds on the Athletics check.</section>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Avian Grace</title>
      <class>Ranger</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <frequency>Daily</frequency>
      <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>You don't know the secret of flight, but you have learned some lessons towards it</fluff>
      <keyword>Beast</keyword> <keyword>Martial</keyword>
      <section><name>Prerequisite:</name>You must have a raptor beast companion.</section>
      <section personal=""/>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you are considered to have a running start whenever you make a long jump.</section>
      <section shade="">Also, you gain a +2 power bonus to fly speed if you have it.</section>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Begin the Hunt</title>
      <class>Ranger</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <frequency>Daily</frequency>
      <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
      <fluff>You quickly identify your prey and ready yourself to attack it</fluff>
      <keyword>Martial</keyword>
      <section><name>Trigger:</name>You roll initiative</section>
      <section personal=""/>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>You gain a +2 bonus to the triggering initiative check.</section>
      <section shade="">After initiative has been rolled, you use your <![CDATA[<i>designate quarry</i>]]> class power against one creature you can see. You gain a +2 power bonus to attack rolls against that creature until it is no longer your quarry.</section>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Bending Branch</title>
      <class>Ranger</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
      <fluff>You resist a foe's attempt to move you, and like a great tree swaying in a storm, you snap back, ready to attack</fluff>
      <keyword>Martial</keyword>
      <section><name>Trigger:</name>You are pulled, pushed, or slid</section>
      <section personal=""/>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>You negate the triggering forced movement.</section>
      <section shade="">Also, you gain a +2 bonus to the first melee attack roll you make before the end of your next turn.</section>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Bridge of Roots</title>
      <class>Ranger</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <frequency>Daily</frequency>
      <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>The primal energy you draw from the ground calls forth a churning mass of great roots that can cover even the most dangerous ground</fluff>
      <keyword>Primal</keyword> <keyword>Zone</keyword>
      <section><type>Area</type><range>burst 2 within 10 squares</range></section>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>The burst creates a zone of massive roots until the end of the encounter. At least one square of the zone must be on a solid surface.</section>
      <section shade="">You and your allies can ignore difficult terrain and hindering terrain in the zone. Any portion of a pit, chasm, or similar terrain feature in the zone can be crossed safely.</section>
      <section shade="">While the zone remains, you can take the following action at-will:</section>
      <section shade="" indent="1"><name>Move Action:</name>You move the zone up to 5 squares. At least one square of the zone must remain on a solid surface during the move.</section>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Crucial Advice</title>
      <class>Ranger</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
      <fluff>You are wise in all things, making your friends safer and better off when they rely on you</fluff>
      <keyword>Martial</keyword>
      <section><name>Trigger:</name>An ally within range makes a skill check using a skill with which you have training; you must be able to see and hear the ally</section>
      <section><name>Target:</name><type>Ranged</type><range>5</range><target>the triggering ally</target></section>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>The triggering ally rerolls the triggering skill check with a power bonus equal to your Wisdom modifier.</section>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Entangling Roots</title>
      <class>Ranger</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <frequency>Daily</frequency>
      <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>Thick roots emerge from the ground in response to your command, and your foes stumble as they try to slip through them</fluff>
      <keyword>Primal</keyword> <keyword>Zone</keyword>
      <section><type>Area</type><range>burst 2 within 10 squares</range></section>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>The burst creates a zone of winding roots until the end of the encounter.</section>
      <section shade="">The ground in the zone is difficult terrain for your enemies. When an enemy charges, its movement cannot include any square of the ground in the zone.</section>
   </power>
</catalog>