<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Deva</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Immortal</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Immortal spirits who embody virtue, born and reborn to mortal life in the world</shortfluff>

	<height>6'1" - 6'6"</height>
	<weight>175 - 280</weight>

	<ability>Wisdom</ability>
	<ability>Intelligence</ability>
	<ability>Charisma</ability>
	<speed>7</speed>
	<vision>Normal</vision>

	<language>Common</language> <language>choice of two others</language>

	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
		<description>+2 History, +2 Religion</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Astral Majesty</name>
		<description>You have a +1 bonus to all defenses against attacks by bloodied creaturs.</description>
		<description>If you chose Charisma for your ability bonus, you also gain a +1 racial bonus to Will defense.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Astral Resistance</name>
		<description>You have resist necrotic and resist radiant equal to 5 + one-half your level.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Immortal Origin</name>
		<description>Your spirit is native to the Astral Sea, so your origin is immortal instead of natural.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Deva Racial Power</name>
		<description>You gain the <i>memory of a thousand lifetimes</i> racial power.</description>
	</trait>

	<fluff>Deep in the recesses of memory, devas recall what they once were: immortal servitors of the gods of good, spirits who chose to bind themselves to the world in mortal flesh. For millennia, their souls have been reborn to wage an endless war against the forces of darkness. Most devas are fiercely committed to the cause of good, because they fear what they might become if they turn to evil: A deva whose soul becomes corrupted risks being reborn as a rakshasa.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play an deva if you want: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to have dimly remembered connections to a thousand heroic lifetimes.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to embrace the cause of good and strive for perfection in all you do.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be a member of a race that favors the avenger, cleric, invoker, and wizard classes.
</fluff>

	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Memory of a Thousand Lifetimes</title>
			<class>Deva</class> <category>Utility</category>
			<fluff>The dreamlike memories of your previous lives lend insight to aid you</fluff>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
			<section>
				<name>Trigger:</name>You make an attack roll, a saving throw, a skill check, or an ability check and dislike the result</section>
			<section personal=""/>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name>Effect:</name>You add 1d6 the triggering attack roll, saving throw or check.</section>
		</power>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>In appearance, devas are very similar to humans, but with an unearthly beauty and an uncanny stillness about them. They are almost as tall as dragonborn, but much more slender.Devas' coloration distinguishes them most strongly from humans. All devas have patterns of light and dark colors on their skin. The light portions are chalk white or pale gray, and the dark areas range from blue or purple to dark gray or black. In any individual deva, either light or dark can be dominant, with the opposite shade appearing in simple, elegant patterns on the face, chest, and shoulders. A deva's hair is typically the same color as these skin patterns.</benefit>
		<benefit>When sitting or standing at rest, devas remain almost perfectly still, except for the occasional blink of the eyes. They don't fidget or twitch, and their eyes move only when they are actively examining something.</benefit>
		<benefit>Devas do not have children. When a deva dies, his or her spirit is reincarnated in a new, adult body that appears in some sacred place, such as a mountain peak, a riverbank, or a desert oasis. The new deva retains enough memory of past lives to speak and understand multiple languages and offer the proper prayers and sacrifices to the gods of good.</benefit>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Deva</name>
		<benefit>Devas are refined and polite. They follow the highest moral standards, but they are not afraid of violence. They believe that the pursuit of good is an eternal war with the forces of evil, embodied in rakshasas, demons, devils, and the evil gods and their servant angels. Devas wage that war in their hearts as well, constantly vigilant lest evil take root and corrupt their souls, transforming them into the creatures they most despise.</benefit>
		<benefit>Because they remember, at least dimly, a life in the Astral Sea spent in close company with the gods, most devas are devout worshipers of the gods of good, especially Bahamut but also Moradin and Pelor. Devas seek to achieve a personal connection with the gods rather than approach them through temples and priests. They worship at meals in their homes, setting an empty place for the absent gods, and strive through meditation and prayer to become more like the gods they serve. Deva adventurers are commonly avengers, clerics, and invokers, who savor the experience of divine power flowing through them without any intermediary.</benefit>
		<benefit>Devas do not have cities or societies of their own, and their numbers are so small that a deva can spend entire lifetimes without ever meeting another of his or her kind. They live among other races and, at least to some extent, adopt their ways. However, all devas remember elements of the life they had before their incarnation in flesh and the beginning of their cycle of rebirth, and they share some common cultural elements of dress, religion, and habits. Devas favor flowing clothes of fine silks, polished metal armor with winglike shoulder ornaments, and headdresses or helmets that suggest crowns or halos. In other ways, they prefer to live simply, without extravagance.</benefit> 

		<subfeature>
			<benefit><name>Deva Charasteristics:</name>Dedicated, devout, elegant, enlightened, introspective, mystical, refined, righteous, spiritual, thoughtful</benefit>
			<benefit><name>Male Names:</name>Adiah, Ansis, Ayab, Bavak, Beriah, Eben, Elyas, Galad, Gamal, Hiyal, Iannes, Kerem, Mahar, Marach, Mathas, Natan, Nehem, Oris, Raham, Ronen, Samel, Sered, Tavar, Vered, Zacha</benefit>
			<benefit><name>Female Names:</name>Abea, Adara, Asha, Chana, Danel, Darah, Davi, Elka, Eranah, Hania, Hava, Idria, Isa, Jael, Kana, Kayah, Lihi, Mahel, Marek, Navah, Noma, Paziah, Ravah, Riya, Sada, Shara, Tirah</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Sample Deva Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Galad, Deva Wizard</name>
			<benefit>Galad believes that the goal of his existence is to attain perfect knowledge of the universe. He believes that his arcane power is a manifestation of all he has learned throughout all his past lives.</benefit>
			<benefit>Perhaps in this life, or the next, he will achieve perfect mastery and become a demigod, freed from the cycle of reincarnation.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Eranah, Deva Invoker</name>
			<benefit>Eranah wields the power of Bahamut. Just as Bahamut warred with Tiamat when the world was young, Eranah believes that her calling in this incarnation is to fight against the evil dragons and dragonspawn that that pollute the world.</benefit>
			<benefit>Words of power resonate in Eranah's mind like an echo of the Platinum Dragon's voice when she invokes his wrath upon her enemies.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Raham, Deva Shaman</name>
			<benefit>Raham has embraced their life in the world, abandoning all thought of their previous astral existence.</benefit>
			<benefit>The primal spirits of the world are their patrons and allies, not the gods they left behind. They see their endless rebirth as part of the cycle of nature and have no desire to escape it.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A deva can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>

		<power>
			<title>Astral Shield</title>
			<class>Deva</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>You share a sliver of your astral soul to protect an ally</fluff>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<section>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name>
					<text>You must have the Astral Resistance racial trait.</text>
				</section>
				<section><name>Target:</name><type>Melee</type><range>touch</range><target>one ally</target></section>
				<section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, the target gains resist necrotic and resist radiant equal to your [Intelligence, Wisdom or Charisma] modifer + one-third your level.</section>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Draw from the Past</title>
			<class>Deva</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>Youd draw on all your past experiences to accomplish something you have not trained for in this life</fluff>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section><shade>true</shade><name>Effect:</name>Choose one skill you are not trained in.</section>
				<section><shade>true</shade>You are trained in the chosen skill until the end of the encounter.</section>
				<section><name>Special:</name>You can expend a healing surge to be trained until the end of your next extended rest instead.</section>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Empowered Memory</title>
			<class>Deva</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>When everything is on the line, you dig deep into your past lives</fluff>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<section>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name>
					<text>You must have the <i>memory of a thousand lifetimes</i> racial power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name>
					<text>You use your <i>memory of a thousand lifetimes</i> racial power and dislike the roll</text>
				</section>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name>
					<text>You reroll the triggering roll, and gain a +2 power bonus to the modified attack roll, saving throw or check. You must use the new result, even if it is lower.</text>
				</section>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Rejuvenating Majesty</title>
			<class>Deva</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>Your immortal soul flares, reinvigorating you and protecting you from weakened enemies</fluff>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Healing, Divine</keyword>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<section><name>Prerequisite:</name>You must have the Astral Majesty racial trait.</section>
				<section><name>Trigger:</name>A bloodied enemy hits or damages you with an attack</section>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name>
					<text>You can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your healing surge value.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Until the start of the currently acting creature's next turn, you have a +4 power bonus to all defenses against bloodied enemies.</text>
				</section>
		</power>
	</feature>

</race>
