<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="armortable.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <category selection="Light armor" />
   <category selection="Heavy armor" />
   <category selection="Shield" />

   <armor>
      <title>Cloth Armor</title>
      <category>Light armor</category>
      <bonus>0</bonus>
      <penalty></penalty>
      <speed></speed>
      <cost>1</cost>
      <weight>4</weight>

      <description>Jackets, mantles, woven robes, and padded vests don't, by themselves, provide any significant protection. However, you can imbue them with protective magic.</description>
      <description>Cloth armor doesn't slow you down or hinder your movement at all. All characters have proficiency with cloth armor.</description>
   </armor>

   <armor>
      <title>Leather Armor</title>
      <category>Light armor</category>
      <bonus>2</bonus>
      <penalty></penalty>
      <speed></speed>
      <cost>25</cost>
      <weight>15</weight>

      <description>Leather armor is sturdier than cloth armor. It protects vital areas with multiple layers of boiled-leather plates, while covering the limbs with supple leather that provides a small amount of protection.</description>
   </armor>

   <armor>
      <title>Hide Armor</title>
      <category>Light armor</category>
      <bonus>3</bonus>
      <penalty>1</penalty>
      <speed></speed>
      <cost>30</cost>
      <weight>25</weight>

      <description>Thicker and heavier than leather, hide armor is composed of skin from any creature that has a tough hide, such as a bear, a griffon, or even a dragon.</description>
      <description>Hide armor can bind and slightly hinder your precision, but it's light enough that it doesn't affect your speed.</description>
   </armor>

   <armor>
      <title>Chainmail</title>
      <category>Heavy armor</category>
      <bonus>6</bonus>
      <penalty>1</penalty>
      <speed>1</speed>
      <cost>40</cost>
      <weight>40</weight>

      <description>Metal rings woven together into a shirt, leggings, and a hood make up a suit of chainmail. Chainmail grants good protection, but it's cumbersome, so it reduces your mobility and agility.</description>
   </armor>

   <armor>
      <title>Scale Armor</title>
      <category>Heavy armor</category>
      <bonus>7</bonus>
      <penalty></penalty>
      <speed>1</speed>
      <cost>45</cost>
      <weight>45</weight>

      <description>Overlapping pieces of highly durable material, such as steel or full dragon scales, make up scale armor. Despite its heaviness, scale is surprisingly easy to wear; its straps and buckles make it adjustable and able to fit snugly on the body, allowing for flexibility and agility.</description>
   </armor>

   <armor>
      <title>Plate Armor</title>
      <category>Heavy armor</category>
      <bonus>8</bonus>
      <penalty>2</penalty>
      <speed>1</speed>
      <cost>50</cost>
      <weight>50</weight>

      <description>The heaviest of armor, made up of shaped plates of matal or similarly resilient material, plate provides the most armor protection. The cost for its superior fortification is mobility and agility.</description>
   </armor>

   <armor>
      <title>Light Shield</title>
      <category>Shield</category>
      <bonus>1</bonus>
      <penalty></penalty>
      <speed></speed>
      <cost>5</cost>
      <weight>6</weight>

      <description>While you're using a light shield, you can use your shield hand to hold another item, to climb, and the like, but you can't make attacks with that hand or with anything in it.</description>
   </armor>

   <armor>
      <title>Heavy Shield</title>
      <category>Shield</category>
      <bonus>2</bonus>
      <penalty>2</penalty>
      <speed></speed>
      <cost>10</cost>
      <weight>15</weight>

      <description>While you're using a heavy shield, you can't use your shield hand for any other task, since you must use that hand to handle the shield.</description>
   </armor>

</catalog>
