<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ritual.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <list selection="1" />
   <list selection="2" />
   <list selection="3" />
   <list selection="4" />
   <list selection="5" />
   <list selection="6" />
   <list selection="7" />
   <list selection="8" />
   <list selection="9" />
   <list selection="10" />
   <list selection="11" />
   <list selection="12" />
   <list selection="13" />
   <list selection="14" />
   <list selection="15" />
   <list selection="16" />
   <list selection="17" />
   <list selection="18" />
   <list selection="19" />
   <list selection="20" />
   <list selection="21" />
   <list selection="22" />
   <list selection="23" />
   <list selection="24" />
   <list selection="25" />
   <list selection="26" />
   <list selection="27" />
   <list selection="28" />
   <list selection="29" />
   <list selection="30" />

   <ritual>
      <title>Aberrant Totemic Link</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>13</level>
      <fluff>You cloak your mind with the eerie energies of the Far Realm and reach out to an aberrant creature to draw information from it</fluff>

      <price>3,200</price>
      <skill>Dungeoneering</skill>
      <component>350</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>1 day or until discharged</duration>

      <line>When you master this ritual, you choose a single type of aberrant creature, such as chaos beast or mind flayer. This choice remains fixed through your adventuring career. If you are able to create ritual scrolls, any scrolls you create also reflect this choice. This ritual can only be mastered once.</line>
      <line>For the ritual's duration, you are able to determine the presence or absence of creatures of the chosen type within 10 miles, but with no specific direction or distance information. If there are any within range, you can connect to the mind of a random creature of that type and try to gain information from it. You must expend a healing surge to make this connection (and to conceal it from the aberrant creature).</line>
      <line>Your Dungeoneering check result determines how many questions you can try to find the answers to. Once you have asked all the questions allowed by the ritual, the ritual ends.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Dungeoneering Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>9 or lower:</i>]]> One question</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10 - 19:</i>]]> Two questions</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> Three questions</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> Four questions</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> Five questions</line>
      <line>Your questions can be as specific or as general as you wish, but the answers you receive back are cryptic and rarely longer than a phrase, a short sentence, or a single image. In particular, aberrant creatures often have different conceptions of time, so questions regarding future events or plans are more likely to result in answers that are incomprehensible. The answers are also limited to what the individual creature knows, and its information could be incorrect if it has been misled by others.</line>
      <line>If a particual creature does not know the information you seek, you can try to find another individual who does know it. If there is another creature of the chosen type, you can expend a healing surge to connect (and conceal) to that creature, and re-ask any questions for which you received no answer.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> Members of the Morphic Web can master and perform this ritual even if they cannot normally master rituals. They also do not expend a healing surge to make the first connection.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Adjure</title>
      <category>Binding</category>
      <level>16</level>
      <fluff>Filled with righteous authority, you order and immortal entity to serve you</fluff>

      <price>7,500</price>
      <skill>Religion</skill>
      <component>2,000</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Until discharged</duration>

      <line>You command an immortal creature whose level does not exceed yours. The subject of this ritual must be able to see and hear you and must remain within 5 squares of you for the entire time necessary to perform the ritual. Because most creatures do not willingly submit to this ritual, you must usually make the creature helpless or restrain the creature by means of a <![CDATA[<i>magic circle</i>]]> ritual. Unless it is prevented from doing so, the creature can leave at any time. Finally, you must be able to communicate with the creature, or the ritual automatically fails.</line>
      <line>To determine the extent of your authority over the subject, you engage in a special skill challenge during the time it takes to perform the ritual. The DC for all checks is a Moderate DC of the subject's level, and the primary skill is Religion; each time you or an ally succeeds on a Religion check in the challenge, you or an ally can use Diplomacy, History, Arcana, or Intimidate for the next attempted check. Attempting an Intimidate check increases the DC of Diplomacy checks by +5 for the rest of the skill challenge.</line>
      <line>Once you have amassed 3 failures or achieved 10 successes, the skill challenge ends. Consult the following values and apply the effect for the number of successes you achieved:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Number of Successes</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>0 or 1:</i>]]> The creature has authority over you and can issue one command that you must obey, a task that requires up to a day of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>2 or 3:</i>]]> You have immediate authority over the creature and can command it to perform one task that takes no more than 5 minutes.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>4 or 5:</i>]]> You have moderate authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a day of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>6 or 7:</i>]]> You have significant authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a week of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>8 or 9:</i>]]> You have great authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a month of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10:</i>]]> You have ultimate authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a year an a day of effort.</line>
      <line>When the specified task is completed, the ritual is discharged, and the creature (or you) is released from service.</line>
      <line>The requested task can be any kind that does not compel the subject to obey multiple commands, force the subject to engage in combat, or ensure the subject's death (the subject can engage in combat to achieve a task if it wishes, but combat cannot be required). If the task is impossible, such as commanding a creature that cannot fly to soar into the sky, the creature can ignore the command.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Affect Normal Fire</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Fire leaps and dances at your command, brightening or dimming</fluff>

      <price>100</price>
      <skill>Arcane or Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>15</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>8 hours</duration>

      <line>You gain mastery over nonmagical fire. For the duration of the ritual, or until you take an extended rest, you can manipulate nonmagical flames within 10 squares of you as a minor action.</line>
      <line>You can make a fire that normally proves only dim light produce an equal amount of bright light and dim light up to twice the distance, or you can double the radius of light produced by a fire that produces both bright and dim light.</line>
      <line>Alternatively, you can diminish a fire's light, reducing its bright light to dim light and dim light to darkness. Reducing a fire's light does not extinguish the flame.</line>
      <line>You can also extinguish 1 square of nonmagical fire as a minor action, or expand nonmagical fire into 1 adjacent square that has sufficient fuel for the fire.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Alarm</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You scribe runes around an area's perimiter to warn of unauthorized entry</fluff>

      <price>40</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>set of focuses, and 5</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>8 hours or until discharged</duration>

      <line>You ward an area up to 10 squares by 10 squares, and designate a spoken password that allows a creature to enter the warded area without triggering an alarm. This alarm can send a mental signal to you or make an audible ringing sound.</line>
      <line>If a Tiny or larger creature enters the warded area without speaking the password, the alarm you set triggers, and the ritual is discharged. However, an insubstantial creature or any creature that succeeds on a Stealth check against your passive Arcana does not trigger the alarm.</line>
      <line>The result of triggering the alarm depends on the type of alarm:</line>
      <line indent="1">When an audible alarm triggers, all creatures in the warded area that are capable of hearing can hear the ringing. If they are sleeping, the noise awakens them.</line>
      <line indent="1">When a mental alarm triggers, a mental ping alerts you to the intrusion and awakens you from sleep.</line>
      <line>In either case, the alarm informs you where the warded area was breached.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A tiny bell (5 gp), and a fine silver wire (5 gp); you hold the bell and use the wire to scribe runes on the warded area's perimeter.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Amanuensis</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You touch the writing, tracing each character or glyph with a gently glowing crystal; as you do so, the words flicker into existence one the specially prepared parchment before solidifying into a near-perfect copy</fluff>

      <price>20</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 5</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Permanent</duration>

      <line>You capture the writing from one source (such as a book, scroll, or tablet) and cause it to appear onto a specially prepared paper, parchment, book, or some other similar item. This ritual copies up to 250 words of text, enough to fill one page with text. A copied illustration counts as a number of words proportional to the amount of the page the illustration requires.</line>
      <line>This ritual can be used to copy a ritual scroll, even if you have not mastered the ritual on the original scroll. Creating a ritual scroll in this way costs the normal amount for creating a ritual scroll, in addition to the component cost for this ritual, and takes a quarter of the time in addition to the time spent to perform this ritual.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Analyze Portal</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>8</level>
      <fluff>Scintillating motes of color sparkle inside the portal and from their patterns and movements you discern its secrets</fluff>

      <price>800</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>200</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>

      <line>When you perform this ritual, choose a specific active and permanent portal you can clearly see. This ritual causes the portal to erupt with faint lights that flicker and spin, letting you learn a great deal about its destination and function.</line>
      <line>The most basic effect of the ritual is to reveal the portal's destination. Although a portal usually displays what its destination looks like, this ritual reveals the destination's name and its general location in the world or the plane on which it is located.</line>
      <line>If you learn the origin and type of the last creature to use the portal, you also learn any keywords associated with that creature.</line>
      <line>The ritual can also reveal the identity of the creature that created the portal. If the portal was not created by a creature, you learn of the event that formed it.</line>
      <line>The information you learn depends on your Arcana check result. You learn all the information for your result and lower.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Arcana Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>29 or lower:</i>]]> The name of the portal's destination.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 or higher:</i>]]> The origin and type of the creature to use the portal last.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 + one-half the creator's level:</i>]]> Identity of the creature that created the portal, if any.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual in 10 minutes instead of 1 hour.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
     <title>Ancestral Whispers</title>
     <category>Divination</category>
     <level>6</level>
     <fluff>You commune with the ancestral spirits, seeking their wisdom and experience to aid your cause</fluff>

     <price>300</price>
     <skill>Religion (no check)</skill>
     <component>At least 100</component>
     <time>1 hour</time>
     <duration>24 hours</duration>

     <line>You invite the spirit of an ancestor to inhabit your body for a time. Choose one skill in which you are not trained. For the ritual's duration, you are considered trained in that skill.</line>
     <line>The greater the hero who calls the spirit, the more power required of the called spirit, and thus greater the cost. The component cost of this ritual increases to 600 gp for an 11th-level caster, to 3 000 gp for a 16th-level caster, 15 000 gp for a 21st-level caster, and to 60 000 for a 26th-level caster.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to halve the component cost of this ritual.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
     <title>Animal Friendship</title>
     <category>Binding</category>
     <level>5</level>
     <fluff>You speak to an animal, convincing it to help you with simple tasks</fluff>

     <price>220</price>
     <skill>Nature</skill>
     <component>45</component>
     <time>1 minute</time>
     <duration>Special</duration>

     <line>You target a nonhostile Tiny natural beast, such as a cat, a fox, a fish, a mouse, or a sparrow. The animal must remain within 5 squares of you for the time necessary to perform the ritual.</line>
     <line>Once the ritual is complete, the animal regards you have as friend and performs simple tasks on your behalf. The tasks are limited ot the options below,  and assigning a task requires standard action.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<i>Fetch:</i>]]> The animal retrieves a Tiny ofject of 10 pounds or less that you and it can see. If the animal is unable to carry the object due to the item's size or weight, the animal enlists the aid of other creatures of its kind to fulfill the task.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<i>Perform:</i>]]> The animal performs a simple trick, such as rollin over or playing dead.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<i>Seek:</i>]]> The animal scouts ahead and examines an area for anything that's alive or animate. The animal can travel up to 20 squares away, and uses your Passive Perception value to determine if it notices hidden creatures in the area. When the animal returns, you learn whether a creature occupies the area. The animal cannot communicate any other information aside from the presence or absence of creatures.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<i>Watch:</i>]]>The animal remains in its current location and watches the area. When you assing the animal the task, you designate creatures that are allowed to enter the location. If a creature that you have not designated enters the location, the watching animal informs you by coming to you and making a noise. If you move more than 20 squares away from the area, the animal leaves its post and rejoins you.</line>
     <line>Unless otherwise commanded, the animal accompanies you for the duration of the ritual, perching on your shoulder, hiding in your pocket, or walking alongside you.</line>
     <line>The animal has AC 14, Fortitude 12, Reflex 12, and Will 12. It is a minion with 3 hit points.</line>
     <line>Your Nature check check determines the length of time the animal remains in your servitude, but you can release an animal from your service as a minor action.</line>
     <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check Result</b>]]></line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 1 hour</line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 8 hours</line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 1 day</line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 1 week</line>
     <line>You can have one animal at a time bound to your service using this ritual. Starting at 11th level, you can have two animals bound, and starting at 21st level, you can have three animals bound. You must complete a separate ritual for each animal you bind.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Animal Messenger</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You whisper to the animal before you, and it bounds off in the direction you point to carry your message</fluff>

      <price>30</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 5</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>

      <line>You target a nonhostile Tiny animal, such as a sparrow, a raven, a fox, or a carp. The animal must remain within 5 squares of you for the time necessary to perform the ritual.</line>
      <line>Once the ritual is complete, you whisper a message of up to 25 words to the animal and name a recipient and a location. The animal bounds off towards the location, in search of the recipient. The animal avoids danger along its path. Upon finding the recipient, the animal approaches until it is adjacent to the recipient, and your whisper issues from the animal's mouth, conveying the message.</line>
      <line>When the animal delivers its message or the ritual's duration ends, your influence ends and the animal reverts to its natural behavior. Your Nature check determines how long the animal is affected by the ritual:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 6 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 12 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 18 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 24 hours</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
     <title>Animate Rope</title>
     <category>Exploration</category>
     <level>2</level>
     <fluff>Under your commands, a rope moves around almost like a snake under your hypnosis</fluff>

     <price>80</price>
     <skill>Arcana or Nature (no check)</skill>
     <component>1 healing surge, a focus, and 5</component>
     <time>1 minute</time>
     <duration>10 minutes</duration>

     <line>The rope you use as the focus for this ritual gains the ability to move and tie itself under your command. To command the rope, you must have line of sight and line of effect to it, and the rope must be within 20 squares of you. You have the following options:</line>
     <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Move Action:</b>]]> The rope either moves, coils up, uncoils, or does a similar action.</line>
     <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Standard Action:</b>]]> The rope ties a knot, forms a tied loop, or does a similar action.</line>
     <line>The rope as a speed of 6, and a climb speed of 6. The animated rope cannot carry or pull any weight as it moves.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A rope of any length.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
     <title>Anthem of Unity</title>
     <category>Binding</category>
     <level>8</level>
     <fluff>The anthem's invigorating notes fill the audience with pride and single-minded purpose</fluff>

     <price>600</price>
     <skill>Diplomacy</skill>
     <component>a focus, and 120</component>
     <time>10 minutes</time>
     <duration>Special</duration>
     <bard />

     <line>When you perform this anthem to a crowd of ordinary people -peasants, commoners, artisans, and the like- you unite them behind a single cause. Only creatures whose leve is at least 2 lower than yours are affected by this ritual.</line>
     <line>The crowd must not be hostile to you and must be able to see and hear you for the entire performance. At the end of the ritual, you can request a single service from the crowd, to which the members of the audience respond as if you were a trusted friend: you can request anything that doesn't involve violence, put the listener at inordinate risk or imperil their friends or family, or place them in financial ruin. For example, you might ask the listeners to help you put out a fire raging in the city, hide you and your allies from searching guards, or provide you with shelter or food.</line>
     <line>Your Diplomacy check determines the scope of help you can request.</line>
     <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Diplomacy Check Result</b>]]></line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> The listeners perform an action that lasts up to 1 hour and that benefits them in at least some small way.</line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> The listeners perform a task that lasts up to 1 hour and that poses no risk or reward to them.</line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> The listeners perform a task that lasts up to 6 hours and that poses a mild risk but at least some benefit to them.</line>
     <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> The listeners perform a task that lasts up to 1 dau and that poses a mild risk without any benefit to them.</line>
     <line>The number of individuals affected depends extends to anyone who witnesses the entire performance, so the larger the venue, the more people you can affect.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A musical instrument or similar item worth at least 600 gp.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual in 1 minute.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
     <title>Arcane Barrier</title>
     <category>Warding</category>
     <level>12</level>
     <fluff>You create a translucent wall, seemingly impenetrable to brute force</fluff>

     <price>3 000</price>
     <skill>Arcana</skill>
     <component>750</component>
     <time>10 minutes</time>
     <duration>4 hours</duration>

     <line>You create a magical barrier that is up to 2 squares long and tall, typically large enough to block a doorway or the entrance of a hallway. The obstruction is imperceptible from more than 10 squares away, but is readily apparent as a translucent, shimmering, paper-thin wall from closer than that.</line>
     <line>When creating the barrier, you also determine circumstances that open the barrier; this is the same as for the <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]> ritual. Your Arcana check result + 5 is the DC for <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> or similar rituals to open the barrier, and the DC to burst the barrier with a Strength check is +5 greater than that.</line>
     <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to cast this ritual as a standard action. If you do, the duration is reduced to 10 minutes, the component cost is reduced to 200 gp, and you do not gain the +5 bonus to the DC to open the barrier.</line>
     <line>If you spend 4 hours and four times the component costs to perform this ritual, the duration increases to permanent. A ritual caster who uses <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> or a similar ritual to open a permanent barrier can choose to bring it down temporary, in which case it seals again after 5 minutes, or to destroy the barrier.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Arcane Mark</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Onto the object's surface you etch a glowing rune, which shimmers for a moment before fading, marking the item as your own</fluff>

      <price>20</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>3</component>
      <time>5 minutes</time>
      <duration>Permanent</duration>

      <line>You set your personal arcane mark on an object. It manifests as a unique sigil of your devising.</line>
      <line>After the first moment, it is invisible and can be seen only by a creature using Arcana to detect magic. Ritual casters use arcane marks to identify their property and sometimes to designate places of great import.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Banish Vermin</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Minor preparation is all it takes to ward against pests</fluff>

      <price>30</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>5</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>

      <line>You ward a singe zone, up to burst 5, to be unpleasant to all kinds of unwanted rodents and insects of size Tiny or smaller, even if they are part of a swarm. Any vermin that are in the burst must leave by the most expedient means possible, and none enter the affected area for a period determined by your Nature check result:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>9 or lower:</i>]]> 3 days</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10 - 19:</i>]]> 1 week</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 2 weeks</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 or higher:</i>]]> 1 month</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Brew Potion</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Liquids brew and bubble, coalescing the raw substance of magic into a form you can drink</fluff>

      <price>50</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Religion (no check)</skill>
      <component>At least 20</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Permanent (consumed)</duration>

      <line>You create a common potion, elixir, or similar common item of your level or lower. The ritual's component cost is equal to the price of the item you create.</line>
      <line>You can create uncommon, rare, or unique potions, elixirs, and similar items if your DM allows it. In some cases, this might require you to discover how to create a specific item, or acquire special components.</line>
   </ritual>
</catalog>
