<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ritual.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <list selection="1" />
   <list selection="2" />
   <list selection="3" />
   <list selection="4" />
   <list selection="5" />
   <list selection="6" />
   <list selection="7" />
   <list selection="8" />
   <list selection="9" />
   <list selection="10" />
   <list selection="11" />
   <list selection="12" />
   <list selection="13" />
   <list selection="14" />
   <list selection="15" />
   <list selection="16" />
   <list selection="17" />
   <list selection="18" />
   <list selection="19" />
   <list selection="20" />
   <list selection="21" />
   <list selection="22" />
   <list selection="23" />
   <list selection="24" />
   <list selection="25" />
   <list selection="26" />
   <list selection="27" />
   <list selection="28" />
   <list selection="29" />
   <list selection="30" />

   <ritual>
      <title>Alarm</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You scribe runes around an area's perimiter to warn of unauthorized entry</fluff>

      <price>40</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>set of focuses, and 5</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>8 hours or until discharged</duration>

      <line>You ward an area up to 10 squares by 10 squares, and designate a spoken password that allows a creature to enter the warded area without triggering an alarm. This alarm can send a mental signal to you or make an audible ringing sound.</line>
      <line>If a Tiny or larger creature enters the warded area without speaking the password, the alarm you set triggers, and the ritual is discharged. However, an insubstantial creature or any creature that succeeds on a Stealth check against your passive Arcana does not trigger the alarm.</line>
      <line>The result of triggering the alarm depends on the type of alarm:</line>
      <line indent="1">When an audible alarm triggers, all creatures in the warded area that are capable of hearing can hear the ringing. If they are sleeping, the noise awakens them.</line>
      <line indent="1">When a mental alarm triggers, a mental ping alerts you to the intrusion and awakens you from sleep.</line>
      <line>In either case, the alarm informs you where the warded area was breached.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A tiny bell (5 gp), and a fine silver wire (5 gp); you hold the bell and use the wire to scribe runes on the warded area's perimeter.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Amanuensis</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You touch the writing, tracing each character or glyph with a gently glowing crystal; as you do so, the words flicker into existence one the specially prepared parchment before solidifying into a near-perfect copy</fluff>

      <price>20</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 5</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Permanent</duration>

      <line>You capture the writing from one source (such as a book, scroll, or tablet) and cause it to appear onto a specially prepared paper, parchment, book, or some other similar item. This ritual copies up to 250 words of text, enough to fill one page with text. A copied illustration counts as a number of words proportional to the amount of the page the illustration requires.</line>
      <line>This ritual can be used to copy a ritual scroll, even if you have not mastered the ritual on the original scroll. Creating a ritual scroll in this way costs the normal amount for creating a ritual scroll, in addition to the component cost for this ritual, and takes a quarter of the time in addition to the time spent to perform this ritual.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Animal Messenger</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You whisper to the animal before you, and it bounds off in the direction you point to carry your message</fluff>

      <price>30</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 5</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>

      <line>You target a nonhostile Tiny animal, such as a sparrow, a raven, a fox, or a carp. The animal must remain within 5 squares of you for the time necessary to perform the ritual.</line>
      <line>Once the ritual is complete, you whisper a message of up to 25 words to the animal and name a recipient and a location. The animal bounds off towards the location, in search of the recipient. The animal avoids danger along its path. Upon finding the recipient, the animal approaches until it is adjacent to the recipient, and your whisper issues from the animal's mouth, conveying the message.
      <line>When the animal delivers its message or the ritual's duration ends, your influence ends and the animal reverts to its natural behavior. Your Nature check determines how long the animal is affected by the ritual:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check Result</b>]]>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 6 hours</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 12 hours</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 18 hours</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 24 hours</line>
   </ritual>
</catalog>
