<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ritual.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <list selection="1" />
   <list selection="2" />
   <list selection="3" />
   <list selection="4" />
   <list selection="5" />
   <list selection="6" />
   <list selection="7" />
   <list selection="8" />
   <list selection="9" />
   <list selection="10" />
   <list selection="11" />
   <list selection="12" />
   <list selection="13" />
   <list selection="14" />
   <list selection="15" />
   <list selection="16" />
   <list selection="17" />
   <list selection="18" />
   <list selection="19" />
   <list selection="20" />
   <list selection="21" />
   <list selection="22" />
   <list selection="23" />
   <list selection="24" />
   <list selection="25" />
   <list selection="26" />
   <list selection="27" />
   <list selection="28" />
   <list selection="29" />
   <list selection="30" />

   <ritual>
      <title>Aberrant Totemic Link</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>13</level>
      <fluff>You cloak your mind with the eerie energies of the Far Realm and reach out to an aberrant creature to draw information from it</fluff>

      <price>3,200 gp</price>
      <skill>Dungeoneering</skill>
      <component>350 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>1 day or until discharged</duration>

      <line>When you master this ritual, you choose a single type of aberrant creature, such as chaos beast or mind flayer. This choice remains fixed through your adventuring career. If you are able to create ritual scrolls, any scrolls you create also reflect this choice. This ritual can only be mastered once.</line>
      <line>For the ritual's duration, you are able to determine the presence or absence of creatures of the chosen type within 10 miles, but with no specific direction or distance information. If there are any within range, you can connect to the mind of a random creature of that type and try to gain information from it. You must expend a healing surge to make this connection (and to conceal it from the aberrant creature).</line>
      <line>Your Dungeoneering check result determines how many questions you can try to find the answers to. Once you have asked all the questions allowed by the ritual, the ritual ends.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Dungeoneering Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>9 or lower:</i>]]> One question</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10 - 19:</i>]]> Two questions</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> Three questions</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> Four questions</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> Five questions</line>
      <line>Your questions can be as specific or as general as you wish, but the answers you receive back are cryptic and rarely longer than a phrase, a short sentence, or a single image. In particular, aberrant creatures often have different conceptions of time, so questions regarding future events or plans are more likely to result in answers that are incomprehensible. The answers are also limited to what the individual creature knows, and its information could be incorrect if it has been misled by others.</line>
      <line>If a particual creature does not know the information you seek, you can try to find another individual who does know it. If there is another creature of the chosen type, you can expend a healing surge to connect (and conceal) to that creature, and re-ask any questions for which you received no answer.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> Members of the Morphic Web can master and perform this ritual even if they cannot normally master rituals. They also do not expend a healing surge to make the first connection.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Adjure</title>
      <category>Binding</category>
      <level>16</level>
      <fluff>Filled with righteous authority, you order and immortal entity to serve you</fluff>

      <price>7,500 gp</price>
      <skill>Religion</skill>
      <component>2,000 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Until discharged</duration>

      <line>You command an immortal creature whose level does not exceed yours. The subject of this ritual must be able to see and hear you and must remain within 5 squares of you for the entire time necessary to perform the ritual. Because most creatures do not willingly submit to this ritual, you must usually make the creature helpless or restrain the creature by means of a <![CDATA[<i>magic circle</i>]]> ritual. Unless it is prevented from doing so, the creature can leave at any time. Finally, you must be able to communicate with the creature, or the ritual automatically fails.</line>
      <line>To determine the extent of your authority over the subject, you engage in a special skill challenge during the time it takes to perform the ritual. The DC for all checks is a Moderate DC of the subject's level, and the primary skill is Religion; each time you or an ally succeeds on a Religion check in the challenge, you or an ally can use Diplomacy, History, Arcana, or Intimidate for the next attempted check. Attempting an Intimidate check increases the DC of Diplomacy checks by +5 for the rest of the skill challenge.</line>
      <line>Once you have amassed 3 failures or achieved 10 successes, the skill challenge ends. Consult the following values and apply the effect for the number of successes you achieved:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Number of Successes</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>0 or 1:</i>]]> The creature has authority over you and can issue one command that you must obey, a task that requires up to a day of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>2 or 3:</i>]]> You have immediate authority over the creature and can command it to perform one task that takes no more than 5 minutes.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>4 or 5:</i>]]> You have moderate authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a day of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>6 or 7:</i>]]> You have significant authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a week of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>8 or 9:</i>]]> You have great authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a month of effort.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10:</i>]]> You have ultimate authority over the creature and can command it to perform a task that requires up to a year an a day of effort.</line>
      <line>When the specified task is completed, the ritual is discharged, and the creature (or you) is released from service.</line>
      <line>The requested task can be any kind that does not compel the subject to obey multiple commands, force the subject to engage in combat, or ensure the subject's death (the subject can engage in combat to achieve a task if it wishes, but combat cannot be required). If the task is impossible, such as commanding a creature that cannot fly to soar into the sky, the creature can ignore the command.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Affect Normal Fire</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Fire leaps and dances at your command, brightening or dimming</fluff>

      <price>100 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>15 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>8 hours</duration>

      <line>You gain mastery over nonmagical fire. For the duration of the ritual, or until you take an extended rest, you can manipulate nonmagical flames within 10 squares of you as a minor action.</line>
      <line>You can make a fire that normally proves only dim light produce an equal amount of bright light and dim light up to twice the distance, or you can double the radius of light produced by a fire that produces both bright and dim light.</line>
      <line>Alternatively, you can diminish a fire's light, reducing its bright light to dim light and dim light to darkness. Reducing a fire's light does not extinguish the flame.</line>
      <line>You can also extinguish 1 square of nonmagical fire as a minor action, or expand nonmagical fire into 1 adjacent square that has sufficient fuel for the fire.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Alarm</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You scribe runes around an area's perimiter to warn of unauthorized entry</fluff>

      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>set of focuses, and 5 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>8 hours or until discharged</duration>

      <line>You ward an area up to 10 squares by 10 squares, and designate a spoken password that allows a creature to enter the warded area without triggering an alarm. This alarm can send a mental signal to you or make an audible ringing sound.</line>
      <line>If a Tiny or larger creature enters the warded area without speaking the password, the alarm you set triggers, and the ritual is discharged. However, an insubstantial creature or any creature that succeeds on a Stealth check against your passive Arcana does not trigger the alarm.</line>
      <line>The result of triggering the alarm depends on the type of alarm:</line>
      <line indent="1">When an audible alarm triggers, all creatures in the warded area that are capable of hearing can hear the ringing. If they are sleeping, the noise awakens them.</line>
      <line indent="1">When a mental alarm triggers, a mental ping alerts you to the intrusion and awakens you from sleep.</line>
      <line>In either case, the alarm informs you where the warded area was breached.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A tiny bell (5 gp), and a fine silver wire (5 gp); you hold the bell and use the wire to scribe runes on the warded area's perimeter.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Amanuensis</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You touch the writing, tracing each character or glyph with a gently glowing crystal; as you do so, the words flicker into existence one the specially prepared parchment before solidifying into a near-perfect copy</fluff>

      <price>20 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 5 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Permanent</duration>

      <line>You capture the writing from one source (such as a book, scroll, or tablet) and cause it to appear onto a specially prepared paper, parchment, book, or some other similar item. This ritual copies up to 250 words of text, enough to fill one page with text. A copied illustration counts as a number of words proportional to the amount of the page the illustration requires.</line>
      <line>This ritual can be used to copy a ritual scroll, even if you have not mastered the ritual on the original scroll. Creating a ritual scroll in this way costs the normal amount for creating a ritual scroll, in addition to the component cost for this ritual, and takes a quarter of the time in addition to the time spent to perform this ritual.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Analyze Portal</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>8</level>
      <fluff>Scintillating motes of color sparkle inside the portal and from their patterns and movements you discern its secrets</fluff>

      <price>800 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>200 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>

      <line>When you perform this ritual, choose a specific active and permanent portal you can clearly see. This ritual causes the portal to erupt with faint lights that flicker and spin, letting you learn a great deal about its destination and function.</line>
      <line>The most basic effect of the ritual is to reveal the portal's destination. Although a portal usually displays what its destination looks like, this ritual reveals the destination's name and its general location in the world or the plane on which it is located.</line>
      <line>If you learn the origin and type of the last creature to use the portal, you also learn any keywords associated with that creature.</line>
      <line>The ritual can also reveal the identity of the creature that created the portal. If the portal was not created by a creature, you learn of the event that formed it.</line>
      <line>The information you learn depends on your Arcana check result. You learn all the information for your result and lower.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Arcana Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>29 or lower:</i>]]> The name of the portal's destination.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 or higher:</i>]]> The origin and type of the creature to use the portal last.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 + one-half the creator's level:</i>]]> Identity of the creature that created the portal, if any.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual in 10 minutes instead of 1 hour.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Ancestral Whispers</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You commune with the ancestral spirits, seeking their wisdom and experience to aid your cause</fluff>

      <price>300 gp</price>
      <skill>Religion (no check)</skill>
      <component>At least 100 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>

      <line>You invite the spirit of an ancestor to inhabit your body for a time. Choose one skill in which you are not trained. For the ritual's duration, you are considered trained in that skill.</line>
      <line>The greater the hero who calls the spirit, the more power required of the called spirit, and thus greater the cost. The component cost of this ritual increases to 600 gp for an 11th-level caster, to 3 000 gp for a 16th-level caster, 15 000 gp for a 21st-level caster, and to 60 000 for a 26th-level caster.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to halve the component cost of this ritual.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Animal Friendship</title>
      <category>Binding</category>
      <level>5</level>
      <fluff>You speak to an animal, convincing it to help you with simple tasks</fluff>

      <price>220 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>45 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>Varies</duration>

      <line>You target a nonhostile Tiny natural beast, such as a cat, a fox, a fish, a mouse, or a sparrow. The animal must remain within 5 squares of you for the time necessary to perform the ritual.</line>
      <line>Once the ritual is complete, the animal regards you as friend and performs simple tasks on your behalf. The tasks are limited ot the options below,  and assigning a task requires standard action.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Fetch:</i>]]> The animal retrieves a Tiny ofject of 10 pounds or less that you and it can see. If the animal is unable to carry the object due to the item's size or weight, the animal enlists the aid of other creatures of its kind to fulfill the task.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Perform:</i>]]> The animal performs a simple trick, such as rollin over or playing dead.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Seek:</i>]]> The animal scouts ahead and examines an area for anything that's alive or animate. The animal can travel up to 20 squares away, and uses your Passive Perception value to determine if it notices hidden creatures in the area. When the animal returns, you learn whether a creature occupies the area. The animal cannot communicate any other information aside from the presence or absence of creatures.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Watch:</i>]]>The animal remains in its current location and watches the area. When you assing the animal the task, you designate creatures that are allowed to enter the location. If a creature that you have not designated enters the location, the watching animal informs you by coming to you and making a noise. If you move more than 20 squares away from the area, the animal leaves its post and rejoins you.</line>
      <line>Unless otherwise commanded, the animal accompanies you for the duration of the ritual, perching on your shoulder, hiding in your pocket, or walking alongside you.</line>
      <line>The animal has AC 14, Fortitude 12, Reflex 12, and Will 12. It is a minion with 3 hit points.</line>
      <line>Your Nature check check determines the length of time the animal remains in your servitude, but you can release an animal from your service as a minor action.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 1 hour</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 8 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 1 day</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 1 week</line>
      <line>You can have one animal at a time bound to your service using this ritual. Starting at 11th level, you can have two animals bound, and starting at 21st level, you can have three animals bound. You must complete a separate ritual for each animal you bind.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Animal Messenger</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You whisper to the animal before you, and it bounds off in the direction you point to carry your message</fluff>

      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge or 10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Varies</duration>

      <line>You target a nonhostile Tiny animal, such as a sparrow, a raven, a fox, or a carp. The animal must remain within 5 squares of you for the time necessary to perform the ritual.</line>
      <line>Once the ritual is complete, you whisper a message of up to 25 words to the animal and name a recipient and a location. The animal bounds off towards the location, in search of the recipient. The animal avoids danger along its path. Upon finding the recipient, the animal approaches until it is adjacent to the recipient, and your whisper issues from the animal's mouth, conveying the message.</line>
      <line>When the animal delivers its message or the ritual's duration ends, your influence ends and the animal reverts to its natural behavior. Your Nature check determines how long the animal is affected by the ritual:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 6 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 12 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 18 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 24 hours</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Animate Rope</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>2</level>
      <fluff>Under your commands, a rope moves around almost like a snake under your hypnosis</fluff>

      <price>80 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, a focus, and 5 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>The rope you use as the focus for this ritual gains the ability to move and tie itself under your command. To command the rope, you must have line of sight and line of effect to it, and the rope must be within 20 squares of you. You have the following options:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Move Action:</b>]]> The rope either moves, coils up, uncoils, or does a similar action.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Standard Action:</b>]]> The rope ties a knot, forms a tied loop, or does a similar action.</line>
      <line>The rope as a speed of 6, and a climb speed of 6. The animated rope cannot carry or pull any weight as it moves.</line>
      <line>If the rope is within your possession and undamaged when the ritual ends, you regain the healing surge you paid as a component cost.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A rope of any length.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Anthem of Unity</title>
      <category>Binding</category>
      <level>8</level>
      <fluff>The anthem's invigorating notes fill the audience with pride and single-minded purpose</fluff>

      <price>600 gp</price>
      <skill>Diplomacy</skill>
      <component>a focus, and 120 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>
      <bard />

      <line>When you perform this anthem to a crowd of ordinary people -peasants, commoners, artisans, and the like- you unite them behind a single cause. Only creatures whose leve is at least 2 lower than yours are affected by this ritual.</line>
      <line>The crowd must not be hostile to you and must be able to see and hear you for the entire performance. At the end of the ritual, you can request a single service from the crowd, to which the members of the audience respond as if you were a trusted friend: you can request anything that doesn't involve violence, put the listener at inordinate risk or imperil their friends or family, or place them in financial ruin. For example, you might ask the listeners to help you put out a fire raging in the city, hide you and your allies from searching guards, or provide you with shelter or food.</line>
      <line>Your Diplomacy check determines the scope of help you can request.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Diplomacy Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> The listeners perform an action that lasts up to 1 hour and that benefits them in at least some small way.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> The listeners perform a task that lasts up to 1 hour and that poses no risk or reward to them.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> The listeners perform a task that lasts up to 6 hours and that poses a mild risk but at least some benefit to them.</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> The listeners perform a task that lasts up to 1 dau and that poses a mild risk without any benefit to them.</line>
      <line>The number of individuals affected depends extends to anyone who witnesses the entire performance, so the larger the venue, the more people you can affect.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A musical instrument or similar item worth at least 600 gp.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual in 1 minute.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Arcane Barrier</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>12</level>
      <fluff>You create a translucent wall, seemingly impenetrable to brute force</fluff>

      <price>3,000 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>750 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>4 hours</duration>

      <line>You create a magical barrier that is up to 2 squares long and tall, typically large enough to block a doorway or the entrance of a hallway. The obstruction is imperceptible from more than 10 squares away, but is readily apparent as a translucent, shimmering, paper-thin wall from closer than that.</line>
      <line>When creating the barrier, you also determine circumstances that open the barrier; this is the same as for the <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]> ritual. Your Arcana check result + 5 is the DC for <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> or similar rituals to open the barrier, and the DC to burst the barrier with a Strength check is +5 greater than that.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to cast this ritual as a standard action. If you do, the duration is reduced to 10 minutes, the component cost is reduced to 200 gp, and you do not gain the +5 bonus to the DC to open the barrier.</line>
      <line>If you spend 4 hours and four times the component costs to perform this ritual, the duration increases to permanent. A ritual caster who uses <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> or a similar ritual to open a permanent barrier can choose to bring it down temporarily, in which case it seals again after 5 minutes, or to destroy the barrier.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Arcane Lock</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>4</level>
      <fluff>You bind a door so that intruders can't easily pass - the door is limned with amber light which fades to a soft glow, marking it as impassible to anyone other than you amd your companions</fluff>
      
      <price>100 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>20 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Permanent</duration>
      
      <line>You lock a door, a window, a gate, a portcullis, or some other means of ingress. You can open the target normally, but those who don't have your permission find it locked.</line>
      <line>Your passive Arcana check result, with a +5 power bonus, sets the DC for Thievery checks or Strength checks made to open the target.</line>
      <line>When you perform the ritual, you can allow for certain other creatures or types of creatures to pass through the door normally, ignoring the ward's effect. You can choose any or all (or none) of the following options:</line>
      <line indent="1">><![CDATA[<i>Password:</i>]]> You can set a verbal password. If uttered within 5 squares of the target, the speaker can ignore the ward for one minute.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Individuals:</i>]]> You can designate up to ten other specific individuals who can ignore the ward at all times. You can cast the ritual again on the same target to add further individuals each time.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Descriptions:</i>]]> You can describe one or more categories of creatures who can ignore the ward at all times, using specific, observable characteristics such as species, type, size, or equipment carried or worn.</line>
      <line>The ward remains until you dismiss it as a standard action, the ingress is destroyed, or the ward is defeated, such as with the <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> ritual, or a successful Strength check or Thievery check. Wherever you are, you instantly know if your <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]> is defeated.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Arcane Mark</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Onto the object's surface you etch a glowing rune, which shimmers for a moment before fading, marking the item as your own</fluff>

      <price>20 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>3 gp</component>
      <time>5 minutes</time>
      <duration>Permanent</duration>

      <line>You set your personal arcane mark on an object. It manifests as a unique sigil of your devising.</line>
      <line>After the first moment, it is invisible and can be seen only by a creature using Arcana to detect magic. Ritual casters use arcane marks to identify their property and sometimes to designate places of great import.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Aria of Revelation</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>10</level>
      <fluff>Your operatic notes spark new ideas, helping your allies overcome a challenging problem</fluff>

      <price>750 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>A focus, and 300 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
      <bard />

      <line>When you finish performing this ritual, each ally who heard it can make an Arcana check, a Dungeoneering check, a History check, a Nature check, or a Religion check to uncover a clue or recall a bit of useful information. The ally must be trained in the skill.</line>
      <line>Your Arcana check result determines the power bonus that the allies gain to their check.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Arcana Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> +5 power bonus</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> +7 power bonus</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> +10 power bonus</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> +12 power bonus</line>
      <line>The information learned is equivalent to a successful knowledge check or monster knowledge check, as usual.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A musical instrument worth at least 400 gp, which you play as part of performing the ritual.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual as your minor action, move action, and standard action during a single turn. If you do, the component cost and the power bonus are halved.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Astral Guide</title>
      <category>Binding</category>
      <level>14</level>
      <fluff>A mote of white light coalesces before you, prepared to guide you through the Astral Sea</fluff>

      <price>1 900 gp</price>
      <skill>Religion</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 500 gp</component>
      <time>30 minutes</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>
      <requirement>You can only perform this ritual in the Astral Sea.</requirement>

      <line>You summon a fragment of divine essence to guide you. The guide sheds bright light in a radius of 8 squares, and it lacks a physical form and cannot be harmed in any way.</line>
      <line>As part of this ritual, you name a specific, fixed destination in the Astral Sea. The most common use of this ritual is to lead its user to a particular astral dominion. However, the astral guide could also lead you to the exit of a labyrinth, the entrance to a dungeon, or to a specific site within an astral dominion. The guide cannot lead you to a general location, such as "a room with astral diamonds" or to an unknown place, like "the place where the death knight Malachi is hiding." If the named location does exist within the Astral Sea, the guide leads you there by the shortest (though not always the safest) route.</line>
      <line>The guide hovers in the air and moves at your speed. It remains within 12 quares of you. The guide remains until you reach your destination, the ritual's duration expires, or you take an extended rest.</line>
      <line>Your Religion check result determines the duration of the ritual.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Religion Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 30 minutes</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 1 hour</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 4 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 16 hours</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Astral Sojourn</title>
      <category>Travel</category>
      <level>15</level>
      <fluff>With each word of the ritual, the world around you grows fainter, until finally it vanishes altogether, and you find yourself floating in the silvery void of the Astral Sea</fluff>

      <price>3,500 gp</price>
      <skill>Religion</skill>
      <component>At least 700 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>
      <requirement>You can only perform this ritual in the world.</requirement>

      <line>When you perform this ritual, you transport yourself and up to eight allies to a random spot in the Astral Sea.</line>
      <line>Creatures that travel the Astral Sea using this ritual have a faint silver nimbus surrounding them, which coalesces into a ghostly silver cord trailing a few inches from the neck. The manifestation of the cord represents the traveler's connection to the location from which they departed the world.</line>
      <line>If you or one of your affected allies leaves the Astral Sea, such as by stepping through a portal to another place, then the ritual ends and all participants return to the location from which they departed the world. At the end of the ritual's duration, or upon the death of the ritual caster, the participants also return to the location from which they departed the world.</line>
      <line>The ritual caster can choose to end the ritual at any time. This requires 10 minutes, has no cost or skill check, and instantly returns all participants to the world. A participant always returns to the same location from which he or se departed the world.</line>
      <line>Your Religion check result determines how long the ritual's participants can remain in the Astral Sea</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Religion Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 3 days</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 7 days</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 21 days</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 1 year</line>
      <line>The component cost for this ritual is 700 gp, plus 300 gp for each traveller beyond the ritual caster.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> Travellers in addition to the ritual caster can expend a healing surge to halve the increased component cost from him or her.</line>
      <line>The ritual caster can expend a healing surge to end the ritual in 1 minute instead of 10 minutes.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Aura Mask</title>
      <category>Deception</category>
      <level>8</level>
      <fluff>Before your eyes, the wondrous object shimmers briefly and then returns to an apparently mundane state - though you know the truth of its power and value, to others it appears normal in every way</fluff>

      <price>250 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours (see optional focus)</duration>

      <line>When performed upon a magic item, this ritual makes it appear nonmagical when someone tries to use an Arcana check to detect magic. Your Arcana check result determines the DC for the Arcana check to see through your deception. This makes the Arcana check DC to determine that an item is magical the higher of the item's normal DC or the result of your Arcana check made as part of this ritual.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Optional Focus:</b>]]> You can extend the duration of this ritual indefinitely by leaving the affected item near a small, jeweled eye of gold and ruby wrappen in a silken blindfold. The blindfolded eye is a focus worth 100 gp. As long as the item remains within 20 squares of the focus, the ritual's duration does not expire. You can hide or protect the focus in any way you like, as long as it remains within range.</line>
      <line>A single focus can maintain up to five <![CDATA[<i>aura mask</i> or <i>false aura</i>]]> rituals on five separate items, as long as they are all close enough to the focus.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Aura of True Vision</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>15</level>
      <fluff>With the last wods of the ritual and a wave of your ring, you banish invisibility</fluff>

      <price>5,000 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>focus</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>30 minutes</duration>

      <line>The ritual activates and Aura 5 (Arcane) for the ritual's duration, centered on the creature wearing the ring used as the focus for this ritual.</line>
      <line>Invisible creatures and objects in the aura become visible and cannot become invisible again while they remain in the aura.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b> A <i>ring of true seeing</i>]]>.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Banish Illusions</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>11</level>
      <fluff>What was hidden is now revealed</fluff>

      <price>1,500 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>480 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>

      <line>You ward a single zone, up to burst 4, against illusions. Any invisible creature within the area or that enters the area becomes visible. In addition, Illusion powers used within or targeting someone inside the area take a -2 penalty to attack rolls and checks, and creatures inside the area have a +5 power bonus on checks to see through illusions, and a +2 power bonus to saving throws against Illusion effects.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual in 10 minutes, but the duration is reduced to 1 hour.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Banish Vermin</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Minor preparation is all it takes to ward against pests</fluff>

      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>5 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>

      <line>You ward a single zone, up to burst 5, to be unpleasant to all kinds of unwanted rodents and insects of size Tiny or smaller, even if they are part of a swarm. Any vermin that are in the burst must leave by the most expedient means possible, and none enter the affected area for a period determined by your Nature check result:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>9 or lower:</i>]]> 3 days</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10 - 19:</i>]]> 1 week</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 2 weeks</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 or higher:</i>]]> 1 month</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Battlefield Elocution</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>3</level>
      <fluff>With your voice magically amplified, every soul in the army standing before you can hear your words</fluff>

      <price>100 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Religion (no check)</skill>
      <component>20 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>
      <bardAffinity />

      <line>You gain the ability to speak so that all creatures within 100 squares with a DC 0 Perception check can hear you. Only words you desire to be heard so broadly are. For some ritual casters, this spell makes their voices loud as thunder; others' voices ring in people's ears without crossing the intervening space.</line>
      <line>As long as the ritual's duration persists, you or another creature under the effect can use a minor action to touch a willing creature and transfer the power to that creature.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual as a standard action.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Beast Growth</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>4</level>
      <fluff>The beast grows to incredible size and exhibits tremendous strength</fluff>

      <price>150 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>50 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>8 hours</duration>

      <line>A nonhostile Small or larger natural beast, such as a dog, horse, camel, or elephant, remain within 5 squares of you while you perform this ritual. Upon the ritual's completion, the creature's size increases by one category.</line>
      <line>This change does not alter the beast's statistics, though its Strength is considered 8 higher for the purposes of determining how much the creature can carry, drag, or lift. In addition, the beast gains a +4 power bonus to Strength checks (but not Strength-based attack rolls or damage rolls).</line>
      <line>The ritual's effect ends if the beast dies, at which point it reverts to its normal size.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Bloom</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>2</level>
      <fluff>Grass grows, trees bear fruit, and the land's bounty is available to all</fluff>

      <price>80 go</price>
      <skill>Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>15 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>

      <line>Upon completion of the ritual, you cause all outdoor terrain within 20 squares of you to bloom with new growth and foliage. The entire area becomes difficult terrain.</line>
      <line>Alternatively, the ritual causes crops and fruit-bearing plants within 20 squares of you to yield food. The plants produce enough food to feed five people for a week.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to reduce the component cost to 5 gp.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
   <title>Bolster Object</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>6</level>
      <fluff>Though it looks no different, the iron portcullis has become harder than steel thanks to this ritual</fluff>
      
      <price>250 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Nature</skill>
      <component>100 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
      
      <line>You target an object you must touch during the casting of this ritual. An object can only benefit from one casting of this ritual, keeping the best result.</line>
      <line>The target's current and maximum hit points increase by 10% for each 5 points of your check result. For example, if your check result is 23, the hit points increase by 40%</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Breach Disguise</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>5</level>
      <fluff>The recipient of this ritual can feel their their intuition grow, especially as it comes to people pretending to be what they are not</fluff>
      
      <price>220 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>20 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>
      
      <line>You grant either yourself or an ally present during the casting of the ritual the ability to discern when a creature appears as something other than what it truly is.</line>
      <line>The target gains a +3 power bonus to checks to discern disguises or alternative form, and can use his or her Arcana check modifier in place of his or her Insight check modifier.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Brew Potion</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Liquids brew and bubble, coalescing the raw substance of magic into a form you can drink</fluff>

      <price>50 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Religion (no check)</skill>
      <component>At least 20 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Permanent (consumed)</duration>

      <line>You create a common potion, elixir, or similar common item of your level or lower. The ritual's component cost is equal to the price of the item you create.</line>
      <line>You can create uncommon, rare, or unique potions, elixirs, and similar items if your DM allows it. In some cases, this might require you to discover how to create a specific item, or acquire special components.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Call Wilderness Guide</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>6</level>
      <fluff>The spirit of an animal native to the local wilderness answers you call, approaching you and then turning away and looking over its shoulder to make sure you're following</fluff>
      
      <price>250 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>50 gp</component>
      <time>30 minutes</time>
      <duration>Varies</duration>
      
      <line>You call a nature spirit into your service to act as a guide. The guide takes the form of a Medium or smaller natural beast, and is treated as a minion of your level with defenses equal to yours at the time of performing this ritual. It has a speed or fly speed, as appropriate to its form, of 8, though it measures its pace to so your group can keep up.</line>
      <line>The guide leads you to a location you name as you perform the ritual. The destination must be a specific place, such as a unique natural formation or specific city. The guide cannot lead you to a general location, such as "a cave full of treasure", or to an unknown place, such as the secret lair of a dragon. For the duration of the ritual, the guide leads you to the destination by the shortest (although not necessarily the safest) route.</line>
      <line>Your Nature check result determines how long the guide serves you. If you can't reach the destination within the allotted time, the guide leads you as far as it can along the way and then disappears.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> 1 hour</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 4 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 8 hours</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 16 hours</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Call of Friendship</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>4</level>
      <fluff>Your song calls to a person's heart, filling it with feelings of kinship, affection, and perhaps even love</fluff>
      
      <price>150 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>a focus, plus 10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Varies</duration>
      <bard />
      
      <line>You target one nonhostile natural humanoid creature that is at least 2 level lower than you. The target must remain within 10 squares of you and hear the entire performance.</line>
      <line>Once you finish casting the ritual, make a Diplomacy check to determine the effect it has on the target. Once the ritual's duration ends, the target's attitude returns to normal. The ritual does not affect the target's memory in any way.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Diplomacy Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> The target acts as a friend for 1 hour, assisting you as he or she can, but takes no actions that put him or her in danger or that requires an expense of more than 5 gp</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> The target acts as a friend for 1 hour, assisting you as he or she can, but takes no actions that put him or her in danger or that requires an expense of more than 25 gp</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> The target acts as a friend for 6 hours, assisting you as he or she can, but takes no actions that put him or her in danger or that requires an expense of more than 50 gp</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> The target acts as a friend for 1 day, assisting you as he or she can, but takes no actions that put him or her in danger or that requires an expense of more than 500 gp</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A musical instrument worth at least 50 gp you play as part of performing the ritual.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to ignore the focus.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Calm Emotions</title>
      <category>Deception</category>
      <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You weave this ritual among your speech, giving magical weight to your words</fluff>
      
      <price>120 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Religion (no check)</skill>
      <component>2 healing surges</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>
      <bardAffinity />
      
      <line>When you complete this ritual, nonhostile humanoid creatures within 10 squares of you become calm and reasonable, though you can exclude any creatures from the ritual's effects as you wish.</line>
      <line>For the ritual's duration, Bluff checks, Diplomacy checks, and other similar checks to influence the affected creatures gain a +2 power bonus. The effect immediately ends on a creature if takes part on combat.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Chamber of Vulnerability</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>20</level>
      <fluff>You slowly exhale, watching as the destructive energy of your breath weapon swirls about before sinking into the world, as if absorbed by the world</fluff>
      
      <price>20,000 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>3,500 gp</component>
      <time>30 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours (see optional focus)</duration>
      <requirement>You must possess an innate breath weapon</requirement>
      
      <line>You ward an area so that creatures in it gain vulnerable to the damage type you deal with your breath weapon, such as fire damage if you are a red dragon. If you deal multiple types of damage or can choose between different types of damage, you choose one of them when performing this ritual.</line>
      <line>Your Arcana check result determines both the size of the warded area, and the vulnerable that affected creatures gain.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Arcana Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> burst 3, vulnerable 5</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> burst 5, vulnerable 5</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> burst 8, vulnerable 10</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> burst 12, vulnerable 10</line>
      <line>You are not affected by your own <![CDATA[<i>chamber of vulnerability</i>]]>. In addition, you can designate any number of ritual participants as not being affected. When performing the ritual, you can also designate one or more categories of creatures that are not affected by the ritual. You can designate these categories by obvious physical characteristics (such as height, weight, or body shape), creature type or subtype (such as humanoid, magical beast, kobold, or dragon), creature race (such as red dragon), or obvious equipment (such as creatures wearing a specific signet ring).</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Optional Focus:</b>]]> You can extend the duration of this ritual indefinitely by keeping a focus in the vicinity. This ritual focus is a small fanged mouth carved of ivory and silver, worth 2,000 gp. The ritual lasts as long as the focus remains within the warded area. You can hide or protect the ritual focus in any way you like, as long as it remains within the area.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Chameleon's Cloak</title>
      <category>Deception</category>
      <level>10</level>
      <fluff>No one can notice you or your friends thanks to the concealing cloak of magic you have conjured</fluff>
      
      <price>800 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>150 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>
      
      <line>You conceal yourself and up to 8 allies within 5 squares of you, using a combination of camouflage and distraction to ensure that no one notices any of you while you stay in place.</line>
      <line>The Perception DC to notice a creature concealed by this ritual is equal to 10 + your Arcana check modifier or your Nature check modifier, with a +5 power bonus. A concealed creature that leaves the space it occupies at the completion of the ritual or that attacks a creature loses all benefit from the ritual.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to cast this ritual as a standard action. If you do, the duration is reduced to 1 hour, and the component cost is reduced to 30 gp.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Comprehend Language</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>As you finish the ritual, the guttural language of the creatures before you clarifies into something you understand</fluff>

      <price>50 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>
      <bardAffinity />

      <line>When beginning the ritual, choose a language you have heard or a piece of writing you have seen within the past 24 hours.</line>
      <line>Using this ritual on a language you have heard allows you to understand it when spoken for the duration of the ritual and, if your Arcana check result is 35 or higher, to speak the language fluently for the duration.</line>
      <line>Using this ritual on a language you have seen as a piece of writing allows you to read the language for the duration and, if your Arcana chek result is 35 or higher, to write the language in its native script or in any other script you know for the duration.</line>
      <line>Using this ritual on a language you have both heard and seen as a piece of writing within the past 24 hours allows you to understand it in both forms for the duration of the ritual, and an Arcana check result of 35 or higher alows you to speak and write the language.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual as a standard action, but you must be currently hearing the language and the duration is reduced to 4 hours.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Comrades' Succor</title>
      <category>Restoration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Participants of this ritual share their vitality and luck with one another</fluff>

      <price>120 gp</price>
      <skill>Heal</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 5 gp</component>
      <time>5 minutes</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>

      <line>While performing this ritual, you and up to 5 participants can exchange healing surges.</line>
      <line>A character can choose any number of their existing healing surges to lose, and then choose another participant to gain that number of healing surges. No participant can have more healing surges than his or her daily maximum, healing surges given in excess of this amount are wasted.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> The healing surge part of this ritual's component cost can be paid by the ritual caster or one of the participants.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Conceal Dragonmark</title>
      <category>Deception</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Before your eyes, the complex marking fades from view</fluff>

      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Until broken</duration>

      <line>You conceal a dragonmark on either yourself or on an adjacent willing creature. Creatures that examine the area where the mark is hidden are entitled to a Perception check against your Arcana check result to notice the deception.</line>
      <line>When the affected creature uses any powers or effects related to the dragonmark, this ritual's effect is broken and it ends.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Create Campsite</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>A crackling fire, a hot meal, and a warm bedroll await you after a long day of adventuring</fluff>

      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>8 hours</duration>

      <line>You summon numerous diminutive nature spirits to assemble a campsite in a 5-square radius around you. The spirits clear the area, set up tents, unroll bedrolls, gather water, and prepare a nourishing meal. They also conceal the campsite, with your Nature check result serving as the DC for Perception checks to notice the hidden camp.</line>
      <line>The spirits utilize you and your allies' gear to make he campsite as necessary, allowing you to benefit from any relevant equipment. If you and your allies lack the appropriate gear, the spirits gather raw materials from the environment to make the campsite.</line>
      <line>At the end of the ritual's duration, the spirits break down the campsite, pack up your gear, and restore the site to its original state, removing evidence that you and your allies camped there. The Perception DC to notice the previous campsite is +5 higher than the DC to notice it when it was in use.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Create Holy Water</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>The sparkling water you create seems proof against all impurities</fluff>

      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Religion (no check)</skill>
      <component>At least 20 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Permanent (consumed)</duration>

      <line>This ritual infuses astral radiance into a small quantity of ordinary water. The ritual's component cost is equal to the cost of the holy water you create. You cannot create holy water of a level higher than your own.</line>
      <line>Aside from its effect on undead and demons, holy water act as normal pure water in all ways. It can be distinguished from normal water with examination and a successful DC 15 Religion or Arcana check.</line>
      <line>Holy water created with this ritual deals +1 damage per damage die.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Dancing Lights</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You conjure ghostly lights that float around at your peck and call</fluff>

      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>10 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You create up to four floating orbs or light, or one light of vaguely humanoid shape. These lights can be of any color of your choosing. Each orb sheds bright light in a 2-square radius and dim light for a further 2 squares; a humanoid light sheds dim light in a 2-square radius.</line>
      <line>Each light has a flight speed of 10. Whever you use a move action to move, you can move all the lights as part of that action. You can also use a minor action to move all your lights up to their speed. You must have line of effect to a light to move it. Any light goes out of it is more than 20 squares from you at the end of your turn.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to ignore the component cost.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Dowsing Rod</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You find a gnarled branch, and it turns as you hold it, point the way to a natural feature</fluff>

      <price>50 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>5 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>12 hours or until discharged</duration>

      <line>You transform a stick or other natural object into dowsing rod. When you do so, name a natural feature of the environment, such as mountains, rivers, forests, or caves. The dowsing rod points the way to the nearest place that fits the description.</line>
      <line>You can't name a specific place, such as Mount Baneflame or a cave used as a bandit hideout, and the rod can't find magically concealed locations. When you reach the destination, the ritual is discharged.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Erudite Conversion</title>
      <category>Restoration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Taking a moment to breathe and concentrate intently on your powers, you convert arcane energy into restorative one</fluff>
      
      <price>80 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>At least 5 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
      
      <line>Favored by ritual casters accustomed to long battles and constant warfare, this ritual allows an individual to convert powerful spells into healing reserves.</line>
      <line>The component cost for this ritual is equal to 5 gp, plus a number of gp equal to one-half your level.</line>
      <line>After performing this ritual, you sacrifice any number of your unused daily arcane powers, and regain an equal number of expended healing surges. This does not allow you to exceed your normal daily maximum number of healing surges.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b> In the Forgotten Realms setting, this ritual is known as <i>Simbul's conversion</i>]]>, as the ritual was developed by the Simbul and taught to her apprentices.</line>
   </ritual>

   <ritual>
      <title>Explorer's Fire</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You enchant a fire so that it isn't visible from more than a short distace, in the hope that it won't attract unwanted attention</fluff>

      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Nature</skill>
      <component>5 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>8 hours</duration>

      <line>You alter one fire of bonfire size or smaller within 5 squares of you. Light cast by the fire cannot be seen from more tha 5 squares from the fire, regardless of how much light it casts.</line>
      <line>The fire's light is unchanged, and the ritual does not diminish or contain the fire's heat or sounds. Putting out the fire ends the ritual.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Fastidiousness</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You are clean, and you would like to remain so, even while digging through grime for lost treasures</fluff>
      
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana, Nature or Religion (no check)</skill>
      <component>2 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>
      
      <line>You or a creature within 2 squares of you is warded against becoming dirty.</line>
      <line>No matter what the target does, touches, walks through, or experiences, the target's person, clothes, and carried possessions are not soiled. If the target is in any way soiled when the ritual is completed, that filth is immediately shed.</line>
      <line>Attacks or other effects that involve dirtying the character work as normal, but leave no lasting waste or residue.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Gentle Repose</title>
      <category>Restoration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Your practiced hands perform the ritual fast enough to preserve the body for a later restoration</fluff>
      
      <price>50 gp</price>
      <skill>Heal (no check)</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge, and 2 gp</component>
      <time>1 hour</time>
      <duration>Special</duration>
      
      <line>You perform this ritual on an adjacent corpse.</line>
      <line>The ritual quintuples the time the target corpse can lie dead and still be affected by <![CDATA[<i>raise dead</i>]]> or a similar ritual.</line>
      <line>The target corpse is also protected from being raised as an undead creature for 150 days.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Glib Limerick</title>
      <category>Deception</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You recite a short rhyme and feel your tongue loosen so the lies can flow freely</fluff>
      
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>a focus, and 5 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>
      <bard />
      
      <line>For the ritual's duration, whenever you make a Bluff check, you can roll twice and use either result. The ritual's effect immediately ends when you roll Initiative.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A musical instrument, worth at least 5 gp, that you play as part of performing the ritual.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Hold Portal</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>With a quick word and sigils drawn on a door, you seal it magically</fluff>
      
      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>1 healing surge</component>
      <time>1 standard action</time>
      <duration>10 minutes or until discharged</duration>
      
      <line>You magically hold shut one nonmagical door, gate, window, shutter, or similar device.</line>
      <line>Your Arcana check sets the DC for the Strength check or Thievery check needed to force the held portal open, which discharges the ritual.</line>
      <line>A creature with training in the Arcana skill can instead make an Arcana check against the same DC to discharge the spell.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend an additional healing surge to be able to affect a magical door, gate, or similar device.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Magic Mouth</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>The stone wall grinds as it reshapes into the semblance of dry, cracked lips framing teeth like canting tombstones</fluff>
      
      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>5 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Until discharged</duration>
      <bardAffinity />
      
      <line>You bind a message into a surface you touch. When conditions you set are met, the surface manifests a mouth and conveys your message, discharging the ritual.</line>
      <line>The mouth appears to be made out of the same material as the surface, but you otherwise decide the mouth's appearance.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual as a standard action or the time it takes for you to convey the message, whichever is longer. If the length of your message is 25 words or less, you do not pay the normal component cost.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Make Whole</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>As you finish the ritual, the oaken door stands whole and unblemished as if it had not just been burst through in a surprise attack</fluff>
      
      <price>40 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana or Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>Varies</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
      
      <line>A single object that can fit in a 10-foot cube is completely repaired. At the DM's discretion, you can restore a larger object by increasing the casting time by 10 minutes for each 10-foot cube.</line>
      <line>The component cost is one-fifth of the item's cost. In cases where you attempt to repair an item not on any price list, the DM determines the cost.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to ignore the component cost of this ritual. If you do, you must have all of the pieces of the item to be restored, and the ritual only lasts for 24 hours, after which the item returns to its broken state. Each time this ritual is used on the same item in this way, the number of healing surges increases by one unless the item has been fully repaired or restored.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Pass without Trace</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>After the completion of this ritual, it is as if someone keeps erasing the marks you and your allies leave in your surroundings</fluff>
      
      <price>35 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>At least 4 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>10 hours</duration>
      
      <line>You and up to five allies present while you perform this ritual leave fewer tracks. The component costs of this ritual is equal to 4 gp, plus a 2 gp increase for each affected creature (thus a minimum of 6 gp if you only affect yourself and don't expend a healing surge).</line>
      <line>The DC to track those affected by the ritual increases by 5, as if you had taken the time to obscure the tracks.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> A creature affected by this ritual can expend a healing surge to negate the component cost increase for him or her.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Portend Weather</title>
      <category>Divination</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You see what the weather will be in the near future</fluff>
      
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>2 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>
      
      <line>You determine what the weather will be like for the next 24 hours within a 50-mile radius of your current position.</line>
      <line>You and up to 8 allies present during the casting of this ritual gain a +5 bonus to Endurace checks to endure any extreme weather you foresee.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Purify Water</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>The tainted water becomes crystal clear and refreshing to drink</fluff>
      
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana, Nature, or Religion</skill>
      <component>at least 10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
      
      <line>You purify a volume of water. </line>
      <line>Your Arcana check, Nature check or Religion check determines the volume of water that you can purify.</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>9 or lower:</i>]]> a 5-foot cube</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10 - 19:</i>]]> two 5-foot cubes</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> five 5-foot cubes</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> twenty 5-foot cubes</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> fifty 5-foot cubes</line>
      <line>The component cost for the ritual is 10 gp for each 5-foot cube.</line>
      <line>A 5-foot cube is roughly 935 gallons of liquid, or the contents of a sizable barrel.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Special:</i>]]> If you are purifying a larger volume of water than you can affect with a single casting, you can expend a healing surge when you finish casting the ritual.</line>
      <line>If you expend the healing surge and immediately begin another casting of this ritual, the affected volume remains magically pure for the duration of the casting. You can keep expending healing surges to combine castings as long as you have healing surges remaining.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Raise Beast Companion</title>
      <category>Restoration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You call out to your beast companion and, though death separates you, the ties of faith and friendship between you can cross any gulf</fluff>
      
      <price>none</price>
      <skill>Nature (no check)</skill>
      <component>at least 50 gp</component>
      <time>4 hours</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
      <requirement>You must have an animal companion, a beast companion, or a similar feature</requirement>
      
      <line>This ritual allows you to restore life to your slain companion. It functions as the <![CDATA[<i>raise dead</i>]]> ritual, with the following exceptions:</line>
      <line indent="1">&#9658; You can expend a healing surge to perform the ritual without having a part of your companion's corpse.</line>
      <line indent="1">&#9658; The death penalty fades after you finish three encounter without expending an action point.</line>
      <line indent="1">&#9658; The component cost for a paragon companion is 500 gp, and 5,000 gp for an epic companion.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> A character trained in Nature automatically masters this ritual without needing a ritual book if they have an animal companion, beast companion, or similar feature and have training in Nature.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Raise Dead</title>
      <category>Restoration</category>
      <level>8</level>
      <fluff>You bend over the body of your slain comrade, applying sacramental unguents until, finally, their eyes flutter open as life has been restored</fluff>
      
      <price>600 gp</price>
      <skill>Heal (no check)</skill>
      <component>at least 400 gp</component>
      <time>8 hours</time>
      <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
      
      <line>To perform this ritual, you must have a part of the corpse of a creature that died no more than 20 days ago.</line>
      <line>You apply mystic salves, then pray to the gods to restore the dead creature's life. The subject returns to life as if he or she had taken an extended rest. The subject is freed of any temporary conditions suffered at death, but permanent conditions remain.</line>
      <line>The subject returns with a death penalty: -1 to all attack rolls, skill checks, saving throws, and ability checks. This death penalty fades after the subject finishes four encounters without expending action points.</line>
      <line>You can't restore life to a creature that has been petrified or to a creature that died of old age.</line>
      <line>The subject's soul must be free and willing to return to life. Some magical effects trap the soul and this prevent this ritual from working, and gods can intervene to prevent a soul from journeying back to the realm of the living.</line>
      <line>In all cases, death is less inclined to return paragon and epic heroes; the component cost is 4,000 gp for returning a paragon tier character to life, and 40,000 for returning an epic tier character to life. Also, <![CDATA[<i>raise dead</i>]]> counts as a ritual of the target's level or level 8, whichever is higher, for abilities that let you cast rituals at reduced cost, for free, or with other modifications.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can extend the time that the subject has been dead by expending 2 healing surges for each 5-day extension.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Secret Page</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>While your opponents might be able to find your journal, they'll never see what you wrote there</fluff>
      
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>1 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>Permanent</duration>
      
      <line>You ward writings so others cannot read them. Use this ritual to protect one page (maximum 250 words).</line>
      <line>You make the page appear not to exist, causing any other than you to ignore it; the page's presence is blocked from the a reader's mind. You can choose instead to obscure the page with false writings, which you produce before performing the ritual. Other readers see the false text rather than the real text.</line>
      <line>The DC for a Perception check to notice the concealed writing is equal to 15 + your Arcana check modifier. Readers use passive Perception unless they are specifically looking for concealed text.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Silence</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You block away any inquisitive ears that might be after your secrets</fluff>
      
      <price>25 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>
      <bardAffinity />
      
      <line>You ward a single room (or a burst 4 area) against eavesdropping. Creatures outside of the area attempting to liston to something in the area take a -10 penalty to their Perception checks and passive Perception to do so.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Silent Image</title>
      <category>Deception</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>The arcane words you mutter turn into colors that you trace on thin air with your fingers in intricate patterns, painting a life-like picture</fluff>
      
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>2 gp</component>
      <time>1 minute</time>
      <duration>1 hour or until discharged</duration>
      
      <line>You create an illusion of an object, a creature, or an effect such as fire. The illusion has only a visual aspect.</line>
      <line>A creature can use a minor action to make an Arcana check or a Perception check (DC 10 + your Arcana skill check modifier) when it sees the illusion. If the check succeeds, the creature discerns the illusory nature of the image.</line>
      <line>If a creature interacts with the image, the illusory nature is readily apparent, and the ritual is immediately discharged.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> You can expend a healing surge to perform this ritual as a standard action. If you do, the DC to discern the illusion is reduced by 5.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Ritual Scroll:</b>]]> When you perform this ritual from a ritual scroll, you can do so as a standard action, as if you had expended a healing surge to do so.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Tenser's Floating Disk</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>A plane of force follows you everywhere, like a porter that never needs rest</fluff>
      
      <price>10 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana</skill>
      <component>2 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours</duration>
      
      <line>You create a slightly concave, circular plane of force that floats a foot off the ground and can carry what you lay upon it. The disk is 3 feet in diameter and 1 inch deep at its center.</line>
      <line>The disk remains stationary unless you move more than 5 squares away from it, in which case it immediately moves with your base speed towards you once. If it cannot end this movement within 5 squares of you, it continues to move once at the end of your subsequent turns until it is within 5 squares of you. If you are more then 5 squares away from the disk at the end of your turn (after the disk has moved) for more than 2 consecutive turns, the disk disappears, dropping whatever it was carrying.</line>
      <line>As a move action, you can command the disk to move. If it is within 5 squares of you, it can move to any other position within 5 squares of you by the shortest possible path. If it is not within 5 squares of you, it moves at your base speed towards you. You cannot move the disk if you are on it.</line>
      <line>Your Arcana check result determines the maximum load the disk can carry:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Arcana Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>9 or lower:</i>]]> 250 pounds</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>10 - 19:</i>]]> 500 pounds</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> 500 pounds, and the disk disappears after 3 consecutive rounds</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 - 39:</i>]]> 1000 pounds, and the disk disappears after 3 consecutive rounds</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>40 or higher:</i>]]> 2000 pounds, and the disk disappears after 4 consecutive rounds</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Special:</b>]]> When casting this ritual, you can expend a healing surge to increase the distance that the disk can exist away from you to 10 squares. You can use a minor action to change between the two distances.</line>
      <line>You can cast this ritual as part of your morning preparations, in which case you instead refresh the duration of a currently existing disk instead of creating a new one.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Traveller's Camouflage</title>
      <category>Deception</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You and your allies take on the textures and colors of the world around you</fluff>
      
      <price>15 gp</price>
      <skill>Nature</skill>
      <component>at least 4 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>10 hours</duration>
      
      <line>You cload yourself and up to eight allies present during the casting of this ritual in a camouflaging shroud. The component costs of this ritual is equal to 4 gp, plus a 2 gp increase for each affected creature (thus a minimum of 6 gp if you only affect yourself and don't expend a healing surge).</line>
      <line>The targets gain a power bonus to Stealth checks while traveling. The size of the power bonus depends on your Nature check result:</line>
      <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Nature Check Result</b>]]></line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>19 or lower:</i>]]> +2 power bonus</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>20 - 29:</i>]]> +5 power bonus</line>
      <line indent="2"><![CDATA[<i>30 or higher:</i>]]> +10 power bonus</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Traveller's Chant</title>
      <category>Exploration</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Your chant lifts your allies steps, and helps take their mind off the drudgery of the journey</fluff>
      
      <price>25 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>a focus, and 2 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>10 hours</duration>
      <bard />
      
      <line>You target yourself and up to eight allies that hear the whole performance of the ritual. The targets gain a +2 power bonus to exploration speed.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A musical instrument you play as part of performing the ritual.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Unseen Servant</title>
      <category>Creation</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Why bother with real servants when magical ones are so much more obedient?</fluff>
      
      <price>25 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>a focus, and 5 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours or until dismissed</duration>
      
      <line>You conjure a Medium unseen servant of invisible force. It cannot move more than 20 squares away from your space, though you do not need line of effect to it. Each unseen servant you currently control doubles the component cost of conjuring another one.</line>
      <line>An unseen servant never tires. It obeys your commands, moves at your speed, can lift up to 100 pounds, and performs basic functions and repetitive tasks, such as cleaning, making camp, and moving, holding, or carrying objects.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Focus:</b>]]> A ceramic hand. The same focus can be used to conjure multiple unseen servants.</line>
      <line>The person who holds this focus is empowered to command any unseen servant conjured with it as the focus. If the ceramic hand is broken or not in anyone's possession for 1 minute or longer, all unseen servants conjured using it as the focus disappear.</line>
   </ritual>
   
   <ritual>
      <title>Wizard's Curtain</title>
      <category>Warding</category>
      <level>1</level>
      <fluff>Some activities call for privacy</fluff>
      
      <price>20 gp</price>
      <skill>Arcana (no check)</skill>
      <component>10 gp</component>
      <time>10 minutes</time>
      <duration>24 hours or untill dismissed</duration>
      
      <line>You draw a curtain or several curtains from nowhere to conceal a single room (or a burst 4 area) to ensure visual privacy. The curtain is nearly opaque and appears in any pattern or colors you desire. Creatures outside of the area attempting to see into the warded area take a -10 penalty to Perception checks and passive Perception to do so.</line>
      <line>You can dismiss the ritual by pulling the curtains back to nothingness.</line>
   </ritual>
</catalog>
