<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="item.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <list selection="1" />
   <list selection="2" />
   <list selection="3" />
   <list selection="4" />
   <list selection="5" />
   <list selection="6" />
   <list selection="7" />
   <list selection="8" />
   <list selection="9" />
   <list selection="10" />
   <list selection="11" />
   <list selection="12" />
   <list selection="13" />
   <list selection="14" />
   <list selection="15" />
   <list selection="16" />
   <list selection="17" />
   <list selection="18" />
   <list selection="19" />
   <list selection="20" />
   <list selection="21" />
   <list selection="22" />
   <list selection="23" />
   <list selection="24" />
   <list selection="25" />
   <list selection="26" />
   <list selection="27" />
   <list selection="28" />
   <list selection="29" />
   <list selection="30" />

   <item>
      <title>Backpack of Concealment</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This plain leather backpack is covered with pockets big and small</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This backpack can conceal any one object placed within it from a physical search. Any creature other than the one that placed the item in the backpack cannot find the object.</line>
         <line>If the backpack is destroyed, the object falls from its remains.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Blessed Book</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This leather tome, bound in iron and silver, contains far more pages than naturally possible</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This ritual book has the dimensions and weight of a standard ritual book, but holds 1,200 pages.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Bottled Twilight</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This black glass bottle holds the power to turn all light to dusk</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Effect:</i>]]> You remove the cork from the bottle, and until the end of the encounter all light within 10 squares of the bottle becomes dim light.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Collapsible Campfire</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This small box is made of darkly stained pine with a number of arcane symbols branded into the side</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>As part of taking a short rest or extended rest, you can unfold this box to reveal a magical campfire. The fire can be refolded into a box as part of ending the rest.</line>
         <line>This fire is warm, comfortable, and cannot be doused by any action beyond refolding the box.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Delver's Light</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Often attached to the forehead or chest, this magic gem gives off light powered by your life force</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline>
         <name>Attached Component</name>
         <text>You must have the Living Construct racial trait to use this item.</text>
      </headline>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can mentally command the delver's light as a free action. When you command the light, you command it to shed dim light to a radius of 10 squares, bright light to a radius of 10 squares and dim light to a further 10 squares, or to shed no light.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 7:</i>]]> Dim light to a radius of 20 squares, or bright to a radius of 20 squares and dim light to a further 10 squares.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Door of Alarm</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This seemingly innocuous door issues a shrill alarm when an unknown creature walks through it</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Structure</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The creator can spend 1 minute to attune any number of individuals to this door. The creator can also spend 5 minutes to unattune any number of individuals, or to give one attuned individual the ability to attune or unattune individuals as if he or she was the creator.</line>
         <line>When a creature other than an attuned individual walks through the door, a shrill alarm sounds and doesn't stop for 1 hour or until that creature leaves through the same door.</line>
         <line>The creator or an individual with the ability to attune others to the door can command the alarm to become silent as a free action while within 20 squares of the door.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Eternal Chalk</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>The marks left by this chalk glow briefly as you scribe them, remaining in place to guide you until you choose to erase them</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>A stick of eternal chalk never breaks or wears down with normal use. Any writing or drawing made with this chalk cannot be erased for one week by anyone except the original artist or author.</line>
         <line>A stick of eternal chalk can be created in any color. The creator chooses a color they know at the time of creation.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Impenetrable Barding</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Through this barding, your heroism imparts a protective aura upon your mount</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>180</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>11</value>
         <price>4,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>21</value>
         <price>112,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount barding</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>While ridden, the mount wearing this barding gains resist 5 to all damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 11:</i>]]> Resist 10.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 21:</i>]]> Resist 15.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Ioun's Parchment</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This thin sheet of bronze, the size of a roll of parchment, is embossed with Ioun's symbol in one corner</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This material can be written on like paper or parchment, and the writing can't be erased until the parchment's owner wills it blank. It is flexible enough to roll.</line>
         <line>Creating a ritual scroll using this item fills it with text, but takes half the usual time. Once the ritual is performed, the piece of Ioun's parchment turns blank and can be reused.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Mirrored Caparison</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This coat contains rows of faceted crystals that protect against wide-ranging attacks</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount barding</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>A mount wearing this caparison gains a +1 item bonus to Fortitude, Reflex, and Will.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Mount</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Trigger:</i>]]> The mount is targeted by a close or area attack</line>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Effect:</i>]]> The triggering attack does not target the mount.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Mountebank's Deck</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This plain deck of cards looks crisp and new, suggesting that you are likewise new at the game</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can attune this deck of cards to yourself by shedding six drops of blood on it during a short rest.</line>
         <line>From that point forward, whenever you draw or deal a card from this deck, it is of a suit and value of your choice. Anyone else who interacts with the deck finds it to be a normal deck of whatever game it is designed for.</line>
         <line>Only one creature can be attuned to the deck at a time.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Pierced Heart Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Arrows, spears, swords - anything with a point serves to pincushion the heart at the center of this tattoo</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you use your <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, you gain a +2 bonus to damage the first time you hit before the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 12:</i>]]> +4 bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 22:</i>]]> +6 bonus.</line>
         <line>If you are raging when you use your <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, you also gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls until you hit, or until the end of your next turn, whichever comes first.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Restfull Bedroll</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>A good long rest in this magic bedroll grants you extra vigor</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>11</value>
         <price>9,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>21</value>
         <price>225,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>Whenever you complete an extended rest in the restful bedroll, you gain 1d8 temporary hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 11:</i>]]> 2d8 temporary hit points, and an additional healing surge for the day</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 21:</i>]]> 3d8 temporary hit points, and two additional healing surges for the day</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Shroud of Protection</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This diaphanous shroud appears insubstantial, yet when laid over a dying ally, it provides a defense stronger than steel</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous  Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Effect:</i>]]> Melee 1 (one dying creature); The target gains resist 20 all.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 12:</i>]]> Resist 35.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 22:</i>]]> Resist 50, and the target gains a +2 item bonus to saving throws, including death saves.</line>
         <line>The effect lasts until the target is no longer dying or until the shroud is removed (a standard action), whichever comes first.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Silent Tool</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This mundane-looking tool muffles the noise you make while you work</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When used to do the work it was designed for, a silent tool makes practically no noise. For example, a silent crowbar could aid attempts to open a locked door without alerting the sleeping monster on the other side, while a silent grppling hook has less chance of being heard by nearby guards.</line>
         <line>You gain a +5 item bonus to Stealth checks related to using the tool.</line>
         <line>Any individual mundane tool -a woodcutter's axe, a crowbar, a hammer, a shovel, and so on- can be made silent. Weapons, clothing, jewelry, or other mundane objects cannot.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Spellshard</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This shard of obsidian or crystal can be imbued with magical knowledge</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Properties</name>
         <line>A spellshard has the following properties:</line>
         <line>&#9658; Rituals, Wizard spells, and similar effects can be stored in the shard. Each item is stored as mental information rather than written words. A spellshard is equivalent to a spellbook or a ritual book for the purposes of holding such information.</line>
         <line indent="1">The cost of storing the information is unchanged, and using the stored information functions normally in all ways.</line>
         <line>&#9658; A spellshard can be enchanted like it were a tome implement.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Stalker's Flint</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>A warm, bright fire quickly erupts from a single spark struck off this magical shard</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Illusion</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Effect:</i>]]> You light a campfire using this flint.</line>
         <line>The fire burns without smoke or sound, and sheds bright light to a radius of 10 squares. The light is invisible from outside its radius, though creatures and objects within that area can be seen if the surrounding lighting conditions allow it or if a viewer has darkvision.</line>
         <line>The campfire is a normal fire in all other respects, burning as long as it has fuel or until extinguished normally.</line>
         <line>The flint can be used to light lanterns and other fires as normal, but such fires gain no magical qualities.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Sun Globe</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>After being installed in a socket on the wall or ceiling, these fist-sized crystal globes shed light when commanded</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>180</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Structure</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can command this globe as a free action. It can be commanded to shed either bright light or dim light, or shed no light. It can shed light either 5 or 10 squares in all directions.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Tattoo of Vengeance</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This tattoo shows wicked-looking blades and bolts of lightning, representing the comeuppance you will extract</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>Whenever an enemy scores a critical hit against you and deals damage, you gain a +3 item bonus to damage rolls against that enemy until the end of the encounter.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 15:</i>]]> +6 item bonus</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 25:</i>]]> +9 item bonus</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Vistani Tambourine</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>A tiny drum with ringing bells, or zils, this instrument help you keep a lively tempo despite difficulty</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <bonus>+1</bonus>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline>
         <name>Enhancement Bonus</name>
         <text>Attack rolls and damage rolls</text>
      </headline>
      <headline>
         <name>Critical</name>
         <text>+1d6 damage per plus</text>
      </headline>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>If you are a bard, you can use this instrument as an implement for Bard powers.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Requirement:</i>]]> You must be wielding the tambourine in one hand</line>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Effect:</i>]]> Close burst 5 (you and each ally in the burst); Each target can ignore difficult terrain until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line>You move up to your speed.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Woundstitch Powder</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This worn leather pouch contains a replenishing quantity of life-saving yellow powder</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>11</value>
         <price>9,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Effect:</i>]]> Melee touch (one creature); If the target is dying, it stops making death saving throws until it takes damage.</line>
         <line>If the target is taking untyped ongoing damage, it makes a saving throw against all such effects.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 11:</i>]]> With a +5 bonus to the save.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

</catalog>
