<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="item.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <collection>Wondrous items</collection>
   
   <list selection="1" />
   <list selection="2" />
   <list selection="3" />
   <list selection="4" />
   <list selection="5" />
   <list selection="6" />
   <list selection="7" />
   <list selection="8" />
   <list selection="9" />
   <list selection="10" />
   <list selection="11" />
   <list selection="12" />
   <list selection="13" />
   <list selection="14" />
   <list selection="15" />
   <list selection="16" />
   <list selection="17" />
   <list selection="18" />
   <list selection="19" />
   <list selection="20" />
   <list selection="21" />
   <list selection="22" />
   <list selection="23" />
   <list selection="24" />
   <list selection="25" />
   <list selection="26" />
   <list selection="27" />
   <list selection="28" />
   <list selection="29" />
   <list selection="30" />

   <item>
      <title>Arcane Key</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>Using this silver key enhances certain rituals</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This item can be used as an optional focus for the <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i> or <i>knock</i>]]> rituals. Doing so allows you to use this item's associated at-will power while you hold this item.</line>
         <line>When used as an optional focus for the <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> ritual that is used to defeat an <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]>, the creator of that ward does not know of the ward being defeated until 5 minutes later.</line>
         <line>This item can only be the optional focus of one ritual casting at a time. Performing another ritual removes any association this has with a previous casting.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>This item is the optional focus for an <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]> ritual.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You deactivate the associated <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]>, no matter how far you are from it, even if y ou are on another plane.</line>
         <line>You can use this power again to reactivate it.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>This item is the optional focus for a <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> ritual that was cast in the past 5 minutes.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You relock, reseal, or otherwise restore the target of the associated <![CDATA[<i>knock</i>]]> ritual, up to and including restoring any <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]> on the target, preventing the creator of that ward from learning it was defeated.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Backpack of Concealment</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This plain leather backpack is covered with pockets big and small</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This backpack can conceal any one object placed within it from a physical search. Any creature other than the one that placed the item in the backpack cannot find the object.</line>
         <line>If the backpack is destroyed, the object falls from its remains.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Bag of Holding</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This item appears to be a simple sack of brown canvas</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This bag can hold up to 200 pounds in weight or 20 cubic feet in volume, but it always weighs only 1 pound.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Bed of Rapid Resting</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This comfortable bed speeds your rest but is too large to cart around in the dungeon</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>420</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Furniture</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you take an extended rest in this bed in a comfortable environment, you spend 4 hours (instead of the usual 6) to gain the benefit of that rest.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Blessed Book</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This leather tome, bound in iron and silver, contains far more pages than naturally possible</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This ritual book has the dimensions and weight of a standard ritual book, but holds 1,200 pages.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Bottled Cinders</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This brass bottle is hot to the touch, and spews forth a cloud of ash and smoke when opened</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Fire</keyword> <keyword>Zone</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 1; The burst creates a zone of floating ash and smoke until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 17</name>Close burst 3.</line>
         <line>Creatures in the zone have concealment. Any creature other than you that starts its turn in the zone takes 5 fire damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Sustain Minor</name> <![CDATA[<i>Requirement:</i>]]>You must be within 10 squares of the zone; The zone persists until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 17</name>10 fire damage.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Bottled Spirit</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>The spirit bound within this rune-inscribed black metal flask manipulates objects at your command</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Conjuration</keyword>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You conjure the spirit contained within the bottle in an unnoccupied square within 10 squares of you. The spirit lasts until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line>If you conjure the spirit into a square adjacent to yourself and are holding an object when you use this power, the hand can move the object into a pack, a pouch, a sheath, or a similar container and simultaneously move any one object carried or worn anywhere on your body into your hand.</line>
         <line>While the spirit persists, you can use the following actions:</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Minor Action:</b>]]> The spirit picks up or manipulates an object weighing 20 pounds or less. It can hold only one object at a time.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Move Action:</b>]]> The spirit moves up to 10 squares in any direction, carrying the object it holds.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Free Action:</b>]]> The hand drops the object it is holding.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Sustain Minor:</b>]]> The hand persists until the end of your next turn.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Bridle of Rapid Action</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This fine leather bridle lets you and your mount react more quickly to danger</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>12,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You roll initiative while riding the mount wearing this bridle</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The mount rolls initiative using your initiative modifier. If its check result is higher than yours, you can use the mount's result in place of yours.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15</name>This power is an encounter power instead.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Bridle of Summoning</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This simple leather bridle conjures a magical mount for your use</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Summoning</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You summon a riding horse in a space adjacent to you. Unlike most summons, this one does not use your statistics and lacks the usual summon traits. The horse does not have its attack, and you do not lose a healing surge if the horse is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, though you can expend your healing surges when an effect allows the horse to spend one.</line>
         <line>The bridle transforms into the mount's tack and saddle, and the horse serves you, obeying you spoken commands.</line>
         <line>The horse disappears after 12 hours or if it is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Cask of Liquid Gold</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This cask contains a never-ending supply of dwarven ale</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>At the start of each day, the cask fills to its full volume with dwarven ale.</line>
         <line>Any ale taken from the cask evaporates if it has not been consumed when the cask refills.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Chime of Awakening</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This silver chime sounds an alarm in the minds of you and your resting allies</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You set the chime to ring when a specific trigger occurs within 10 squares of it. Example triggers include the presence of anyone other than you and your allies, the light of the sun touching the area, or the appearance of a specific character or type of creature.</line>
         <line>When the trigger is met, the chime rings in the minds of you and all allies; a creature must be within 10 squares of the chime to hear it. Creatures that hear the chime are instantly awoken (if asleep) and alert.</line>
         <line>The chime can be fooled by creatures in disguise or hiding. It makes active Perception checks, and has a Perception check modifier of +10.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Chime of Opening</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>When struck, this chime rings out with a magical tone that opens locks</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>25,0000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Ranged 5 (one locked door, chest, gate, or other object); The chime makes Thievery checks to open any locks and disable any traps on the target.</line>
         <line>The chime makes one check on each of your turns for up to 1 minute, starting on the turn you use this power, with a +10 Thievery check modifier.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15</name>+17 Thievery check modifier.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 25</name>+24 Thievery check modifier.</line>
         <line>The DM makes these checks, and if the results would not be obvious (such as when disabling a hidden trap), you do not know the result of the checks. When the chime fails a check, it starts making checks against the next lock or trap, if there are any. The chime can end up opening or disabling only some or none of all locks and traps on the target.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Climber's Rope</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>When a slope of wall cannot be climbed, the projectile creates an easier path</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must be wielding a Bow or Crossbow</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Ranged weapon (one wall, ceiling, or similar surface or a sufficiently have unattended object such as a large statue; the target cannot be at long range); A magic trope trails behind the projectile as you fire it, connecting the target to your position. The rope can support up to 500 pounds at a time.</line>
         <line>The rope remains in place until the end of the encounter or until you dismiss it as a minor action. The projectile does not automatically return to you, and if fired at a creature, it deals no damage.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Coin of Good Luck</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This shiny gold coin can mean the difference between life and death, brilliant success and utter failure</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>50</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When flipped, this coin always lands tails up.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You make an attack roll, skill check, or saving throw and dislike the result</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You gain a +1 bonus to the triggering attack roll, skill check, or saving throw.</line>
         <line><name>Special</name>You cannot use the utility power of another <![CDATA[<i>coin of good luck</i>]]> until you have finished an extended rest.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Collapsible Campfire</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This small box is made of darkly stained pine with a number of arcane symbols branded into the side</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>As part of taking a short rest or extended rest, you can unfold this box to reveal a magical campfire. The fire can be refolded into a box as part of ending the rest.</line>
         <line>This fire is warm, comfortable, and cannot be doused by any action beyond refolding the box.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Companion's Defender</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This belt is contructed from woven bones and enhances a companion's defensive ability while adjacent to you</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Companion Item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>While adjacent to you, your companion gains a +1 item bonus to all defenses.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15</name>+2 item bonus while adjacent to you, and a +1 item bonus at other times.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 25</name>+3 item bonus while adjacent to you, and a +1 item bonus at other times.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Cosmic Cycle Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>The sun, moon, and stars wind around your chest in this tattoo and flare into motion when you use its power</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <line>If you have the Cosmic Magic sorcerer class feature and use your <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, you can choose to change your cosmic phase to the next higher-numbered phase (or back to the phase of the sun if you are in the phase of the stars).</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Decanter of Endless Water</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>When you open this always-dripping flask, it will release a steady stream of water, or a torrent that blasts away obstacles</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You cause the decanter to pour forth fresh or salt water in one of three volumes:</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/><name>Stream</name>1 gallon.</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/><name>Fountain</name>5 gallons in a 5-foot-long stream.</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/><name>Geyser</name>30 gallons in a 20-foot-long stream. The geyser creates considerable pressure, and you must succeed at a DC 16 Strength check when you use this function, or you are knocked prone.</line>
         <line>In addition to filling a container of suitable volume, the fountain function of the decanter can be used to clear dirt or light debris from an area 2 squares on a side.</line>
         <line>The geyser function can be used to break a door or other similarly sized object. Make an Athletics check at a +12 check modifier to break the object. The area in a burst 1 centered on the door or object is difficult terrain until the end of the encounter.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Deepfarer's Pouch</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This oilskin pouch holds more than it should, including a small breathing tube that extends from the inside</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This belt pouch contains 1 hour's worth of air, which remains fresh indefinitely.</line>
         <line>Once the air in the pouch has been used up, you can refresh the supply by exposing the open pouch to any supply of breathable air during a short rest.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Delver's Light</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Often attached to the forehead or chest, this magic gem gives off light powered by your life force</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attached" />
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can mentally command the delver's light as a free action. When you command the light, you command it to shed dim light to a radius of 10 squares, bright light to a radius of 10 squares and dim light to a further 10 squares, or to shed no light.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 7</name>Dim light to a radius of 20 squares, or bright to a radius of 20 squares and dim light to a further 10 squares.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Demonskin Tattoo</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>Not all societies understand that tattooing a portion of demonskin onto your body isn't an evil act</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <price>425,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you spend an action point to take an extra action, choose acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder. You gain resist 5 to the chosen damage type until the end of the encounter.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13</name>Resist 10.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 23</name>Resist 15.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Distracting Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Any small, bright image in a highly visible place is sufficient for the magic of this tattoo</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you spend an action point, you can end any mark affecting you.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Door of Alarm</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This seemingly innocuous door issues a shrill alarm when an unknown creature walks through it</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Structure</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The creator can spend 1 minute to attune any number of individuals to this door. The creator can also spend 5 minutes to unattune any number of individuals, or to give one attuned individual the ability to attune or unattune individuals as if he or she was the creator.</line>
         <line>When a creature other than an attuned individual walks through the door, a shrill alarm sounds and doesn't stop for 1 hour or until that creature leaves through the same door.</line>
         <line>The creator or an individual with the ability to attune others to the door can command the alarm to become silent as a free action while within 20 squares of the door.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Doss Lute</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>The dulcet music of this lute imbues its listeners with resilience and quiet resolve</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attackenh"/>
      <headline crit="d6"/>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line auto="bardinstrument"/>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Short</action> <subaction>Rest</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Choose yourself, or an ally who remained within 20 squares of you during the rest.</line>
         <line>The chosen character gains a +1 power bonus to saving throws until the end of his or her next rest.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Song of Rest</name>If the target also benefited from your Song or Rest class feature, the power bonus increases to +2.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Echo of Ty'h'kadi</title>
      <category>Rare</category>
      <fluff>Light worms through this violet shard, as if somehow it contains the very essence of lightning</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Primordial Shard</subtype>
      <headline itemdamage="">Lightning or Thunder</headline>
      <block>
         <name>Primordial Shard</name>
         <line>You can benefit from only one primordial shard at a time. If you carry more than one, none of them function.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>Your origin changes to elemental.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Attack Power</name>
         <keyword>Elemental</keyword> <keyword>Thunder</keyword>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You take lightning damage</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 1 (each enemy in the burst); Each target takes 5 thunder damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 17</name>10 thunder damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 27</name>Close burst 2, 10 thunder damage.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Enshrouding Candle</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This candle creates a dim corona of light that helps conceal you from foes</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This candle never burns down.</line>
         <line>When lit, this candle sheds dim light in a 2-square radius. Bright light within the candle's radius is reduced to dim light.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Illusion</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>The candle must be lit.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The candle creates an illusion within the area of its illumination. The illusion moves with the candle, and lasts for 8 hours or until the candle is extinguished as a minor action.</line>
         <line>Creatures within the illusion are invisible to those outside the area, though other features within the area appear as normal. Sound (including speech) within the area is likewise inaudible to those outside. Creatures within the area are unaffected by the illusion and can perceive each other normally.</line>
         <line>Other senses are unaffected by the candle's illusion. For example, a creature with tremorsense could locate characters hidden by the illusion normally. Likewise, if characters within the area move objects around them, the moving objects can be seen.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Escape Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Broken chains and skeleton keys are popular images for this tattoo</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <price>425,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Teleportation</keyword>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Opportunity</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>A nonminion enemy scores a critical hit against you and deals damage</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You teleport up to 1 square.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13</name>Up to 2 squares.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 23</name>Up to 3 squares.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Eternal Chalk</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>The marks left by this chalk glow briefly as you scribe them, remaining in place to guide you until you choose to erase them</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>A stick of eternal chalk never breaks or wears down with normal use. Any writing or drawing made with this chalk cannot be erased for one week by anyone except the original artist or author.</line>
         <line>A stick of eternal chalk can be created in any color. The creator chooses a color they know at the time of creation.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Everlasting Provisions</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This plain basket radiates delicious smells</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>After an extended rest, you open the basket, creating enough food and water to feed five Medium or Small creatures (or one Large creature) for 24 hours.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Faerie Field Catalog</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>From boggles to brownies, nixies to nymphs, this volume keenly details the fey, giving you access to obscure knowledge</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can make monster knowledge checks regarding fey creatures even if you don't have training in the Arcana skill.</line>
         <line>If you do have training in the Arcana skill, you instead gain a +2 bonus to monster knowledge checks regarding fey creatures.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Familiar's Baldric</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This jeweled collar or harness identifies your familiar belonging to you and extends your protection to it</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <bonus>+1</bonus>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>425,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Familiar item</subtype>
      <headline>
         <name>Item Bonus</name>
         <text>All your familiar's defenses.</text>
      </headline>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Final Messenger</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This warforged communication device is built to resemble a small winged animal, yet it is an intricate assembly of clockwork pieces</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attached"/>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This mechanical messenger is stored inside you, and has a speed of 8.</line>
         <line>When activated, it can function for 8 hours, after which it deactivates. A creature can reactivate the messenger by using 1 minute to make a DC 20 Arcana check. On a success, the creature spends a healing surge to reactivate the messenger for 8 hours.</line>
         <line>A creature that is not the intended recipient can use 1 minute to make a DC 25 Arcana check to view the messenger's programmed image and hear its message. If the check succeeds against DC 30, the creature also learns the messenger's destination or intended recipient.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You program the messenger with with an image of what you currently see, a statement of up to 25 words, and a destination or message recipient. The messenger retains this information until you use this power again, or until you die.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You activate the messenger, and it leaves your body for its programmed destination or recipient. When it reaches its target, it delivers the programmed image and statement.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You are killed</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The messenger is programmed with the last image you saw while conscious, and the message that you were killed. Choose a destination or intended recipient.</line>
         <line>You activate the messenger, and it leaves your body for its programmed destination or recipient.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Fireheart Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>As you call upon its power, flames flare and twist around the heart at the center of this tattoo</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>14</value>
         <price>21,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>24</value>
         <price>525,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you spend an action point to take an extra action, you gain 5 temporary hit points after resolving that action. These temporary hit points last until the end of the encounter.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 14</name>10 temporary hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 24</name>15 temporary hit points.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Flagon of Ale Procurement</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Sought by brewers and barflies, this ornate flagon is not one you can take away from a dwarf</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You know the rough distance to the nearest alcoholic bewerage.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>For five minutes, you know the direction and distance to the nearest source of water within 30 squares of you, or the nearest alcoholic beverage within 60 squares of you.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<b>Dwarf:</b>]]> You can choose to instead know the direction and distance to ingredients for alcoholic beverages within 60 squares of you.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Floating Lantern</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This silver lantern floats in midair under your control</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This lantern never needs ligthing or refilling.</line>
         <line>When you let go of the lantern, it continues to hang in the air where you leave it. If weight in excess of 1 pound is applied to the lantern, it falls to the ground.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must be holding the lantern, or be the last creature to hold it and adjacent to it.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You set the lantern to full (bright light in 10-square radius and dim light for a further 10 squares), half (dim light in a 5-square radius), or off.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must be the last creature to hold the lantern.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You move the lantern up to 10 squares to a square within 10 squares of you.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Flute of the Dancing Satyr</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Carved from wood and inscribed with arcane glyphs, this flute can play a tune of speed and elegance</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Special</name>If you have the Quick Draw feat, you can use this power as a minor action instead.</line>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must have a hand free to use this power.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You shift up to 2 squares.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 5 (each ally in the burst); Each target can shift up to 1 square as a free reaction.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Fochlucan Bandore</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This instrument's song imbues listeners with fervor and strength</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <bonus>+1</bonus>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>8</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>3,400</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>18</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>85,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>425,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>28</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>2,125,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attackenh"/>
      <headline crit="d6"/>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line auto="bardinstrument"/>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Rest</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You use this action as part of a short rest.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>One ally who remained within 20 squares of you during the rest and could hear you gains a +1 power bonus to Weapon damage rolls until the end of his or her next rest. This increases to a +2 power bonus if you have the Song of Rest class feature.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13 or 18</name>+2 or +3 power bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 23 or 28</name>+3 or +4 power bonus.</line>
         <line>You must continue wielding this instrument for the ally to gain this bonus.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Friend's Gift</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Your companion wears this crimson badge on its chest as a sign of friendship</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>14</value>
         <price>21,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>24</value>
         <price>525,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Companion Item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <keyword>Healing</keyword>
         <line>Your companion regains an additional 5 hit points when it spends a healing surge to regain hit points, uses its <![CDATA[<i<second wind</i>]]>, or you spend a healing surge to allow it to regain hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 14</name>Additional 10 hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 24</name>Additional 15 hit points.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Ghost Bridle</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This bridle gives a mount a phantasmal appearance and the ability to slip through solid objects</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>420</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>14</value>
         <price>10,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>24</value>
         <price>262,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The mount gains resist 10 necrotic.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 14</name>Resist 15.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 24</name>Resist 20.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The mount gains phasing until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line>If you are riding the mount when you use this power, you also gain phasing, but lose it if you are no longer riding the mount.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Glowing Globe</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This luminous glass globe floats a handspan above the creature that last touched it</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The glowing globe follows the last creature that touched it, remaining in that creature's space. It can be commanded to remain in a particular spot as a free action.</line>
         <line>If the glowing globe is brought within 1 square of another glowing globe, it goes dark and its powers become unavailable.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The globe sheds dim light in a 2-square radius, bright ligth in a 10-square radius and dim light for a further 10 squares, or stops shedding light.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Attack Power</name>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 3 (enemies in the burst); The target is blinded until the start of your next turn.</line>
         <line><name>Special</name>The globe is destroyed.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Grey Security Card</title>
      <category>Rare</category>
      <fluff>This grey rectangle resembles a heavy leaded pany of colored glass</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="losttech"/>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Melee touch (one locked door, chest, gate, or other object); Make a Thievery check to open the target object with a +12 check modifier instead of your Thievery check modifier.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Malfunction</name>If you roll a 1 on this check, the clothing and armor that you are wearing falls off you.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Guardian's Whistle</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This tin whistle is covered with runes that look like they have been crudely scratched into its surface</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>14</value>
         <price>21,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Teleportation</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement:</name>You are holding the whistle in your hand.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Leve 14</name>You can draw the whistle, use it, and put it away as part of the same action. You still need a free hand, though.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 10 (one ally in the burst); You teleport the target to a space adjacent to you.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Harp of Deeper Slumber</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>A single tone from this small harp leaves creatures briefly inattentive and sleeping creatures even deeper in their dreams</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <price>425,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 20 (each creature in the burst); Each target takes a -10 penalty to Perception checks until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13</name>-15 penalty, and an aftereffect of -5 penalty until the end of your following turn.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 23</name>-15 penalty, and an aftereffect of -10 penalty until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line>An unconscious creature takes the penalty until it is no longer unconscious, and is not aware that it was affected by this power..</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Horseshoes of Speed</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>These thin steel horseshoes grant your mount increased speed</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>340</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>7,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The mount gains a +1 bonus to all speeds.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13</name>The bonus increases to +2 for exploration speed.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Horn of Summons</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This steel battle horn alerts even those allies you cannot see</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You sound the horn. All creatures within 1 mile hear its call.</line>
         <line>Allies within that range are awakened if they are sleeping, and instantly know your current location, hit point total, and any effects currently affecting you.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Hyrsam Fiddle</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This finely crafted fiddle bears a glamer that betrays its fey origin</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <bonus>+1</bonus>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>8</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>3,400</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>18</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>85,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>425,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>28</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>2,125,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attackenh"/>
      <headline>
         <name>Critical</name>
         <text>+1d6 damage per plus, or +1d8 damage per plus if you are wielding the Hyrsam fiddlestick in your other hand</text>
      </headline>
      <block>
         <name>Properties</name>
         <line>The Hyrsam fiddle has the following properties:</line>
         <line auto="bardinstrument"><bullet /></line>
         <line><bullet />When you wield a Hyrsam fiddle in one hand and a Hyrsam fiddlestick in the other, you gain a +1 shield bonus to your AC and Reflex.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You miss with a Charm, Psychic, or Thunder attack power using this implement</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Reroll the triggering attack roll, and use either result.</line>
         <line><name>Special</name>If you are wielding a Hyrsam fiddlestick in your other hand and miss the triggering attack roll even with the reroll, you regain the use of this power when you take a short rest.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Impenetrable Barding</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Through this barding, your heroism imparts a protective aura upon your mount</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>180</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>11</value>
         <price>4,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>21</value>
         <price>112,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount barding</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>While ridden, the mount wearing this barding gains resist 5 to all damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 11</name>Resist 10.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 21</name>Resist 15.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Infinite-use Inkpit</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This glass inkwell is stained and battered, as if it has seen much use</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Zone</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You open the inkwell and spill the ink in a close blast 2. The blast creates an extradimensional pit zone until the end of the encounter.</line>
         <line>The ground of the zone becomes a pit that is 20 feet deep. The pit is extradimensional, and does not create a hole in the floor. The hole appears slow enough that a creature in the zone when it is created does not take falling damage.</line>
         <line>Climbing out of the pit requires a DC 15 Athletics check. A creature in the pit when the zone ends rises back to the ground safely.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Instant Campsite</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This tightly packed satchel expands into a complete campsite that can automatically pack up again</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You open this satchel and it magically expands into a complete campsite.</line>
         <line>The campsite includes a campfire and four two-person tents with bedrolls. The campfire requires no fuel and lasts up to 12 hours, or until the campsite is packed into the satchel once more, whichever comes first.</line>
         <line>Packing the campsite into the satchel is a standard action. The tents and bedrolls unceremoniously eject any creatures inside them when the campsite is packed.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Ioun's Parchment</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This thin sheet of bronze, the size of a roll of parchment, is embossed with Ioun's symbol in one corner</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This material can be written on like paper or parchment, and the writing can't be erased until the parchment's owner wills it blank. It is flexible enough to roll.</line>
         <line>Creating a ritual scroll using this item fills it with text, but takes half the usual time. Once the ritual is performed, the piece of Ioun's parchment turns blank and can be reused.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Jar of Steam</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This clay jar is warm to the touch and, when opened, creates a cloud of steam that fills the area around it</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Zone</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 1; You pull the lid off the jar and it creates a zone of steam in the burst until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line>Any creature other than you that ends its turn in the zone takes 1d10 fire damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Sustain Minor</name>Requirement: you must be within 10 squares of the zone; The zone persists until the end of your next turn.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Lamp of Discerning</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This plain-looking lantern grants those in its light the ability to see through deception</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When lit, this lantern sheds bright light in a 10-square radius and dim light for a further 10 squares, like a normal lantern, but never needs refilling.</line>
         <line>You and allies within the bright light gain a +1 power bonus to Insight checks and Perception checks.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Lens of Reading</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Holding this lens to your eye allows you to read even the most complex scripts and obscure languages</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must be perusing a text written in a language you do not know.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>For 6 hours, as long as you read using this lens, you can read the unknown language you are perusing. This does not give you any special ability to notice hidden messages in the text.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Life Shroud</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This clean linen wrap protects a corpse from the ravages of time and the blashphemies of necromancers</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>40</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>9</value>
         <price>160</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>14</value>
         <price>800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Consumable</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>While wrapped in this shroud, a corpse does not decay, can't be touched by an undead creature unless that undead is at least 5 levels higher than the shroud, and can't become undead.</line>
         <line>Once wrapped around a body, the magic in the shroud dissipates after 90 days.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 9</name>After a year and a day.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 14</name>After five years.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Long Day's Battle Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This tattoo is often depicted as a shield surrounded by weapons</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You gain a bonus to damage rolls with daily powers equal to the number of healing surges you have spent.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Mac-Fuirmidh Cittern</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>The music of this magic lute lingers in the mind, providing vigor long after its tones have ceased</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <bonus>+1</bonus>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>10</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>5,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>20</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>125,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>30</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>3,125,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attackenh"/>
      <headline crit="d6"/>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line auto="bardinstrument"/>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Healing</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Short</action> <subaction>Rest</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>At the end of the rest, choose yourself or an ally who remained within 20 squares of you during the rest.</line>
         <line>Until the end of the chosen character's next rest, he or she regain 2 additional hit points when he or she spends a healing surge to regain hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15 or 20</name>3 additional hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 25 or 30</name>4 additional hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Song of Rest</name>Increase the additional hit points regained by 1.</line>
         <line indent="2"><name>Level 20, 25 or 30</name>Increase by 2.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Magical Musician</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This tiny, well-carved wooden box holds a small fiddle bow that, with a touch, produces delightful, mesmerizing music</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <price>425,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>For 1 hour, the item plays a pleasant tune that can be heard within 10 squares.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 23</name>This power is an encounter power instead.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Charm</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>The item must be playing music.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13</name>This power does not have the requirement.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You gain a +2 item bonus to attack rolls with Charm powers until the end of your next turn.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Map of Unseen Lands</title>
      <category>Rare</category>
      <fluff>Unseen images glimmer within this mundane-looking sheet of vellum, which erupts with detail as it creates complex maps at your command</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You gain a +2 bonus to Nature checks and Perception checks realted to navigating through areas mapped by this item's power.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You command the map to redraw itself, depicting the surface area in a 10-mile radius around you. The map doesn't go into precise detail, but it is accurate. It shows only aboveground terrain, not underground areas. The map displays the following features:</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/>General terrain, such as mountains, rivers, and lakes</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/>Structures 5,000 squares feet or larger in area</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/>Structures important for travel, such as bridges and portals</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/>Lairs of creatures that are significant threats</line>
         <line indent="1"><bullet/>Names or general descriptions of any of the above features, if such information is well-known within the area presented by the map</line>
         <line>The map depicts the same area until this power is used again.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Martyr's Saddle</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Those who seek to protect their mounts at any cost favor this saddle</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>900</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>16</value>
         <price>22,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>26</value>
         <price>562,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The mount gains a +1 item bonus to all defenses.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 16</name>+2 item bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 26</name>+3 item bonus.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Mount</keyword>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>The mount would take damage; you must be riding the mount</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The mount takes half of the triggering damage, and you take the remainder. The damage you take is typeless, and cannot be reduced or prevented.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Marvelous Pigments</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>You smear a glob of this paint on a wall or floor, creating any object you desire</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>100</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Consumable</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You create a nonmagical object that is up to 1 square in volume and weighs up to 200 pounds. The object remains until the end of the encounter.</line>
         <line>The object must be created in an unoccupied square and on a solid surface, such as a floor, a wall, or a tree.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Midnight Sixes</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This pair of six-sided dice look innocent, but when rolled, they often come up a winnder</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you roll one or both of these dice, you can mentally command them to roll any desired result.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Mirrored Caparison</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This coat contains rows of faceted crystals that protect against wide-ranging attacks</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <price>6,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <price>162,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount barding</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>A mount wearing this caparison gains a +1 item bonus to Fortitude, Reflex, and Will.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 12</name>+2 item bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 22</name>+3 item bonus.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Mount</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>The mount is targeted by a close or area attack</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The triggering attack does not target the mount.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Mountebank's Deck</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This plain deck of cards looks crisp and new, suggesting that you are likewise new at the game</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can attune this deck of cards to yourself by shedding six drops of blood on it during a short rest.</line>
         <line>From that point forward, whenever you draw or deal a card from this deck, it is of a suit and value of your choice. Anyone else who interacts with the deck finds it to be a normal deck of whatever game it is designed for.</line>
         <line>Only one creature can be attuned to the deck at a time.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Monocle of Comprehension</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Using this monocle as part of your ritual, you share the comprehensive magic with your allies</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can use this item as an optional focus for the <![CDATA[<i>comprehend language</i>]]> ritual.</line>
         <line>If you do, this monocle splits into up to 8 duplicate monocles for the duration of the ritual. Any creature holding one of the monocles gains the same comprehension granted you by the ritual as long as it keeps holding the monocle.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Nail of Sealing</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This thick iron nail is adorned with warding symbols and can hold shut any portal or container</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>40</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Consumable</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You push this nail into a door, chest, or other closable object, and it magically sinks into the material of that object and seals it shut.</line>
         <line>This has the same effects as if you had you performed the <![CDATA[<i>arcane lock</i>]]> ritual on the object, and the DC for Thievery checks or Strength checks made to open the target is set at 25. If you want to allow other creatures to pass normally, you can only choose the password option and must speak the password when you use the nail.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Obsidian Steed</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This figurine of dark volcanic glass can become a sleek riding horse</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Summoning</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You summon a Large obsidian steed in a space adjacent to you. Unlike most summons, this one does not use your statistics and you do not lose a healing surge if the obsidian steed is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, though you can expend your healing surges when an effect allows the steed to spend one.</line>
         <line>When activating this item, you can expend a healing surge to give the obsidian steed temporary hit points equal to your healing surge value.</line>
         <line>The steed disappears after 8 hours or if it is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Onyx Dog</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This figurine, sculpted of reflective onyx, depicts a barking dog</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Summoning</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You summon a Medium onyx dog in a space adjacent to you. Unlike most summons, this one does not use your statistics and you do not lose a healing surge if the onyx dog is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, though you can expend your healing surges when an effect allows the dog to spend one.</line>
         <line>When activating this item, you can expend a healing surge to give the onyx dog temporary hit points equal to your healing surge value.</line>
         <line>The dog disappears after 8 hours or if it is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Opal Carp</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This opal lozenge is carved with scales, and can transform into a giant fish</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Summoning</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You summon a Medium opal carp in a space adjacent to you. The carp can only appear in a body of water. Unlike most summons, this one does not use your statistics and you do not lose a healing surge if the opal carp is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, though you can expend your healing surges when an effect allows the carp to spend one.</line>
         <line>When activating this item, you can expend a healing surge to give the opal carp temporary hit points equal to your healing surge value.</line>
         <line>A character riding the carp can breathe water as if it were air, and can speak normally underwater. The carp can carry one Medium or smaller character weighing no more than 300 pounds.</line>
         <line>The dog disappears after 8 hours or if it is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer. The carp also disappears if more than 300 pounds is placed on it.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Pale Tooth</title>
      <category>Rare</category>
      <fluff>This milky white shard is cool to the touch, hinting at the elemental power contained within</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Primordial Shard</subtype>
      <headline itemdamage="">Cold</headline>
      <block>
         <name>Primordial Shard</name>
         <line>You can benefit from only one primordial shard at a time. If you carry more than one, none of them function.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>Your origin changes to elemental.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Ice Walk</name>
         <line>You ignore difficult terrain that is the result of ice or snow.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Attack Power</name>
         <keyword>Cold</keyword> <keyword>Elemental</keyword>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You take cold damage</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 1 (each enemy in the burst); Each target is frozen until the start of the currently acting creature's next turn.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 17</name>Close burst 2.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 27</name>Close burst 3.</line>
         <line>While frozen, the target is immobilized and has vulnerable 5 cold.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Pearl of Power</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This pearl grows warm to the touch each time you attack, ready to overcome your enemies' best attempts to thwart you</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You miss all targets with an encounter attack power of 3rd level or lower</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 17</name>13th level or lower.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 27</name>23rd level or lower.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You regain the use of the triggering power at the start of your next turn.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Phantom Soldier</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This tiny figuriine is carved in the shape of a warrior and can be used to summon a life-sized illusion of the depicted warrior to distract your enemies in battle</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Illusion</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <line auto="no-opportunity"/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Ranged 5; An illusory soldier appears in an unnocpied square in range. The illusion occupies its square and lasts until the end of the encounter.</line>
         <line>The illusory soldier counts as one of your allies for the purposes of flanking and movement, but can not make any attacks. The illusion uses your defenses, not counting temporary bonuses, has 5 hit points, and is damaged like a minion. You can use the following action once per round:</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Minor Action</name>You move the illusory soldier up to your speed.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Pierced Heart Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Arrows, spears, swords - anything with a point serves to pincushion the heart at the center of this tattoo</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you use your <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, you gain a +2 bonus to damage the first time you hit before the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 12</name>+4 bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 22</name>+6 bonus.</line>
         <line>If you are raging when you use your <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, you also gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls until you hit, or until the end of your next turn, whichever comes first.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Polyglot Gem</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This intricately carved gemstone holds the secrets of language within its many facets</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,8000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Creation</name>
         <line>When this gem is created, the creator chooses any one language.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>As long as you carry this gem on your person, you can speak, read, and write the language chosen when it was created.</line>
         <line>If you carry more than one <![CDATA[<i>polyglot gem</i>]]> on your person, none of them function.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Portrait of Holding</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This painting conceals a secure extradimensional space</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The painting has a hidden extradimensional space that can hold up to 5 cubic feet of material up to 100 pounds.</line>
         <line>The portrait always weights 1 pound, regardless of what it contains.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must look exactly like the creature depicted by the portrait.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The portrait canvas vanishes, providing access to the extradimensional space. Retrieving an item is a minor action, as usual.</line>
         <line>Using this power again ends the effect.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Pouch of Platinum</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This platinum-embossed leather pouch can convert gems and goins into platinum pieces</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>Nonmagical gemstones and coins of any denomination placed into the pouch are converted to an equal value of platinum pieces. Coins or gems that cannot be evenly converted to platinum pieces are unaffected.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Power Jewel</title>
      <category>Rare</category>
      <fluff>Magical energy pulses within this stunning-red jewel, allowing you to regain some of your expended power</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must have finished an encounter without using your action point.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You regain the use of an expended encounter power of 3rd level or lower.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15</name>13th level or lower.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 25</name>23rd level or lower.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Quick-Step Tattoo</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Cheetahs, panthers, and other fast predators serve well for these tattoos</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>1,300</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you spend an action point to take an extra action, each ally who can see you and that also has a <![CDATA[<i>quick-step tattoo</i>]]> can shift 1 square as a free reaction.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Restfull Bedroll</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>A good long rest in this magic bedroll grants you extra vigor</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>11</value>
         <price>9,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>21</value>
         <price>225,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>Whenever you complete an extended rest in the restful bedroll, you gain 1d8 temporary hit points. These temporary hit points last for 4 hours or until the end of the next encounter, whichever comes first.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 11</name>2d8 temporary hit points, and an additional healing surge for the day</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 21</name>3d8 temporary hit points, and two additional healing surges for the day</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Ruby Scabbard</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Blood-red rubies adorn this scabbard, their magic granting your blade extra sharpness</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This scabbard resizes to fit any Light blade or Heavy blade. You can attune a blade to the scabbard as part of your daily preparations.</line>
         <line>An attuned blade can be drawn from this scabbard as part of the same action used to make an attack with that weapon.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You make a Weapon attack with a blade attuned to this scabbard</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You gain a +2 power bonus to damage with the triggering attack. This increases to a +3 power bonus if you draw the weapon from the scabbard as part of the attack.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15</name>+4 power bonus or +6 power bonus, respectively.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 25</name>+6 power bonus or +9 power bonus, respectively.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Saddle of Strength</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This dyed leather saddle is inset with brass, and allows a mount to carry the heaviest loads</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>680</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>17,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Mount item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The mount's carrying capacity increases by 50 percent in all categories (normal load, heavy load, and maximum drag).</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13</name>By 100 percent.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Scroll of Protection</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>You read words of power from this scroll that repel your enemies and prevent them from attacking</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>50</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>10</value>
         <price>200</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>20</value>
         <price>5,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>30</value>
         <price>125,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Consumable</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Special</name>
         <line>When this item is created, the creator chooses one of the following kinds of creatures:</line>
         <line indent="1">angels, demons; devils; dragons; elementals with the air, earth, fire, or water keyword; undead</line>
         <line>The aura created by this scroll's power affects creatures of the chosen kind whose level is equal to or lower than this scroll's level.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Aura</keyword>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You activate an Aura 2 until the end of the encounter or until you make an attack, whichever comes first.</line>
         <line>Affected creatures take a -4 penalty to all attack rolls against targets inside the aura, and cannot enter the aura willingly. If an affected creature starts its turn in the aura, its first action must be to leave the aura by the shortest route possible, unless no route exists.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Sending Fork</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>Speaking your voice into this tuning fork casts it farther across the world when used with magic</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>This item can be used as an optional focus for the <![CDATA[<i>sending</i>]]> ritual. Doing so multiplies the range of the ritual by 10.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Ranged 10 (one square); You speak a short phrase (no more than twenty-five words) into the fork. Creatures can hear you as though you are in the target square. You do not need line of sight or line of effect to the target square.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Shroud of Protection</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This diaphanous shroud appears insubstantial, yet when laid over a dying ally, it provides a defense stronger than steel</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous  Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Melee 1 (one dying creature); The target gains resist 20 all.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 12</name>Resist 35.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 22</name>Resist 50, and the target gains a +2 item bonus to saving throws, including death saves.</line>
         <line>The effect lasts until the target is no longer dying or until the shroud is removed (a standard action), whichever comes first.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Shroud of Revival</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This white gossamer shroud grants protection and bodily strength to a dying ally</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Melee 1 (one dying creature); The target gains resist 25 all, and a +2 power bonus to death saving throws.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 17</name>Resist 40, and a +3 power bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 27</name>Resist 60, and a +4 power bonus.</line>
         <line>The effect lasts until the target is no longer dying or until the shroud is removed (a standard action), whichever comes first.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Sigil of Companionship</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This medal, which can be strapped to a leg or hung around a neck, signifies the depth of experience you and your companion have working together</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>16</value>
         <price>45,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>26</value>
         <price>1,125,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Companion Item</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>While you flank an enemy with your companion wearing this item, you both gain a +2 item bonus to damage rolls against that enemy.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 16</name>+3 item bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 26</name>+4 item bonus.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Silence-Warded Room</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This lush chamber offers privacy for your conversations</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>420</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Structure</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You speak the command word to activate this effect. You can use this power again to end the effect.</line>
         <line>While the effect is active, creatures outside of the room attempting to liston to something in the room take a -10 penalty to their Perception checks and passive Perception to do so.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Silent Tool</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This mundane-looking tool muffles the noise you make while you work</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When used to do the work it was designed for, a silent tool makes practically no noise. For example, a silent crowbar could aid attempts to open a locked door without alerting the sleeping monster on the other side, while a silent grappling hook has less chance of being heard by nearby guards.</line>
         <line>You gain a +5 item bonus to Stealth checks related to using the tool.</line>
         <line>Any individual mundane tool -a woodcutter's axe, a crowbar, a hammer, a shovel, and so on- can be made silent. Weapons, clothing, jewelry, or other mundane objects cannot.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Sitar of Restfulness</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>The sweet sounds of this breathtaking wooden stringed instrument instill a luck that can be realized only through boldness of action</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attackenh"/>
      <headline crit="d8"></headline>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line auto="bardinstrument"/>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Short</action><subaction>Rest</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>At the end of the rest, you and each ally who remained within 20 squares of you during the rest gains 6 temporary hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 12 or 17</name>10 temporary hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 22 or 27</name>15 temporary hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Song of Rest</name>Allies benefiting from your Song of Rest bard class feature instead gain 5 additional temporary hit points.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Solitaire (Cinnabar)</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This jagged red crystal boosts your resilience when you hit your foes hard</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
      <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
      <line><name>Trigger</name>You score a critical hit on your turn</line>
      <line><name>Effect</name>You make a saving throw against an effect that a save can end.</line>
      <line><name>Special</name>You can only use one <![CDATA[<i>solitaire</i>]]> in a given encounter.</line>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Solitaire (Quartz Lens)</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This clouded crystal supplements your powers with the energy of the sun</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Varies</keyword>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>You score a critical hit on your turn</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Choose either fire damage or radiant damage. This power gains the corresponding keyword.</line>
         <line>The triggering hit deals the chosen type of damage in addition to its normal damage type or types, and gains the corresponding keyword for that hit.</line>
         <line><name>Special</name>You can only use one <![CDATA[<i>solitaire</i>]]> in a given encounter.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Spellshard</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This shard of obsidian or crystal can be imbued with magical knowledge</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Properties</name>
         <line>A spellshard has the following properties:</line>
         <line><bullet />Rituals, Wizard spells, and similar effects can be stored in the shard. Each item is stored as mental information rather than written words. A spellshard is equivalent to a spellbook or a ritual book for the purposes of holding such information.</line>
         <line indent="1">The cost of storing the information is unchanged, and using the stored information functions normally in all ways.</line>
         <line><bullet />A spellshard can be enchanted like it were a tome implement.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Stalker's Flint</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>A warm, bright fire quickly erupts from a single spark struck off this magical shard</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Illusion</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You light a campfire using this flint.</line>
         <line>The fire burns without smoke or sound, and sheds bright light to a radius of 10 squares. The light is invisible from outside its radius, though creatures and objects within that area can be seen if the surrounding lighting conditions allow it or if a viewer has darkvision.</line>
         <line>The campfire is a normal fire in all other respects, burning as long as it has fuel or until extinguished normally.</line>
         <line>The flint can be used to light lanterns and other fires as normal, but such fires gain no magical qualities.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Stonemeal Biscuit</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This coarse dwarven fare tastes foul but keeps you going throughout the day</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>30</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>650</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Consumable</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>A single stonemeal biscuit weighs one-tenth of a pound.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Healing</keyword>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You eat the biscuit. It provides you with the nutrition equivalent to a full day's worth of food.</line>
         <line>The first time during this day that you spend a healing surge to regain hit points, you regain 2 additional hit points.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 13</name>4 additional hit points.</line>
         <line>You also gain a +2 power bonus to Endurance checks for 12 hours.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Stylus of the Translator</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This writing implement allows you to sribe in translation</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Creation</name>
         <line>When this stylus is created, the creator chooses any one language.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Everything written with this stylus is in the language chosen when it was created, regardless of which language the writer is actually writing.</line>
         <line>Using this power again ends the effect.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Sun Globe</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>After being installed in a socket on the wall or ceiling, these fist-sized crystal globes shed light when commanded</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>180</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Structure</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>You can command this globe as a free action. It can be commanded to shed either bright light or dim light, or shed no light. It can shed light either 5 or 10 squares in all directions.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Tattoo of Arcane Blood</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>Rods, orbs, the eye of Ioun, and other images symbolic of magic are used for this tattoo</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>14</value>
         <price>21,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>24</value>
         <price>525,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Attack Power</name>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Force</keyword>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <line><name>Trigger</name>An enemy bloodies you</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>The triggering enemy takes force damage equal to your Constitution modifier.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 14 or 19</name>Equal to 2 + your Constitution modifier.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 24 or 29</name>Equal to 5 + your Constitution modifier.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Tattoo of Bonded Defense</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>One hero standing before a wounded ally is perfect for these tattoos</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>900</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The first time you become bloodied during an encounter, each ally who can see you and that also has a <![CDATA[<i>tattoo of bonded defense</i>]]> can shift 1 square towards you as an opportunity reaction.</line>
         <line>An ally who can see you and that has a <![CDATA[<i>tattoo of bonded escape</i>]]> can shift 1 square away from you as an opportunity reaction.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Tattoo of Bonded Escape</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>The image of a surly dwarf holding a corridor while allies escape works well for these tattoos</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>900</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>The first time you become bloodied during an encounter, each ally who can see you and that also has a <![CDATA[<i>tattoo of bonded escape</i>]]> can shift 1 square away from you as an opportunity reaction.</line>
         <line>An ally who can see you and that has a <![CDATA[<i>tattoo of bonded defense</i>]]> can shift 1 square towards you as an opportunity reaction.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Tattoo of Vengeance</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This tattoo shows wicked-looking blades and bolts of lightning, representing the comeuppance you will extract</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Tattoo</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>Whenever an enemy scores a critical hit against you and deals damage, you gain a +3 item bonus to damage rolls against that enemy until the end of the encounter.</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 15:</i>]]> +6 item bonus</line>
         <line indent="1"><![CDATA[<i>Level 25:</i>]]> +9 item bonus</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Tempest Fan</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>The tines of this metal fan resemble lightning, augmented with ripples of electricity</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>5</value>
         <bonus>+1</bonus>
         <price>1,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>10</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>5,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>15</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>25,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>20</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>125,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>25</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>625,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>30</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>3,125,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attackenh"/>
      <headline crit="d6">lightning</headline>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>If you are a Wizard, you can use this fan as an implement for Wizard powers.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Attack Power</name>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword> <keyword>Lightning</keyword> <keyword>Teleportation</keyword>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 1 (you, or one ally in the burst); The target teleports up to 5 squares, and then must activate the burst effect as a nonaction reaction.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15 or 20</name>Teleports up to 10 squares.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 25 or 30</name>Teleports up to 15 squares.</line>
         <line><name>Burst Effect</name>Close burst 3 (each enemy in the burst); Each target takes 1d6 lightning damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 15 or 20</name>2d8 lightning damage.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 25 or 30</name>3d12 lightning damage.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Unreadable Ink</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>You look at a blank folio, seeing the hidden message there wihile others see nothing</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>30</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>8</value>
         <price>125</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Consumable</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You activate the ink. It remains active for 1 hour, after which any unused ink dries and becomes unusable. While the ink is activate, you can use it to write a message up to one page long (250 words) to a specific recipient you must concentrate on while writing.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 8</name>For 8 hours, and either up to 40 pages (10,000 words) or one page with up to 10 recipients.</line>
         <line>Once the ink is no longer active, all the writing disappears, and only the chosen recipient can see it. The message's recipient need not be able to read the inscription, or even be literate. The recipient magically understands the full message as soon as he or she touches whatever material it was scribed upon.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Vision Sands</title>
      <category>Rare</category>
      <fluff>This sparkling crystalline sand enhances divinations</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>75</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Consumable</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Consumable</frequency>
         <action>Special</action> <subaction/>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>Use this power when you begin casting a divination ritual.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You gain a +4 bonus to any one skill check made as part of the ritual. You must decide to add this bonus before making the check.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Vistani Tambourine</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>A tiny drum with ringing bells, or zils, this instrument help you keep a lively tempo despite difficulty</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <bonus>+1</bonus>
         <price>520</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>7</value>
         <bonus>+2</bonus>
         <price>2,600</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <bonus>+3</bonus>
         <price>13,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>17</value>
         <bonus>+4</bonus>
         <price>65,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <bonus>+5</bonus>
         <price>325,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>27</value>
         <bonus>+6</bonus>
         <price>1,625,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="attackenh"/>
      <headline crit="d6"/>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line auto="bardinstrument"/>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must be wielding the tambourine in one hand</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Close burst 5 (you and each ally in the burst); Each target can ignore difficult terrain until the end of your next turn.</line>
         <line>You move up to your speed.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Watchful Ruby Eye</title>
      <category>Uncommon</category>
      <fluff>This crimson get set in gold and silver enhances your warding rituals</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>6</value>
         <price>1,800</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>16</value>
         <price>45,000</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>26</value>
         <price>1,125,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>While grasping this gem, you gain a +3 item bonus to any skill checks made as part of a warding ritual.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 16</name>+6 item bonus.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 26</name>+10 item bonus.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Wheely Sled</title>
      <category>Rare</category>
      <fluff>This sheet of solid metal sits on four wheels and is long enough for one person to lie down on, with a number of levers and switches accessible from the side</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>4</value>
         <price>840</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <headline auto="losttech"/>
      <block>
         <name>Malfunction</name>
         <line>When this sled's power malfunctions, you move 5 squares in a random direction and fall prone in a square adjacent to the sled.</line>
      </block>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Requirement</name>You must be lying on the sled.</line>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Roll a d20.</line>
         <line>On a result of 2 - 20, you move up to 10 squares over the ground. You ignore difficult terrain during this move.</line>
         <line>On a result of 1, the sled malfunctions.</line>
      </block>
   </item>
   
   <item>
      <title>Window of Deception</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>A glance through this fine glass window reveals whatever you desire</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>3</value>
         <price>340</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>8</value>
         <price>1,700</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>13</value>
         <price>8,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>18</value>
         <price>42,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>23</value>
         <price>212,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>28</value>
         <price>1,062,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Structure</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <keyword>Illusion</keyword>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>You create an illusion seen by any creature looking through the window. The illusion is static and remains until the window is broken or opened, or until this power is used to change the illusion or end it.</line>
         <line>The window can maintain a separate illusion in each direction, and a character using this power can change either or both at once.</line>
         <line>A creature taking its time to examine the illusion can attempt a Perception check against a Hard DC of the window's level. On a success, the creature can tell that it is looking at an illusion, but still can't see what is on the other side of the window.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Window of Escape</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>When you need to get out of a room in a hurry, this unremarkable window is your best escape</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>2</value>
         <price>260</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>12</value>
         <price>6,500</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>22</value>
         <price>162,500</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type> <subtype>Structure</subtype>
      <block>
         <name>Property</name>
         <line>When you jump or fall out of this window, you take damage as if the fall was 50 feet shorter.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 12</name>150 feet shorter.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 22</name>You take no damage regardless of distance.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

   <item>
      <title>Woundstitch Powder</title>
      <category>Common</category>
      <fluff>This worn leather pouch contains a replenishing quantity of life-saving yellow powder</fluff>
      <level>
         <value>1</value>
         <price>360</price>
      </level>
      <level>
         <value>11</value>
         <price>9,000</price>
      </level>
      <type>Wondrous Item</type>
      <block>
         <name>Utility Power</name>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <line><name>Effect</name>Melee touch (one creature); If the target is dying, it stops making death saving throws until it takes damage.</line>
         <line>If the target is taking untyped ongoing damage, it makes a saving throw against all such effects.</line>
         <line indent="1"><name>Level 11</name>With a +5 bonus to the save.</line>
      </block>
   </item>

</catalog>
