<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Tiefling</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Heirs of a shattered empire who live in the shadows and do not fear the dark</shortfluff>
	
	<height>5'6" - 6'2"</height>
	<weight>140 - 230</weight>
	
	<ability>Charisma</ability>
    <ability>Constitution</ability>
    <ability>Intelligence</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Low-light Vision</vision>
	
	<language>Common</language> <language>choice of one other</language>
	
	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
        <description>+2 Bluff, +2 Stealth</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Bloodhunt</name>
		<description>You gain a +1 racial bonus to attack rolls against bloodied enemies.</description>
	</trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fire Resistance</name>
        <description>You have resist fire equal to 5 + one-half your level.</description>
    </trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Tiefling Racial Power</name>
        <description>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>infernal wrath</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>
	
	<fluff>Heirs to an ancient, infernal bloodline, tieflings have no realms of their own but instead live within human kingdoms and cities. They are descended from human nobles who bargained with dark powers, and long ago their empire subjugated half the world. But the empire was cast down into ruin, and tieflings were left to make their own way in a world that often fears and resents them.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a tiefling if you want to: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be a hero who has a dark side to overcome.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be good at tricking, intimidating, or persuading other to do your will.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to attempt to redeem your people's image.</fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Infernal Wrath</title>
			<class>Tiefling</class> <category>Attack</category>
			<fluff>You call upon the hellfire burning in your soul to punish your enemy</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
                <keyword>Fire</keyword>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
                <type>Close</type> <range>burst 10</range>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An enemy within 10 squares of you hits you with an attack</text>
				</section>
                <section>
                    <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                    <text>The triggering enemy in the burst</text>
                </section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The target takes 1d6 + Intelligence modifier or Charisma modifier fire damage.</text>
				</section>
                <section>
                    <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                    <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                    <text>2d6 + Intelligence modifier or Charisma modifier fire damage.</text>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                    <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                    <text>3d6 + Intelligence modifier or Charisma modifier fire damage.</text>
                </section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Tieflings' appearance testifies to their infernal bloodline. They have large horns; thick, nonprehensile tails that range in length from 4 to 5 feet; sharply pointed teeth; and eyes that are solid orbs of black, red, white, silver, or gold. Their skin color covers the whole human range and also extends to reds, from a ruddy tan to a brick red. Their hair, cascading down from behind their horns, is as likely to be dark blue, red, or purple as more common human colors.</benefit>
		<benefit>Tieflings favor dark colors and reds, leathers and glossy furs, small spikes and buckles. Tiefling-crafted arms and armor often have an archaic style, harkening back to the glory of their long-vanished empire.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Tiefling</name>
		<benefit>Hundreds of years ago, the leaders of the human empire of Bael Turath made pacts with devils to solidify their hold over its enormous territory. Those humans became the first tieflings, and they governed their empire in the name of their infernal masters. In time, Bael Turath came into conflict with Arkhosia, the ancient empire of the dragonborn, and decades of warfare left both empires in ruins. Bael Turath's grand capital was thrown down in ruin.</benefit>
		<benefit>Tieflings are the heirs of the surviving noble dynasties that ruled the empire. Their bloodline is tainted by their diabolical connections, passing to their descendants through all generations. In many ways, they are human: they can have children with humans, for example, but their offspring are always tieflings.</benefit>
		<benefit>Centuries of other races' distrust and outright hatred have made tieflings self-reliant and often too willing to live up to the stereotypes imposed on them. As a race without a homeland, tieflings know that they have to make their own way in the world and that they have to be strong to survive, and they are not quick to trust anyone who claims to be a friend. However, when a tiefling's companions demonstrate that they trust him or her, the tiefling quickly learns to extend the same trust to them. And once a tiefling gives someone trust and loyalty, the tiefling is a firm friend and ally for life.</benefit>
		<benefit>Although the nobles of Bael Turath subjugated themselves to devils, most present-day tieflings give little thought to gods or patrons, preferring to look out for themselves. Therefore, they do not often follow the path of the divine; tiefling clerics and paladins are rare.</benefit>
		<benefit>Tieflings are not numerous. Sometimes a tiefling merchant clan that is descended from a Bael Turath dynasty settles as a group in a land where wealth can purchase safety and comfort. But most tieflings are born outside such hidden dynasties and grow up in the roughest quarters of human cities and towns. These tieflings often become swindlers, thieves, or crime lords, who carve out a niche for themselves amid the squalor of their surroundings.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Tiefling Charasteristics:</b>]]> Cunning, disquieting, imposing, mysterious, proud, rebellious, self-reliant, sinister, sly, unconventional</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Akmenos, Amnon, Barakas, Bamakos, Ekemon, Iados, Kairon, Leucis, Melech, Morthos, Pelaios, Skamos, Therai</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Akta, Bryseis, Damaia, Ea, Kallista, Lerissa, Makaria, Nemeia, Orianna, Phelaia, Rieta</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<benefit>Some young tieflings, striving to find a place in the world, choose a name that signifies a concept and then try to embody the concept. For some, the chosen name is a noble quest. For others, it's a grim destiny.</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Modern Names:</b>]]> Art, Carrion, Chant, Despair, Fear, Gladness, Hope, Ideal, Music, Nowhere, Open, Poetry, Quest, Random, Reverence, Sorrow, Torment, Weary</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Sample Human Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Akmenos, Tiefling Warlock</name>
			<benefit>Akmenos is torn between good and evil. He longs to fit into the human society in which he lives and would like to call himself genuinely good. At the same time, he fears that his soul is irretrievably tainted by the touch of evil -both the evil in his blood and the sinister nature of his infernal pact. He feels as if he is on a tightrope between good and evil and might eventually fall either way.</benefit>
			<benefit>His companions recognize the good in his heart and trust him, and that trust has been enough on some days to keep Akmenos from sliding into evil. His life is tormented, and though he believes he is called to a great destiny, he is not sure whether he will become a hero or a villain.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Kallista, Tiefling Warlord</name>
			<benefit>Kallista prays daily that Bahamut will help her keep her commitment to live justly and honorably. She has no love for Bahamut's priests and temples, but she feels a personal connection to the Platinum Dragon, which inspires her to acts of nobility and sacrifice.</benefit>
			<benefit>She leads a group of adventurers in strikes against evil forces but dreams of one day leading an army under Bahamut's banner. In his name, she struggles to keep her violent temper and cruel streak under tight control.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Random, Tiefling Rogue</name>
			<benefit>Random is a native of the streets and alleys of a human city and no stranger to poverty, mistrust, or prejudice. As far as he's concerned, good and evil are a matter for priests and philosophers to discuss in their marble temples and universities. The reality of life on the street is survival, and he's willing to do what is necessary to survive.</benefit>
			<benefit>As part of an adventuring group, he has had his first taste of wealth and discovered that he likes it, but he hasn't forgotten his roots. He has also had his first taste of trust and friendship, which are growing on him as well.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A tiefling can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>
		
		<power>
			<title>Hellish Gaze</title>
			<class>Tiefling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>Seeing doom reflected in your fiery eyes, your enemy turns away from your countenance</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Fear</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Ranged</type> <range>5</range>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<text>Using this power does not trigger an <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attack</i>]]> from the target</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>One creature that can see you</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Check:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Intimidate vs. passive Insight</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Success:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You push the target 1 square, and it cannot make <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i>]]> against you until the start of your next turn.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Grim Isolation</title>
			<class>Tiefling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>You move with surprising swiftness, accomplishing more than most would think possible</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Martial, Stance</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You assume the Grim Isolation stance.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Until the stance ends, you gain a +2 power bonus to all defenses while no ally is adjacent to you.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Hellfire Shroud</title>
			<class>Tiefling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>Flickering black flames swirl around you to shield you from harm and punish those who would attack you</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Arcane, Fire</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Until the end of your next turn, you gain the following benefits:</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<text>&#9658; +2 power bonus to all defenses.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<text>&#9658; Whenever an enemy adjacent to you hits you with a melee attack, that enemy takes fire damage after the attack has been resolved. The fire damage equals 4 + your Intelligence modifier or your Charisma modifier.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>2</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Equal to 8 + your Intelligence modifier or your Charisma modifier.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Eternal Returns</title>
			<class>Tiefling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>Your defeat opens a door for your return to the world</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Arcane, Healing</keyword>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You drop to 0 hit points or less</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You are not knocked unconscious due to your hit points dropping to 0 hit points or less.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>After the attack has been resolved, you are removed from play until the start of your next turn.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>At the start of your next turn, you can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your healing surge value. You then return to play in an unoccupied space of your choice within 5 squares of the space you previously occupied.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
</race>
