<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Tiefling</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Heirs of a shattered empire who live in the shadows and do not fear the dark</shortfluff>
	
	<height>5'6" - 6'2"</height>
	<weight>140 - 230</weight>
	
	<ability>Charisma</ability>
    <ability>Constitution</ability>
    <ability>Intelligence</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Low-light Vision</vision>
	
	<language>Common</language> <language>choice of one other</language>
	
	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
        <description>+2 Bluff, +2 Stealth</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Bloodhunt</name>
		<description>You gain a +1 racial bonus to attack rolls against bloodied enemies.</description>
	</trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fire Resistance</name>
        <description>You have resist fire equal to 5 + one-half your level.</description>
    </trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Tiefling Racial Power</name>
        <description>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>infernal wrath</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>
	
	<fluff>Heirs to an ancient, infernal bloodline, tieflings have no realms of their own but instead live within human kingdoms and cities. They are descended from human nobles who bargained with dark powers, and long ago their empire subjugated half the world. But the empire was cast down into ruin, and tieflings were left to make their own way in a world that often fears and resents them.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a tiefling if you want to: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be a hero who has a dark side to overcome.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be good at tricking, intimidating, or persuading other to do your will.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to attempt to redeem your people's image.</fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Infernal Wrath</title>
			<class>Tiefling</class> <category>Attack</category>
			<fluff>You call upon the hellfire burning in your soul to punish your enemy</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
                <keyword>Fire</keyword>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
                <type>Close</type> <range>burst 10</range>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An enemy within 10 squares of you hits you with an attack</text>
				</section>
                <section>
                    <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                    <text>The triggering enemy in the burst</text>
                </section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The target takes 1d6 + Intelligence modifier or Charisma modifier fire damage.</text>
				</section>
                <section>
                    <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                    <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                    <text>2d6 + Intelligence modifier or Charisma modifier fire damage.</text>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                    <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                    <text>3d6 + Intelligence modifier or Charisma modifier fire damage.</text>
                </section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Tieflings' appearance testifies to their infernal bloodline. They have large horns; thick, nonprehensile tails that range in length from 4 to 5 feet; sharply pointed teeth; and eyes that are solid orbs of black, red, white, silver, or gold. Their skin color covers the whole human range and also extends to reds, from a ruddy tan to a brick red. Their hair, cascading down from behind their horns, is as likely to be dark blue, red, or purple as more common human colors.</benefit>
		<benefit>Tieflings favor dark colors and reds, leathers and glossy furs, small spikes and buckles. Tiefling-crafted arms and armor often have an archaic style, harkening back to the glory of their long-vanished empire.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Tiefling</name>
		<benefit>Hundreds of years ago, the leaders of the human empire of Bael Turath made pacts with devils to solidify their hold over its enormous territory. Those humans became the first tieflings, and they governed their empire in the name of their infernal masters. In time, Bael Turath came into conflict with Arkhosia, the ancient empire of the dragonborn, and decades of warfare left both empires in ruins. Bael Turath's grand capital was thrown down in ruin.</benefit>
		<benefit>Tieflings are the heirs of the surviving noble dynasties that ruled the empire. Their bloodline is tainted by their diabolical connections, passing to their descendants through all generations. In many ways, they are human: they can have children with humans, for example, but their offspring are always tieflings.</benefit>
		<benefit>Centuries of other races' distrust and outright hatred have made tieflings self-reliant and often too willing to live up to the stereotypes imposed on them. As a race without a homeland, tieflings know that they have to make their own way in the world and that they have to be strong to survive, and they are not quick to trust anyone who claims to be a friend. However, when a tiefling's companions demonstrate that they trust him or her, the tiefling quickly learns to extend the same trust to them. And once a tiefling gives someone trust and loyalty, the tiefling is a firm friend and ally for life.</benefit>
		<benefit>Although the nobles of Bael Turath subjugated themselves to devils, most present-day tieflings give little thought to gods or patrons, preferring to look out for themselves. Therefore, they do not often follow the path of the divine; tiefling clerics and paladins are rare.</benefit>
		<benefit>Tieflings are not numerous. Sometimes a tiefling merchant clan that is descended from a Bael Turath dynasty settles as a group in a land where wealth can purchase safety and comfort. But most tieflings are born outside such hidden dynasties and grow up in the roughest quarters of human cities and towns. These tieflings often become swindlers, thieves, or crime lords, who carve out a niche for themselves amid the squalor of their surroundings.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Tiefling Charasteristics:</b>]]> Cunning, disquieting, imposing, mysterious, proud, rebellious, self-reliant, sinister, sly, unconventional</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Akmenos, Amnon, Barakas, Bamakos, Ekemon, Iados, Kairon, Leucis, Melech, Morthos, Pelaios, Skamos, Therai</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Akta, Bryseis, Damaia, Ea, Kallista, Lerissa, Makaria, Nemeia, Orianna, Phelaia, Rieta</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<benefit>Some young tieflings, striving to find a place in the world, choose a name that signifies a concept and then try to embody the concept. For some, the chosen name is a noble quest. For others, it's a grim destiny.</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Modern Names:</b>]]> Art, Carrion, Chant, Despair, Fear, Gladness, Hope, Ideal, Music, Nowhere, Open, Poetry, Quest, Random, Reverence, Sorrow, Torment, Weary</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Sample Human Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Brandis, Human Fighter</name>
			<benefit>Brandis is a mercenary who has sold his sword arm to every baronet, duke, and princeling from the mountains to the coast. His armor is practical, lacking any decoration, and his sword is intended only for battle, not as a mark of prestige. He prays daily to the Raven Queen -not out of devotion but because he knows that death is inevitable and he hopes to postpone it as long as possible.</benefit>
			<benefit>He began adventuring after a mission ended in disaster. His soldier companions were all dead, and he was captured by hobgoblins and held for ransom that no one cared enough to pay. He joined the band of adventurers that slew the hobgoblins. He has since found adventuring both more lucrative and more satisfying than his previous life.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Mari, Human Ranger</name>
			<benefit>Mari's eyes are always on the horizon. She is driven by a passion for exploration and a love of new places. She dreams of ultimately establishing a new settlement in a place where people can live in peace and freedom. She prays to Avandra for protection in her wandering and to Erathis for help in achieving her dreams.</benefit>
			<benefit>She is aware of her life's contradiction: She is a creature of the wilderness, but her dream is to tame and cultivate it. A part of her wonders whether she would be able to settle in the village she dreams of founding.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Thom, Human Wizard</name>
			<benefit>Thom's one desire is for power. He adventures in search of arcane lore and ancient artifacts that will increase his mastery of magic.</benefit>
			<benefit>He prays to Ioun because he sees knowledge as the key to power, but he is also drawn to Vecna, wondering what power the god of secrets might offer him in exchange for his devotion.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A human can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>
		
		<power>
			<title>Extra Effort</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>You dig deep to find the strength to overcome an affliction</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You make a saving throw and dislike the result</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You reroll the saving throw with a +2 power bonus, and must use the new result.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Rapid Move</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>You move with surprising swiftness, accomplishing more than most would think possible</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You take a move action.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Flush with Success</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>You feel your confidence build with each attack that hits home</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You hit with an attack on your turn</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You gain 10 temporary hit points, and can then shift up to half your speed.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>15 temporary hit points.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Courageous Determination</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>Your enemy's success pales before your stalwart resolve as you refuse to give up</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Healing</keyword>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An enemy bloodies you with an attack or hits you while you are bloodied</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your healing surge value. You can then shift up to your speed.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Until the start of your next turn, you gain a +2 power bonus to all defenses.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
</race>
