<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="fragment.xsl"?>
<catalog>
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Avandra</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>The power of Avandra allows you to ensure that no bonds can hold your allies for long</fluff>
		<benefit>When an ally adjacent to you makes a saving throw against an effect that includes the slowed, immobilized, or restrained condition, the ally rolls two saving throws and takes the better result.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>You grant one ally adjacent to the target of the triggering attack a saving throw.</effect>
			<effect>If the saving throw is against an effect that includes the slowed, immobilized, or restrained condition, the ally rolls two saving throws and takes the better result.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Impatient</quirk>
		<quirk>Impulsive</quirk>
		<quirk>Insightful</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Bahamut</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>Your ire against any who defy the common good fills you and provides you or your allies with additional protection against your foes</fluff>
		<benefit>While all your encounter attack powers are expended, you gain a +1 bonus to all defenses.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>You or one ally you can see gains a +2 power bonus to all defenses until the end of your next turn.</effect>
			<effect>To gain the benefit, you or the chosen ally must be adjacent to a target of the triggering attack.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Aggressive</quirk>
		<quirk>Guarded</quirk>
		<quirk>Protective</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Corellon</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>The secrets of magic and the wisdom of nature are constant companions to your travels, and  at times they provide you or an ally with the ability to move</fluff>
		<benefit>You gain a +2 feat bonus to Arcana and Nature checks.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<keyword>Teleportation</keyword>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>You or an ally adjacent to you can teleport 5 squares.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Detached</quirk>
		<quirk>Distracted</quirk>
		<quirk>Mercurial</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Erathis</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>You understand the desires of the civilized and the fears of those who dwell in savagery, which allows you to better communicate as well as anticipate a foe's next move</fluff>
		<benefit>You gain a +2 feat bonus to Diplomacy checks.</benefit>
		<benefit>You gain one additional language.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<keyword>Fear</keyword>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
			<trigger>You target enemies with a divine encounter or daily attack</trigger>
			<effect>The targets of the triggering attack take a -2 penalty to attack rolls against you until the end of your next turn.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Arrogant</quirk>
		<quirk>Inspired</quirk>
		<quirk>Strong-minded</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Ioun</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>Wisdom floods your mind, revealing the cosmos' secrets - sometimes you see the most vulnerable area of your foe's defenses as you strike</fluff>
		<benefit>When you make a knowledge check, roll two checks and take the best result.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
			<trigger>You have rolled damage for a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>Reroll any number of the triggering damage dice.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Distracted</quirk>
		<quirk>Intellectual</quirk>
		<quirk>Studious</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Kord</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>You veel vigor and life flow through your veins, which sometimes allows you to shove away your foes with divine might</fluff>
		<benefit>You gain a +2 feat bonus to Athletics and Endurance.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>You push the targets of the triggering attack 2 squares.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Abrasive</quirk>
		<quirk>Intimidating</quirk>
		<quirk>Lively</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Melora</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>You feel the forces of the wild stir your soul, granting you extra insight into nature, heartier defenses, and an ability to manipulate both friends and foes in battle</fluff>
		<benefit>You gain a +2 feat bonus to Nature checks.</benefit>
		<benefit>Each time you fail a saving throw, you gain a +2 cumulative bonus to the next saving throw you make against that effect.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>You slide one ally adjacent to you or the targets of the triggering attack 2 squares.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Fierce</quirk>
		<quirk>Tranquil</quirk>
		<quirk>Violent</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Moradin</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>You are tough as iron, and you have the mettle to shield your allies from any danger</fluff>
		<benefit>Increase your number of healing surges by one.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>One ally you can see gains temporary hit points equal to your Constitution or Intelligence modifier.</effect>
			<effect>These temporary hit points increase to 4 + your Constitution or Intelligence modifier at 21st level.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Loyal</quirk>
		<quirk>Intolerant</quirk>
		<quirk>Persistent</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Pelor</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>Like the sun, you bring hope to the living and destruction to creatures of shadow</fluff>
		<benefit>Allies adjacent to you roll two saving throws and take the best result when making death saving throws or saving throws against Necrotic effects.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<keyword>Radiant</keyword>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>The attack deals extra radiant damage equal to your Constitution or Intelligence modifier.</effect>
			<effect>This extra radiant damage increases to 3 + your Constitution or Intelligence modifier at 21st level.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Bold</quirk>
		<quirk>Fiery</quirk>
		<quirk>Pompous</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of the Raven Queen</title>
		<tier>God Frogment</tier>
		<fluff>Winter's cold bolsters your mind and body, and those who cross you feel its icy bite as it slows their movements</fluff>
		<benefit>You gain a +2 feat bonus to Intimidate checks.</benefit>
		<benefit>You and your equipment can resist ambient non-magical cold temperatures, suffering no ill effects.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<keyword>Cold</keyword>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>You slow all targets of the attack until the end of your next turn.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Cruel</quirk>
		<quirk>Impartial</quirk>
		<quirk>Steadfast</quirk>
	</fragment>
	
	<fragment>
		<title>Fragment of Sehanine</title>
		<tier>God Fragment</tier>
		<fluff>You find shadows to cloak yourself within them, and no danger can keep you trapped if you wish to be free of it</fluff>
		<benefit>You gain a +2 feat bonus to Stealth checks.</benefit>
		<benefit>You can use Stealth instead of Acrobatics to escape from a grab.</benefit>
		<manifestation>
			<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
			<keyword>Teleportation</keyword>
			<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
			<trigger>You use a divine encounter or daily attack power</trigger>
			<effect>You gain concealment until the start of your next turn.</effect>
			<effect>If you are hit by an attack while you have this concealment, you can teleport 2 squares an an opportunity reaction.</effect>
		</manifestation>
		<quirk>Alluring</quirk>
		<quirk>Cautious</quirk>
		<quirk>Sneaky</quirk>
	</fragment>
		
</catalog>
