<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <collection>Warlord Lvl 5 Daily Attack Exploits</collection>

   <power>
      <title>A Rock and a Hard Place</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>You focus to work in concert with your companions, harrying your opponents with relentless blows</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="special"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you and allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> can use the Relentless Pressure attack at-will. Only one character can use the action during a given turn.
         </section>
      <part>
         <part-name>Relentless Pressure</part-name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Opportunity</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name>An enemy adjacent to the acting character attacks one or more of the character's allies, and misses all  of them
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name><type>Melee</type><range>1</range><target>the triggering enemy</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>The acting character deals damage to the target equal to your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier + the enhancement bonus of the character's weapon. If the acting character can make a <i>melee basic attack</i> using an implement, it can use that implement's enhancement bonus instead of weapon enhancement bonus.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            If the acting character's <i>melee basic attack</i> deals a type of damage, this action deals the same type of damage and gains the corresponding keyword.
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Archery Commander</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your words advice your allies in avoiding retaliatory attacks and guide them to focused attention as they loose arrows and spells at your enemy</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you do not provoke <i>reactive strikes</i> for making ranged attacks, and your <i>warlord's aura</i> gains the following benefits:
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            Allies in the aura gain a +4 bonus to all defenses against <i>reactive strikes</i> triggered by making a ranged attack. You must see the attacking enemy for the ally to gain this benefit.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When an ally hits an enemy you can see with a ranged attack, the next ally in your aura that hits that same enemy with a ranged attack deals additional damage equal your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Bait the Hook</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your attacks and parries give an ally the encouragement and strength needed to respond to the foe's attacks</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When you attack an enemy, choose one ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i>. Until the end of your next turn, the enemy you attack has vulnerable all against the chosen ally's attacks. The vulnerable equals your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When an enemy attacks you, choose one ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i> as a free reaction. The chosen ally has combat advantage against the enemy until the start of that enemy's next turn.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When an enemy bloodies you or scores a critical hit against you, you can use a free reaction to grant all allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> a bonus to their first damage roll against that enemy. The bonus equals your [Wisdom or Charisma] modfier, and lasts until the end of the enemy's next turn.
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Brave Warriors</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your charge emboldens your allies to do the same</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            Your charge attacks deal +1[W] damage (or +1d8 damage if your charge attack is not a <key>Weapon</key> attack).
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When you charge an enemy, allies who can see you gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls against the target of your charge until the end of your next turn. This increases to a +2 bonus for a given ally if he or she charges the enemy.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When you hit with a charge attack, until the end of your next turn, allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> have a +1 power bonus to AC, and a power bonus to Will equal to one-half your [Wisdom or Charisma] modifier.
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Create Opportunity</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your precisely timed attacks disrupt your foe's concentration, buying time for an ally to act</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When you hit an enemy in your <i>warlord's aura</i> with a ranged attack, one ally adjacent to the enemy can use a free reaction to either make a <i>melee basic attack</i> against it or to shift up to a number of squares equal to your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When you hit an enemy with a melee attack, one ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i> can use a free reaction to either make a <i>ranged basic attack</i> against it or to gain a bonus to all defenses against it until the end of your next turn. The bonus equals one-half your [Wisdom or Charisma] modifier.
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Exemplar of Action</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your series of feints and slashes cows your foe, preparing it for your allies</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            You and allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> deal +3 additional damage against enemies that grant combat advantage for the attack, or +5 damage against weakened enemies.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When you hit an enemy with a melee attack, that enemy grants combat advantage to allies in your <i>warlod's aura</i> until the start of your next turn.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            When you hit an enemy granting combat advantage with a melee attack, that enemy is weakened (save ends).
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Pike Hedge</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>You set yourself and your allies to foil enemy movement, ready to strike at anyone who approaches another comrade</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="special"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, you and allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> can use the Punishing Hedge attack at-will. Only one character can use the action during a given turn.
         </section>
      <part>
         <part-name>Punishing Hedge</part-name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Opportunity</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name>An enemy willingly moves to a square that is within the acting character's reach and adjacent to that character's ally
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name><type>Melee</type><range>weapon</range><target>the triggering enemy</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>The acting character deals damage to the target equal to the character's Strength modifier + the enhancement bonus of the character's weapon.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            If the acting character can use a different ability modifier for his or her damage roll on a <i>melee basic attack</i>, he or she can deal damage based on that ability modifier instead. If the acting character can make a <i>melee basic attack</i> using an implement, it can use that implement's enhancement bonus instead of weapon enhancement bonus.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            If the character's <i>melee basic attack</i> deals a type of damage, this action deals the same type of damage and gains the corresponding keyword.
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Scent of Victory</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>As your enemies stagger from their wounds, you can smell victory and your allies respond to your victorious cry</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls against bloodied enemies. This increases to +2 on triggered attack rolls.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            You can also use the Call for Blood attack at-will while this power lasts.
         </section>
      <part>
         <part-name>Call for Blood</part-name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name><type>Close</type> <range>burst 10</range><target>one or two bloodied enemies in the burst, and the same number of allies your <i>warlord's aura</i></target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Each target ally can make a <i>melee basic attack</i> against a different target enemy as an opportunity reaction.
         </section>
         <section shade="">If you have the <i>opportune command</i> class power, you can apply the effects of that power to these attacks.</section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Stand the Fallen</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>You call to your comrades, lifting their spirit and restoring their will to fight</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="special"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, your <i>warlord's aura</i> gains the following benefits:
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1"><bullet/>Allies in the aura can stand from prone as a minor action.</section>>
         <section shade="" indent="1"><bullet/>When you or an ally spend a healing surge to regain hit points, that character gains a +1 power bonus to attack rolls until the end of his or her next turn.</section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            Also, you can use the Rousing Call action at-will until the end of the encounter.
         </section>
      <part>
         <part-name>Rousing Call</part-name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Healing</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction/>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name><type>Close</type><range>special</range><target>each ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i></target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Each target gains temporary hit points equal to one-half his or her healing surge value + your [Wisdom or Charisma] modifier. A bloodied target can choose to regain the same number of hit points instead.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            A target that already had the same amount or more temporary hit points instead gains a bonus to his or her first damage roll before the end of his or her next turn. The bonus equals your [Wisdom or Charisma] modifier.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            A prone target can stand from prone as a free reaction.
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Surging Assault</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your strike gives an ally the means to recover from his or her injuries, and his or her recovery in turn gets your fighting spirit up</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, when you hit with an attack, one ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i> can use his or her <i>second wind</i> as a free reaction.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            Also, when an ally in your aura spends a healing surge to regain hit points, your first attack before the end of your next turn deals an additional +1[W] damage (or +1d8 damage if it is not a <key>Weapon</key> attack). If multiple allies spend a healing surge, you gain an additional +2 bonus to the damage roll for each ally beyond the first.
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Terrain Advantage</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>With your guidance, your team manages to press the advantage against enemies in a precarious position</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <section auto="special"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of the encounter, enemies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> have vulnerable 2 to all damage while they are in difficult terrain.
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            Also, you and allies in your aura gain a bonus to damage rolls when attacking from higher ground. The bonus equals your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.
         </section>
   </power>
</catalog>
