<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   
   <power>
      <title>Deadly Returns</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You create an opening that allows an ally to capitalize on your foe's aggression</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You hit an enemy with a melee attack on your turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals +1[W] additional damage (+1d8 if it is not a Weapon attack), and you choose one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, the triggering enemy provokes an <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attack</i>]]> from the chosen ally when it makes a melee attack against you or the ally.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Fierce Reply</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You answer an attacker's hit against an ally with a vicious riposte</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text><![CDATA[<b>Immediate</b>]]> Interrupt</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy within your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> hits your ally with an attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier, then make a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> against the triggering enemy. On a miss, you deal damage equal to your weapon's enhancement bonus + your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering ally gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>If the triggering attack bloodied the ally or reduced him or her to 0 hit points or less, your attack deals additional damage equal to your Charisma modifier, and you can use your Charisma modifier when determining the damage on a miss.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If you did not shift the full distance, the triggering ally can shift the remaining distance as a free reaction.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Friendly Fire</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>Such is your presence that you panic an enemy into accidentally hitting one of its allies</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> misses you or an ally with a melee or ranged attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering enemy</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target rerolls the triggering attack against a creature you choose. The chosen creature must be within 2 squares of the original target of the triggering attack, and must be a valid target for the attack.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>General's Gift</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You are generous as well as brave, and your presence alone can keep an ally from surrendering to weariness and wounds</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You gain a +1 cumulative bonus to the first attack roll you make this turn for each bloodied ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>. In addition, until the end of your next turn, you can use the following action at-will:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Free Interrupt:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text><![CDATA[<i>Trigger:</i> An ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i>]]> would spend a a healing surge; You expend a healing surge on the triggering ally's behalf.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>Each time you use this action, you gain a +2 cumulative bonus to the first damage roll you make before the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
</catalog>
