<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <power>
      <title>A Rock and a Hard Place</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>You focus to work in concert with your companions, harrying your opponents with relentless blows</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, you and allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can use the Relentless Pressure attack at-will. Only one character can use the action during a given turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
      <part>
         <part-name>Relentless Pressure</part-name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Opportunity</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <type>Melee</type> <range>1</range>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy adjacent to the character attacks one or more of the character's allies, and misses all targets</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering enemy</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The character deals damage to the target equal to your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier + the enhancement bonus of the character's weapon.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the character's <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> deals a type of damage, this action deals the same type of damage and gains the corresponding keyword.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Archery Commander</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your words advice your allies in avoiding retaliatory attacks and guide them to focused attention as they loose arrows and spells at your enemy</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, you do not provoke <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i> for making ranged attacks, and your <i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gains the following benefits:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; Allies in the aura do not provoke <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i>]]> from enemies you can see when making ranged attacks.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When an ally hits an enemy you can see with a ranged attack, the next ally in your aura to hit that enemy with a ranged attack deals additional damage equal your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Bait the Hook</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your attacks and parries give an ally the encouragement and strength needed to respond to the foe's attacks</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When you attack an enemy, choose one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>. Until the end of your next turn, the target of your attack has vulnerable all against the chosen ally's attacks. The vulnerable equals your Intelligence modifier or Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When an enemy attacks you, choose one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> as a free reaction. The chosen ally has combat advantage against the enemy until the start of that enemy's next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When an enemy bloodies you or scores a critical hit against you, you can use a free reaction to grant all allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> a bonus to their first damage roll against that enemy. The bonus equals your Wisdom modifier or Charisma modfier, and lasts until the end of the enemy's next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Brave Warriors</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your charge emboldens your allies to do the same</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; Your charge attacks deal +1[W] damage, or +1d8 damage if your charge attack is not a Weapon attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When you charge an enemy, allies who can see you gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls against the target of your charge until the end of your next turn. This increases to +2 if the ally charges the enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When you hit with a charge attack, until the end of your next turn, allies gain a +1 power bonus to AC, and a power bonus to Will equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier or one-half your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Create Opportunity</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your precisely timed attacks disrupt your foe's concentration, buying time for an ally to act</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When you hit an enemy in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> with a ranged attack, one ally adjacent to the enemy can use a free reaction to either make a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> against it or to shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier or Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When you hit an enemy with a melee attack, one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can use a free reaction to either make a <![CDATA[<i>ranged basic attack</i>]]> against it or to gain a bonus to all defenses against it until the end of your next turn. The bonus equals one-half your Wisdom modifier or one-half your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Exemplar of Action</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>Your series of feints and slashes cows your foe, preparing it for your allies</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, you gain the following benefits:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; You and allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> deal +3 additional damage against enemies that grant combat advantage for the attack, or +5 damage against weakened enemies.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When you hit an enemy with a melee attack, that enemy grants combat advantage until the start of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; When you hit an enemy granting combat advantage with a melee attack, that enemy is weakened (save ends).</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Pike Hedge</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>5</level>
      <fluff>You set yourself and your allies to foil enemy movement, ready to strike at anyone who approaches another comrade</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Tactic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, you and allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can use the Punishing Hedge attack at-will. Only one character can use the action during a given turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
      <part>
         <part-name>Punishing Hedge</part-name>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Opportunity</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy willingly moves to a square adjacent to an ally and within the character's reach</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering enemy</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The character deals damage to the target equal to the target's Strength modifier + the enhancement bonus of the character's weapon.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the character can use a different ability modifier for his or her damage roll on a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]>, he or she can deal damage based on that ability modifier instead.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the character's <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> deals a type of damage, this action deals the same type of damage and gains the corresponding keyword.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
</catalog>
