<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
	<name>Warlord</name>
	<subname>Tactician</subname>
	<role>Leader</role>
	<source>Martial</source>
	<shortfluff>You rally your companions with a mixture of shouted commands and cunning stratagems, leading them to victory through superior tactics.</shortfluff>
	<keyability>Strength</keyability>
	<keyability>Intelligence</keyability>
	<keyability>Wisdom</keyability>
	<keyability>Charisma</keyability>
	
	<proficiency>
		<type>Armor</type>
		<name>Cloth</name>
		<name>Leather</name>
		<name>Hide</name>
		<name>Chainmail</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Shield</type>
		<name>Heavy</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Weapon</type>
		<name>Simple melee</name>
		<name>Military melee</name>
		<name>Simple ranged</name>
	</proficiency>
	
	<defense>
		<name>Fortitude</name>
		<value>+1</value>
	</defense>
	<defense>
		<name>Will</name>
		<value>+1</value>
	</defense>
	
	<hpbase>12</hpbase>
	<hpgain>5</hpgain>
	<surgebase>7</surgebase>
	
	<skills>
		<trained>Diplomacy, Heal, or Intimidate</trained>
		<number>3</number>
	</skills>
	
	<fluff>Where a marshal leads their allies through example and might of arm, a tactician does his or her job through a steely presence. While a tactician may very well be an excellent warrior, it is his or her tactical acumen, eye for opportunity and inspiring countenance that form the basis of his or her abilities. </fluff>
	<fluff>That does not mean that a tactician prefers to stay far away from battle. The eye of battle affords the most opportunities for him or her to seize the chance and turn even the hardest battle into an easy victory. </fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Commanding Presence</name>
		<benefit>A tactician's presence can shape a battle's outcome, help allies find new reserves, or reveal an opportunity to seize a swift victory.</benefit>
		<benefit>Your demeanor and your approach determine how you lead your allies, whether you inspire them to push harder and reach farther or you command them to take advantage of your enemies' vulnerabilities. Choose one of Inspiring Presence, Resourceful Presence, Skirmishing Presence, or Tactical Presence to best fit your style.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Inspiring Presence</name>
			<benefit>You lead by helping your allies find courage and endurance within themselves. When your allies push themselves, they feel a swell of confidence that helps them overcome their injuries.Your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gains the following benefits: </benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally regains a number of hit points equal to one-half your level + your Charisma modifier after the effects of the action point have been resolved.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura uses his or her <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, he or she regains additional points equal to your Charisma modifier.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At fifth level, when an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally can make a saving throw against a single condition or effect before the effects of the action point are resolved. He or she can attempt a saving throw against an effect even if the effect does not normally allow a saving throw, and adds your Charisma modifier as a bonus to this saving throw.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658;At tenth level, a bloodied ally in the aura that uses <![CDATA[<i>total defense</i>]]> gains resist against all damage equal to your Charisma modifier.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Resourceful Presence</name>
			<benefit>Your watchful eye and versatility help your allies survive in varied situations. Your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gains the following benefits: </benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally gains a bonus to all defenses equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier until the start of their next turn.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura uses his or her <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, he or she can choose to either gain your Wisdom modifier as a bonus on their first attack roll before the end of his or her next turn or as a bonus to all defenses against the first attack made against him or her before the end of his or her next turn.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At fifth level, when an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally gains temporary hit points equal to your one-half your level + your Wisdom modifier.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At tenth level, a bloodied ally in the aura that uses <![CDATA[<i>total defense</i>]]> gains an Aura 1 until the end of his or her next turn. Enemies who end their turn in the aura take damage equal to your Wisdom modifier. The damage increases to 3 + your Wisdom modifier at 11th level, and to 6 + your Wisdom modifier at 21st level.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Skirmishing Presence</name>
			<benefit>Your guidance helps your allies maneuver to better position when they push their offense. Your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gains the following benefits: </benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658;When an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally can use a free interrupt to shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier before or after the effects of the action point have been resolved.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658;When an ally in the aura uses his or her <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, he or she can shift a number of squares equal to one-half your Intelligence modifier as part of the same action.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658;At fifth level, when an ally in the aura spends an action point on his or her turn, he or she can choose to gain either an offensive benefit or a defensive benefit. The ally can choose the offensive benefit if he or she has moved closer to the target of the attack since the start of his or her turn, and the benefit is bonus to the damage rolls of one attack. The ally can choose the defensive benefit if he or she has moved further away from at least one enemy and not closer to any enemies since the start of his or her turn, and the benefit is one-half your Intelligence modifier to all defenses until the start of the ally's next turn.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658;At tenth level, a bloodied ally in the aura who uses <![CDATA[<i>total defense</i>]]> can shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier as part of the same action.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Tactical Presence</name>
			<benefit>Your keen acumen helps your allies to optimize their strikes. Your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gains the following benefits: </benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura spends an action point on his or her turn, he or she gains a bonus to the first attack roll before the end of his or her turn. The bonus equals one-half your Intelligence modifer.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura uses his or her <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, he or she gains a bonus on the first attack roll before the end of his or her next turn equal to your Intelligence modifier.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At fifth level, when an ally in the aura spends an action point on his or her turn, the first attack she makes before the end of his or her turn gains a bonus to the damage roll equal to your Intelligence modifier.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At tenth level, a bloodied ally in the aura who uses <![CDATA[<i>total defense</i>]]> gains a bonus to his or her first attack roll and damage before the end of his or her next turn. The bonus equals one-half your Intelligence modifier.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Leader's Strategy</name>
		<benefit>Every tactician has a knack with a certain kind of leadership. Choose one of Battlefront Leader, Canny Leader, or Combat Leader to represent your knack.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Battlefront Leader</name>
			<benefit>You gain proficiency with heavy shields, and the <![CDATA[<i>battlefront shift</i>]]> power.</benefit>
			
			<power>
				<title>Battlefront Shift</title>
				<class>Warlord</class> <category>Utility </category>
				<fluff>As combat breaks out, you give a quick call, urging an ally to move or spurring yourself to take action</fluff>
				<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Martial</keyword>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Close </type> <range>burst 5</range>
				<section>
					<name-style>bold</name-style>
					<name>Trigger:</name>
					<text>You roll initiative</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name-style>bold</name-style>
					<name>Target:</name>
					<text>You or one one ally in the burst</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name-style>italic</name-style>
					<name>Level 11:</name>
					<text>You and one ally, or two allies</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name-style>italic</name-style>
					<name>Level 21:</name>
					<text>You and two allies, or three allies</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name-style>bold</name-style>
					<name>Effect:</name>
					<text>The target shifts half his or her speed. </text>
				</section>
				</part>
			</power>
			
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Canny Leader</name>
			<benefit>You and any ally within 10 squares of you who can see and hear you gain a +2 bonus to Insight and Perception checks.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Combat Leader</name>
			<benefit>You and any ally within 10 squares of you who can see and hear you gain a +2 bonus to Initiative.</benefit>
		</subfeature> 
		
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Strategic Reservoir</name>
		<benefit>A tactician knows that while he or she can improvise during most battles, it is wise to have a couple of different tactics prepared as contingencies.</benefit>
		<benefit>At first level, you gain two 1st-level Warlord daily attack powers with the Tactic keyword, but each day you can use only one Warlord daily atack. You do not need to make the choice of which power you have available when you regain your daily attack powers. Instead, using one locks away the other until you regain the use.</benefit>
		<benefit>When you gain a Warlord daily attack at 5th level, you gain two powers with the Tactic keyword and can now use two Warlord daily attack powers each day, but no more than one of a particular level.</benefit>
		<benefit>Similarly, when you gain a Warlord daily attack power at 9th level, you gain two powers with the Tactic keyword and can now use three Warlord daily attack powers per day, but still no more than one of a particular level.</benefit>
		<benefit>At levels 15, 19, 25, and 29, you gain two new Warlord daily attack powers with the Tactic keyword without having to replace a power, but the number of daily Warlord attack powers you can use per day remains at three.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Tactician's Command</name>
		<benefit>While a tactician can hold their own in a fight, they know that often it is better to point out an opportunity to their allies than to take one themselves.</benefit>
		<benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>tactician's command</i>]]> power.</benefit>
		
		<power>
			<title>Tactician's Command</title>
			<class>Warlord</class> <category>Utility</category> 
			<fluff>You eye the battle vigilantly, and at the right moment point out an opportunity to an ally</fluff>
			<part>
			<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
			<keyword>Martial</keyword>
			<action>Standard </action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
			<type>Close </type> <range>burst 10</range>
			<section>
				<name-style>bold</name-style>
				<name>Target:</name>
				<text>One enemy you can see in the burst, and one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]></text>
			</section>
			<section>
				<shade>true</shade>
				<name-style>bold</name-style>
				<name>Effect:</name>
				<text>The target ally makes a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> or a <![CDATA[<i>ranged basic attack</i>]]> against the target enemy as a free reaction.</text>
			</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Warlord's Aura</name>
		<benefit>When danger strikes, often the only thing standing between your allies and their defeat is their morale. Your ability to push them past their limits gives them (and you) the energy to fight on.</benefit>
		<benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> power. In addition to the benefits listed here, your Warlord at-will attacks give the aura additional benefits.</benefit>
		
			<power>
				<title>Warlord's Aura</title>
				<class>Warlord</class> <category>Utility </category> 
				<fluff>Your very presence encourages your allies to press on, allowing them to call forth the strength to battle on a little longer</fluff>
				<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Aura, Martial</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name-style>bold</name-style>
					<name>Effect:</name>
					<text>You activate an aura 5 that lasts until the end of the encounter. If the aura ends prematurely for any reason, you can reactivate it during the encounter as a minor action.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Whenever you complete an extended rest, choose one warlord at-will attack that modifies your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>. When you activate the aura, it is automatically modified by that power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>In addition, the Draw Inspiration action, below, can be used twice during the encounter, as long as your aura is active.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 16:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Three times during the encounter.</text>
				</section>
				</part>
				<part>
				<part-name>Draw Inspiration</part-name>
				<frequency>Special</frequency>
				<keyword>Healing, Martial</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<type2>Close</type2> <range2>burst 5</range2>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can use this action as a personal power. You can use it as a personal power, or as a close burst with the following target:</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>One dying ally in the burst</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Effect: </name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The character taking this action (or the target) can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to his or her healing surge value plus an additional 1d6 hit points.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<text>If you used this action on a dying ally and are adjacent to the target, the additional hit points regained is equal to the maximum result and the target can stand up as a free reaction.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 6:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>2d6 additional hit points.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>3d6 additional hit points.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 16:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>4d6 additional hit points.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>5d6 additional hit points.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 26:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>6d6 additional hit points.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You count as having a warlord's <![CDATA[<i>inspiring word</i>]]> class power, and feats and abilities that affect it can be used to modify this action instead.</text>
				</section>
				</part>
			</power>
			
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Words of Encouragement</name>
		<benefit>All tacticians know enough healing techniques that even if they can't mend broken bones or knit together torn flesh, their allies feel the confidence to push on regardless with a little rest.</benefit>
		<benefit>By tending to wounds, sharing inspiring words and showing your own confidence, you and all allies you interact with during a short rest are affected by your Words of Encouragement for that rest.</benefit>
		<benefit>When an affected character spends a healing surge at the end of a rest, that character regains an additional number of hit points equal to your highest ability modifier with each healing surge.</benefit>
		<benefit>The additional hit points increase by 2 at 5th level, by 4 at 15th level, and by 6 at 25th level.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Optional Feature: Archer Warlord</name>
		<benefit>While most warlords focus their martial training towards melee combat, some choose a different path.</benefit>
		<benefit>If you choose this feature, you do not gain proficiency with chainmail armor and with light shields.</benefit>
		<benefit>You instead gain proficiency with military ranged weapons.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
</class>
