<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
	<name>Warlord</name>
	<subname>Tactician</subname>
	<role>Leader</role>
	<source>Martial</source>
	<shortfluff>You rally your companions with a mixture of shouted commands and cunning stratagems, leading them to victory through superior tactics.</shortfluff>
	<keyability>Strength</keyability>
	<keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
	<keyability>Intelligence</keyability>
	<keyability>Wisdom</keyability>
	<keyability>Charisma</keyability>
	
	<proficiency>
		<type>Armor</type>
		<name>Cloth</name>
		<name>Leather</name>
		<name>Hide</name>
		<name>Chainmail</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Shield</type>
		<name>Heavy</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Weapon</type>
		<name>Simple melee</name>
		<name>Military melee</name>
		<name>Simple ranged</name>
	</proficiency>
	
	<defense>
		<name>Fortitude</name>
		<value>+1</value>
	</defense>
	<defense>
		<name>Will</name>
		<value>+1</value>
	</defense>
	
	<hpbase>12</hpbase>
	<hpgain>5</hpgain>
	<surgebase>7</surgebase>
	
	<skills>
		<trained>Diplomacy, Heal, or Intimidate</trained>
		<number>3</number>
	</skills>
	
	<fluff>Where a marshal leads their allies through example and might of arm, a tactician does his or her job through a steely presence. While a tactician may very well be an excellent warrior, it is his or her tactical acumen, eye for opportunity and inspiring countenance that form the basis of his or her abilities. </fluff>
	<fluff>That does not mean that a tactician prefers to stay far away from battle. The eye of battle affords the most opportunities for him or her to seize the chance and turn even the hardest battle into an easy victory. </fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Commanding Presence</name>
		<benefit>A tactician's presence can shape a battle's outcome, help allies find new reserves, or reveal an opportunity to seize a swift victory.</benefit>
		<benefit>Your demeanor and your approach determine how you lead your allies, whether you inspire them to push harder and reach farther or you command them to take advantage of your enemies' vulnerabilities. Choose one of Inspiring Presence, Resourceful Presence, Skirmishing Presence, or Tactical Presence to best fit your style.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Inspiring Presence</name>
			<benefit>You lead by helping your allies find courage and endurance within themselves. When your allies push themselves, they feel a swell of confidence that helps them overcome their injuries.Your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gains the following benefits: </benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally regains a number of hit points equal to one-half your level + your Charisma modifier after the effects of the action point have been resolved.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura uses his or her <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, he or she regains additional points equal to your Charisma modifier.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At fifth level, when an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally can make a saving throw against a single condition or effect before the effects of the action point are resolved. He or she can attempt a saving throw against an effect even if the effect does not normally allow a saving throw, and adds your Charisma modifier as a bonus to this saving throw.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658;At tenth level, a bloodied ally in the aura that uses <![CDATA[<i>total defense</i>]]> gains resist against all damage equal to your Charisma modifier.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Resourceful Presence</name>
			<benefit>Your watchful eye and versatility help your allies survive in varied situations. Your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gains the following benefits: </benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally gains a bonus to all defenses equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier until the start of their next turn.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; When an ally in the aura uses his or her <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, he or she can choose to either gain your Wisdom modifier as a bonus on their first attack roll before the end of his or her next turn or as a bonus to all defenses against the first attack made against him or her before the end of his or her next turn.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At fifth level, when an ally in the aura spends an action point, that ally gains temporary hit points equal to your one-half your level + your Wisdom modifier.</benefit>
			<benefit>&#9658; At tenth level, a bloodied ally in the aura that uses <![CDATA[<i>total defense</i>]]> gain an Aura 1 until the end of his or her next turn. Enemies who end their turn in the aura take damage equal to your Wisdom modifier. The damage increases to 3 + your Wisdom modifier at 11th level, and to 6 + your Wisdom modifier at 21st level.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Skirmishing Presence</name>
		</subfeature>
		
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Leader's Strategy</name>
		<benefit>Every tactician has a knack with a certain kind of leadership. Choose one of Battlefront Leader, Canny Leader, or Combat Leader to represent your knack.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Battlefront Leader</name>
			<benefit>You gain proficiency with heavy shields, and the <![CDATA[<i>battlefront shift</i>]]> power.</benefit>
			
			<power>
				<title>Battlefront Shift</title>
				<class>Warlord</class> <category>Utility </category>
				<fluff>As combat breaks out, you give a quick call, urging an ally to move or spurring yourself to take action</fluff>
				<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Martial</keyword>
				<action>No Action</action>
				<type>Close </type> <range>burst 5</range>
				<section>
					<name-style>bold</name-style>
					<name>Trigger:</name>
					<text>You roll initiative</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name-style>bold</name-style>
					<name>Target:</name>
					<text>You or one one ally in the burst</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name-style>italic</name-style>
					<name>Level 11:</name>
					<text>You and one ally, or two allies</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name-style>italic</name-style>
					<name>Level 21:</name>
					<text>You and two allies, or three allies</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name-style>bold</name-style>
					<name>Effect:</name>
					<text>The target shifts half his or her speed. </text>
				</section>
				</part>
			</power>
			
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Canny Leader</name>
			<benefit>You and any ally within 10 squares of you who can see and hear you gain a +2 bonus to Insight and Perception checks.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Combat Leader</name>
			<benefit>You and any ally within 10 squares of you who can see and hear you gain a +2 bonus to Initiative.</benefit>
		</subfeature> 
		
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Words of Encouragement</name>
		<benefit>All tacticians know enough healing techniques that even if they can't mend broken bones or knit together torn flesh, their allies feel the confidence to push on regardless with a little rest.</benefit>
		<benefit>By tending to wounds, sharing inspiring words and showing your own confidence, you and all allies you interact with during a short rest are affected by your Words of Encouragement for that rest.</benefit>
		<benefit>When an affected character spends a healing surge at the end of a rest, that character regains an additional number of hit points equal to your highest ability modifier with each healing surge.</benefit>
		<benefit>The additional hit points increase by 2 at 5th level, by 4 at 15th level, and by 6 at 25th level.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
</class>
