<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   
   <power>
      <title>Deadly Returns</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You create an opening that allows an ally to capitalize on your foe's aggression</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You hit an enemy with a melee attack on your turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals +1[W] additional damage (+1d8 if it is not a Weapon attack), and you choose one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, the triggering enemy provokes an <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attack</i>]]> from the chosen ally when it makes a melee attack against you or the ally.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Fierce Reply</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You answer an attacker's hit against an ally with a vicious riposte</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text><![CDATA[<b>Immediate</b>]]> Interrupt</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy within your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> hits your ally with an attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier, then make a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> against the triggering enemy. On a miss, you deal damage equal to your weapon's enhancement bonus + your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering ally gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>If the triggering attack bloodied the ally or reduced him or her to 0 hit points or less, your attack deals additional damage equal to your Charisma modifier, and you can use your Charisma modifier when determining the damage on a miss.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If you did not shift the full distance, the triggering ally can shift the remaining distance as a free reaction.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Friendly Fire</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>Such is your presence that you panic an enemy into accidentally hitting one of its allies</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> misses you or an ally with a melee or ranged attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering enemy</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target rerolls the triggering attack against a creature you choose. The chosen creature must be within 2 squares of the original target of the triggering attack, and must be a valid target for the attack.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>General's Gift</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You are generous as well as brave, and your presence alone can keep an ally from surrendering to weariness and wounds</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You gain a +1 cumulative bonus to the first attack roll you make this turn for each bloodied ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>. In addition, until the end of your next turn, you can use the following action at-will:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Free Interrupt:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text><![CDATA[<i>Trigger:</i> An ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i>]]> would spend a a healing surge; You expend a healing surge on the triggering ally's behalf.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>Each time you use this action, you gain a +2 cumulative bonus to the first damage roll you make before the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Join the Crowd</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You swing at a nearby foe and drive it back into the area of an ally's explosive attack</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An ally makes a close or an area attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You make a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> against a creature that is not a target of the triggering attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You can shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier before making the attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>On a hit, you slide the creature a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier. The creature must end the slide inside the triggering attack's area of effect, or closer to it than it started.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the creature ends the slide inside the triggering attack's area of effect, the triggering ally gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering ally gains a bonus to the triggering attack's attack roll against the creature you attacked. The bonus equals 1 + one-half your Wisdom modifier (minimum +2 bonus).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering ally gains a bonus to the triggering attack's damage roll against the creature you attacked. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Lion's Roar</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>With a bellowing roar, you attack your foe, breaking through its defenses, with the ferocity of your attack reinvigorating you or an ally in need</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Healing, Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You, or you and one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]></text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls with the first melee attack you make during your current turn, and that attack deals +1[W] damage (+1d8 damage if it is not a Weapon attack).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You also gain a bonus to all defenses against attacks triggered by your movement until the end of your current turn. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Either you or a target ally can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to his or her healing surge value.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If an ally spends the healing surge, he or she regains additional hit points equal to 2 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The character spending the healing surge gains a bonus to all defenses until the end of your next turn. The bonus equals one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The character spending the healing surge gains a bonus to the first damage roll he or she makes before the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Phalanx Assault</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>From behind your ready shield, you pound your foe and bark an order, calling for defensive tactics</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must be using a shield.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You hit with a melee attack on your own turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals +2[W] damage (+2d8 damage if it is not a Weapon attack).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gain a +1 power bonus to AC and Reflex. This increases to a +2 power bonus if the ally is adjacent to either you or another ally using a shield.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>A bloodied ally increases the bonus he or she gains by +1.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Allies in the aura also gain a +1 power bonus to attack rolls when adjacent to an ally.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Allies using a shield in the aura do not provoke <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i>]]> for movement while this bonus remains.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An ally using a shield in the aura also gains a bonus to melee damage rolls. The bonus equals one-half your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Provoke Overextension</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You goad the enemy into pressing too far, setting it up for a counterstike</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>, and either you or an ally in the aura</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target enemy makes a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i> against you as an opportunity interrupt. If the enemy makes a <i>meleee basic attack</i>, it can choose to treat it as an <i>opportunity attack</i>. If the enemy makes a <i>ranged basic attack</i>, it does not provoke <i>opportunity attacks</i>]]> from your allies. If the enemy is unable to make the attack, the power fails and you immediately regain the use of this power.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>After the enemy's attack has been resolved, choose either you or a target ally. The chosen character can make a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]> against the target enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the enemy's attack missed you and you make the attack, your attack deals +2[W] damage (+2d8 damage if it is not a Weapon attack). If the enemy's attack hit you and an ally makes the attack, his or her attack deals +2[W] damage (+2d8 damage if it is not a Weapon attack).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The character that makes the attack gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You or the ally can use any at-will melee or ranged attack, not just a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The character making the attack can shift before making the attack. The shift is up to a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The character making the attack gains a bonus to the damage. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Sacrificial Lure</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>Leaving yourself wide open, you allows your allies to move in for a decisive strike</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You take a -2 penalty to AC and Reflex until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If an enemy makes an attack against you while you have this penalty, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gain a bonus to attack rolls against the target equal to one-half your Intelligence modifier or one-half your Wisdom modifier. The bonus lasts until the start of that enemy's next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If you are hit by a melee attack while you have this penalty, choose one defense. While you have the penalty, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gain a bonus to the chosen defense equal to your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>If you are hit by a melee attack more than once, you can choose to change which defense has the bonus, but the bonus can only be applied to one defense at a time.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If you are hit by a melee attack while you have this penalty, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gain a bonus to all defenses equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier. The bonus lasts while you have the penalty.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If you are hit by a melee attack while you have this penalty, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can shift a number of squares equal to one-half your Intelligence modifier (minimum 1 square) as a free reaction.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If you are hit by a melee attack while you have this penalty, each ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gain a bonus to his or her first damage roll against the enemy that hit you. The bonus is lost if the ally does not roll damage against the enemy before the end of his or her next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>If multiple enemies hit you with a melee attack, allies gain the bonus against each.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Sudden Motivation</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>Your passionate war cry inspires a burst of motivation in your allies, sending them darting across the battlefield</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You hit an enemy with an attack on your turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals +1[W] damage (+1d8 if it is not a Weapon attack) damage to the triggering enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, each ally that begins his or her turn in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can take an additional move action during that turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Sunder Armor</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>You probe the defenses of your foe until you can land a blow that momentarily leaves it susceptible to other attacks</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have made a melee attack this turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One creature you have attacked this turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can score a critical hit against the target on a roll of 18 to 20.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Allies also gain a bonus to attack rolls on <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i>]]> against the target. The bonus equals one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Also, the first melee attack that hits the target before the end of your next turn deals +1[W] damage (+1d8 if it is not a Weapon attack).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The first ally that hits the target gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The first attack that hits the target deals additional damage equal to Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Tactician's Favor</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>7</level>
      <fluff>Your attack causes an ally's follow-up strike to cement his or her tactical advantage</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have made an attack during this turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One creature you have attacked this turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The first time an ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> hits the target before the end of your next turn, the target takes +1[W] additional damage (+1d8 damage if the attack is not a Weapon attack), and the ally gains your choice of one of the following benefits. The benefit lasts until the end of the ally's next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; A power bonus to all defenses equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier or one-half your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; +1 bonus to attack rolls.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; A power bonus to damage rolls equal to your Intelligence modifier or Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
</catalog>
