<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <collection>Warlord Lvl 3 Encounter Attack Exploits</collection>

   <power>
      <title>Battering Command</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>The slam of your weapon causes your foe to double over, enabling an ally to capitalize on the opening</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You hit an enemy with a melee attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>special</range>
            <target>one ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i></target>
         </section>
         <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>The target can make a <i>basic attack</i> against the triggering enemy as either a free interrupt or free reaction.</section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target gainst temporary hit points equal to your Charisma modifier. If the target is bloodied, he or she gains 5 + your Charisma modifier temporary hit points instead.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target can shift a number of squares equal to one-half your Intelligence modifier before making the attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The triggering attack also knocks the triggering enemy prone.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Bloody Ending</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You guide your allies to finish off a wounded foe</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, you and allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> have a +1 bonus to attack rolls against bloodied enemies, and and can score critical hits on a natural roll of 19 or 20 against them.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You and allies in the aura also have a bonus to AC against bloodied enemies. The bonus equals one-half your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You and allies can choose to have combat advantage instead of scoring critical hits on a natural roll of 19 or 20.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You and allies also gain a power bonus to damage rolls against bloodied enemies. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If you hit a bloodied enemy with an attack, the bonus to attack rolls increases to +2.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Deadly Distraction</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You strike your foe hard, delivering a wound that keeps them distracted while you and your allies reposition</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>On your turn, you hit an enemy with a melee or ranged attack</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="special"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals +1[W] additional damage, or +1d8 additional damage if it isn't a Weapon attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, while the triggering enemy remains in your <i>warlord's aura</i>, it cannot trigger actions based on you and your allies' movement.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Devastating Setup</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You knock the enemy aside and call forth a nearby ally to capitulate</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have the <i>opportune command</i> class power.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Melee</type> <range>1</range>
            <target>one creature adjacent to you</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You either slide the target 1 square, or push it up to 3 squares.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>You then use your <i>opportune command</i> class power, and must choose the target as the target enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the target ally hits, he or she can end one effect on himself or herself that a save can end. If the target ally has no effect that a save can end, he or she can attempt a saving throw against one effect that doesn't normally end on a save.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the target ally's attack hits, the target enemy takes a penalty to all attack rolls with the first attack it makes before the end of your next turn. The penalty equals one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ally can shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier before making the attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ally's attack deals additional damage equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Dicey Predicament</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Surrounded by enemies, you fake weakness and make them careless</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must either be flanked, or be adjacent to 3 or more non-minion enemies.</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section shade="">
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> gain combat advantage against enemies adjacent to you.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>If you hit an enemy with a melee attack, allies also gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls against that enemy while it remains within your reach.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Follow Me In</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You rush into battle with a decisive attack, rallying your friends behind you</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
            <target>you, and each ally in the burst who can see or hear you</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each target ally gains a +1 bonus to speed until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The bonus equals one-half your Intelligence modifier (minimum +1).</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>You charge an enemy. Your charge attack deals an additional +1[W] damage (+1d8 additinal damage if it is not a Weapon attack).</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>If your charge attack hits, allies benefiting from the speed bonus deal additional damage against the enemy you charged. The damage equals one-half your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If an ally benefiting from the speed bonus charges the same enemy you charged, they have a bonus to all defenses triggered by that charge. The bonus equals your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An ally benefiting from the speed bonus has a bonus to all defenses triggered by their movement. This bonus equals one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If an ally benefiting from the speed bonus charges the same enemy you charged, the additional damage increases to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Hold the Line</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Hearing your snap commands, your allies hold their ground</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You, or one or more allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> would be pushed, pulled, or slid</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>special</range>
            <target>each triggering creature</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering forced movement is negated, and one target makes a <i>basic attack</i> as a free reaction against the source of the forced movement.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each target has resist all equal to 2 + your Charisma modifier against the triggering attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The ally making the attack can make a melee or ranged at-will attack instead of a <i>basic attack</i>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each target can shift one-half the distance of the forced movement (minimum 1 square) as a free reaction.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The ally making the attack gains a bonus to the damage roll equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Inspire Resilience</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You follow a solid hit with words that bolster your allies</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have hit an enemy with an attack during your current turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section shade="">
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the start of your next turn, allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> have resist all equal to 2 + one-half your [Wisdom or Charisma] modifier. If you scored a critical hit during your current turn, the resistance increases by +3.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>If an enemy attacks an ally benefiting from this resistance, that ally gains a bonus to the first damage roll he or she makes against that enemy before the end of his or her next turn. The bonus equals your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Inspiring War Cry</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>As you strike, you shout a fierce war cry that shakes your foe and jolts a friend from succumbing to trouble</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Fear, Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>On your turn, you hit an enemy within 5 squares of you with an attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
            <target>the triggering enemy, and one ally in the burst who can hear you</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target enemy takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls until the start of your next turn. The penalty increases to -3 if your triggering attack was a critical hit.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The target ally can make a saving throw against one effect that a save can end. If your triggering attack was a critical hit, the target ally can make a saving throw against any one effect, even if it normally doesn't allow a save.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the target ally is not under any harmful or negative effect, he or she instead gains a +3 bonus to the first attack roll he or she makes before the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Interrupting Combo</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Your weapon strikes a foe, forcing it to focus on you lest an ally gets a chance for a strike of his or her own</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>On your turn, you hit an enemy with a melee or ranged attack</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="special"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You deal additional damage equal to your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier to the triggering enemy, and mark it until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>While it remains marked, the first time the enemy makes an attack that does not include you as a target, one ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i> can take an immediate interrupt to make a <i>basic attack</i> against the marked enemy. If the ally's attack hits, the marked enemy takes a -2 penalty to all attack rolls on the triggering attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If you have the <i>opportune commmand</i> class power, the enemy and ally count as the target ally and target enemy for all effects.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Martial Doom</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You probe an enemy with an attack, then point out an opening that any ally with will or daring can seize</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Special</type>
            <target>one enemy that you have attacked during your current turn</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> have combat advantage against the target, and deal additional damage against it equal to one-half your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Each time an ally hits the target with an attack made during an extra action gained by spending an action point, the additional damage increases by +2.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>No Gambit Is Wasted</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Noticing that an ally failed at a difficult feat, you interrupt the flow of combat to give him or her another chance to use the attack</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One ally in in your <i>warlord's aura</i> misses every target with an encounter or daily attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>special</range>
            <target>the triggering ally, and either you or another ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i></target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the triggering attack was an encounter attack, the triggering ally regains the use of that power at the start of his or her next turn and gains a +2 bonus to attack rolls with the regained power during that turn. If the triggering attack was a daily attack, he or she regains the use of that power the next time he or she takes a short rest.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering ally gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Either the triggering ally or the second target can shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier as a free interrupt.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The second target makes a <i>basic attack</i> against a target of the triggering attack as an opportunity reaction.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The second target can use a melee or ranged at-will attack instead of a <i>basic attack</i>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The second target gains a bonus to the attack roll equal to one-half your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Shielding Retaliation</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You guide an ally to a powerful retaliation while protecting another that has come under assault</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy hits an ally adjacent to you</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>special</range>
            <target>you, and one ally in your <i>warlord's aura</i></target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack hits you instead, and the target ally makes a <i>basic attack</i> against the triggering enemy as a free reaction to the enemy's attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ally gains a bonus to the damage roll equal to your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ally gains a bonus to the attack roll equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Either the triggering ally or the target ally can shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier as a free interrupt.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ally makes his or her attack as a free interrupt to the triggering attack hitting you.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Warlord's Strike</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>One convincing strike is all you need to expose the enemy's weakness and spur your allies into finishing it off</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>On your turn, you hit an enemy with a melee attack</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="special"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals +1[W] additional damage (+1d8 additional damage if the attack is not a Weapon attack).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your <i>warlord's aura</i> have a bonus to damage rolls against the triggering enemy. The bonus equals one-half your [Intelligence or Wisdom] modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your aura have a bonus to all defenses against the triggering enemy equal to your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your aura gain a bonus to all defenses equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your aura gain gain a +1 bonus to speed and a bonus to all defenses against attacks triggered by their movement equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The bonus to damage equals your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

</catalog>
