<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   
   <power>
      <title>Battering Command</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>The slam of your weapon causes your foe to double over, enabling an ally to capitalize on the opening</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You hit an enemy with a melee attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack also knocks the enemy prone.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]></text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>After the triggering attack is resolved, the target makes a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]> against the triggering enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target gainst temporary hit points equal to your Charisma modifier. If the target is bloodied, he or she 5 + your Charisma modifier temporary hit points instead.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target can shift a number of squares equal to one-half your Intelligence modifier before making the attack.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Bloody Ending</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You guide your allies to finish off a wounded foe</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, you and allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls and and score critical hits on a natural roll of 19 or 20 against bloodied enemies.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If you hit a bloodied enemy with an attack, the bonus increases to +2.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You and allies the aura also gain a bonus to AC against bloodied enemies. The bonus equals one-half your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You and allies can choose to have combat advantage instead of scoring critical hits on a natural roll of 19 or 20.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You and allies also gain a power bonus to damage rolls against bloodied enemies. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Deadly Distraction</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You strike your foe hard, delivering a wound that keeps them distracted while you and your allies reposition</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You hit an enemy with a melee or ranged attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals +1[W] additional damage, or +1d8 additional damage if it isn't a Weapon attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, while the triggering enemy remains in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>, it cannot trigger actions based on you and your allies' movement.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Devastating Setup</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You knock the enemy aside and call forth a nearby ally to capitulate</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Melee</type> <range>1</range>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have the <![CDATA[<i>tactician's command</i>]]> class power.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One creature adjacent to you</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You either slide the target 1 square, or push it up to 3 squares.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>You then use your <![CDATA[<i>tactician's command</i>]]> and must choose the target as the target enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the target ally hits, he or she can end one effect on himself or herself that a save can end. If the target ally has no effect that a save can end, he or she can attempt a saving throw against one effect that doesn't normally end on a save.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the target ally's attack hits, the target enemy takes a penalty to its first attack's attack rolls equal to one-half your Wisdom modifier until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ally can shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier before making the attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ally's attack deals additional damage equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Dicey Predicament</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Surrounded by enemies, you fake weakness and make them careless</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must either be flanked, or be adjacent to 3 or more non-minion enemies.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> gain combat advantage against enemies adjacent to you.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <text>If you hit an enemy with a melee attack, allies also gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls against the enemy while it remains adjacent to you.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Follow Me In</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You rush into battle with a decisive attack, rallying your friends behind you</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You, and each ally in the burst who can see or hear you</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each target ally gains a +1 bonus to speed until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The bonus equals one-half your Intelligence modifier (minimum +1).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You charge an enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <text>If your charge attack hits, allies benefiting from the speed bonus deal additional damage against the enemy you charged. The damage equals one-half your Intelligence modifier or one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If an ally benefiting from the speed bonus charges the same enemy you charged, they have a bonus to all defenses triggered by that charge. The bonus equals your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An ally benefiting from the speed bonus has a bonus to all defenses triggered by their movement. This bonus equals one-half your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If an ally benefiting from the speed bonus charges the same eny you charged, the additional damage increases to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Hold the Line</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Hearing your snap commands, your allies hold their ground</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You or an ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> would be pushed, pulled, or slid</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each triggering creature</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering forced movement is negated, and one target makes a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]> against the source of the forced movement.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each target has resist all equal to 2 + your Charisma modifier against the triggering attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The ally making the attack can make a melee or ranged at-will attack instead of a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each target can shift one-half the distance of the forced movement (minimum 1 square) as a free reaction.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The ally making the attack gains a bonus to the damage roll equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Inspire Resilience</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You follow a solid hit with words that bolster your allies</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have hit an enemy with an attack during your current turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the start of your next turn, allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> have resist all equal to 2 + one-half your Wisdom modifier or one-half your Charisma modifier. If you scored a critical hit during your current turn, the resistance increases by +3.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <text>If an enemy attacks an ally benefiting from this resistance, that ally gains a bonus to their first damage roll against the enemy. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier, and the bonus is lost if the ally does not make the attack before the end of his or her next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Inspiring War Cry</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>As you strike, you shout a fierce war cry that shakes your foe and jolts a friend from succumbing to trouble</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Fear, Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>On your turn, you hit an enemy within 5 squares of you with an attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering enemy, and one ally in the burst who can hear you</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target enemy takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls until the start of your next turn. The penalty increases to -3 if your triggering attack was a critical hit.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The target ally can make a saving throw against one effect that a save can end. If your triggering attack was a critical hit, the target ally can make a saving throw against any one effect, even if it normally doesn't allow a save.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the target ally is not under any harmful or negative effect, he or she instead gains a +2 bonus to the first attack roll he or she makes before the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Interrupting Combo</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Your weapon strikes a foe, forcing it to focus on you lest an ally gets a chance for a strike of his or her own</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>On your turn, you hit an enemy with a melee or ranged attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering attack deals additional damage equal to your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier, and you mark the target of that attack until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>While it remains marked, the first time the enemy makes an attack that does not include you as a target, one ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> can take an immediate interrupt to make a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]> against the marked enemy. If the ally's attack hits, the marked enemy takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls on the triggering attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If you have the <![CDATA[<i>tactician's commmand</i>]]> class power, the ally gains the same benefits from your at-will attack as if he or she was the target ally of your command.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Martial Doom</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>You probe an enemy with an attack, then point out an opening that any ally with will or daring can seize</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One enemy that you have attacked during your current turn</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, the target grants combat advantage to allies in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If any of your allies attacks the target with an attack made during any extra action gained by spending an action point, he or she deals additional damage equal to your Intelligence modifier or your Wisdom modifier. For each such attack that hits, the additional damage increases by +1.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>No Gambit Is Wasted</title>
      <class>Warlord</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
      <fluff>Noticing that an ally failed at a difficult feat, you interrupt the flow of combat to give him or her another chance to use the attack</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Martial</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <type>Special</type>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One ally in in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]> misses every target with an encounter or daily attack</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering ally, and either you or another ally in your <![CDATA[<i>warlord's aura</i>]]></text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the triggering attack was an encounter attack, the triggering ally regains the use of that power at the start of his or her next turn and gains a +2 bonus to attack rolls with the regained power during that turn. If the triggering attack was a daily attack, he or she regains the use of that power the next time he or she takes a short rest.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Inspiring Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The triggering ally gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + your Charisma modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The second target makes a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]> against a target of the triggering attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Resourceful Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The second target can use a melee or ranged at-will attack instead of a <![CDATA[<i>basic attack</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Skirmishing Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Either the triggering ally or the second target can shift a number of squares equal to your Intelligence modifier before other parts of this power resolved.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Tactical Presence:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The second target gains a bonus to the attack roll equal to one-half your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
</catalog>
            
