<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Dragonborn</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Proud, honorable warriors, born from the blood of an ancient dragon god</shortfluff>
	
	<height>6'2" - 6'8"</height>
	<weight>220 - 320</weight>
	
	<ability>Charisma</ability>
    <ability>Strength</ability>
    <ability>Constitution</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Normal</vision>
	
	<language>Common</language> <language>Draconic</language>
	
	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
        <description>+2 History, +2 Intimidate</description>
	</trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Draconic Heritage</name>
        <description>You add your Constitution modifier to your healing surge value.</description>
    </trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Dragonborn Fury</name>
		<description>While you're bloodied, you gain a +1 racial bonus to attack rolls.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Dragonborn Racial Power Selection</name>
        <description>Choose an option for your character:</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Dragon Breath:</i> You have the <i>dragon breath</i>]]> racial power.</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Dragonfear:</i> You have the <i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>
	
	<fluff>Born to fight, dragonborn are a race of wandering mercenaries, soldiers, and adventurers. Long ago, their empire contended for worldwide dominion, but now only a few rootless clans of these honorable warriors remain to pass on their legends of ancient glory.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a dragonborn if you want to: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to look like a dragon.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be the proud heir of an ancient, fallen empire.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to breathe acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison, or to inspire fear.</fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Dragon Breath</title>
			<class>Dragpnborn</class> <category>Attack</category>
			<fluff>As you open your mouth with a roar, the deadly power of your draconic kin blasts forth to engulf your foes</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Varies</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Close</type> <range>blast 3</range>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Each creature in the blast</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Ability +2 vs. Reflex</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +4</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +6</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>1d6 + Constitution modifier damage.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>2d6 + ability modifier damage.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>3d6 + ability modifier damage.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>When you gain this power, choose Strength or Constitution. You use the chosen ability score when making attack rolls and damage rolls with this power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<text>Also, choose one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison. Your <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i>]]> deals damage of the chosen type, and has the corresponding keyword.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Dragonfear</title>
			<class>Dragonborn</class> <category>Attack</category>
			<fluff>Your presence causes your enemies to quake and tremble</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Fear</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
				<section>
					<indent>2</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text><![CDATA[<b>Close</b>]]> burst 10</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Each enemy in the burst</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Ability +2 vs. Will</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +4</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +6</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The target is stricken with fear until the end of your next turn.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>While stricken, the target takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls and grants combat advantage.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Halflings stand about 4 feet tall and weight about 80 pounds. They resemble small humans and are proportioned like human adults. Halflings have the same range of complexions as humans, but most halflings have dark hair and eyes. Halfling males don't have beards, but many have long, full sideburns. Halflings of both genders often wear complicated hairstyles, featuring complex braiding and weaving.</benefit>
		<benefit>Halflings typically dress in clothes that match their surroundings and prefer earth tones and various shades of green. Their clothing and gear feature woven textures and stitching. Birds, river patterns, boats, and fish are common images in halfling art and decoration.</benefit>
		<benefit>Halflings have life spans comparable to humans.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Halfling</name>
		<benefit>Hallflings are an affable, warm, and cheerful people. They survive in a world full of larger creatures by avoiding notice or, barring that, avoiding offense. They appear harmless and so have managed to survive for centuries in the shadow of empires and on the edges of wars and polititical strife.</benefit>
		<benefit>Halflings are practical and down-to-earth. They concern themselves with basic needs and simple pleasures, harboring few dreams of gold or glory. Adventurers are no more rare among halflings than among other races, but they usually purse the adventurer's life for reasons of community, friendship, wanderlust, or curiousity. Halfling adventurers are brave and faithful companions, relying on stealth and trickery in battle rather than raw might or magic.</benefit>
		<benefit>Tight-knit halfling communities are found near the settlements of other races, often along or even on the surface of a body of water. Halflings have never built a kingdom of their own or even held much land. They don't recognize any sort of royalty or nobility of their own, instead looking to family elders to guide them. This emphasis on family and community has enabled halflings to maintain their traditional ways for thousands of years, unaffected by the rise and fall of empires.</benefit>
		<benefit>According to halfling legend, Melora and Sehanine created the halflings together, giving the race a love of nature and the gift of stealth. When their interest waned, Melora and Sehanine stopped looking after the race, or so the legends go, and halflings made their own way in the world. They say Avandra, the god of luck, admired their resourcefulness and adopted them, favoring them with good fortune. Not all halflings worship Avandra, but nearly all breathe a prayer of thanks to her when fortune favors them.</benefit>
		<benefit>Halflings are fond of stories and legends such as the myth of Avandra, and their culture is rich in oral tradition. Few members of other races realize that halfling folktales contain a vast amount of lore about people and places long past. Many halflings are able to dredge up knowledge about the history, religion, or culture of other races, but that knowledge is usually wrapped in a fable.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Halfling Charasteristics:</b>]]> Brave, curious, determined, down-to-earth, friendly, good-natured, lucky, nimble, optimistic, practical, resourceful, warm</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Ander, Corrin, Dannad, Errich, Finnan, Garret, Lazam, Lindal, Merric, Nebin, Ostran, Perrin, Reed, Shardon, Ulmo, Wenner</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Andrey, Bree, Callie, Chenna, Eida, Kithri, Lidda, Nedda, Paela, Shaena, Tryn, Vani, Verna, Wella</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Sample Halfling Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Lidda, Halfling Rogue</name>
			<benefit>Lidda possesses a quick wit and an acid tongue. At a young age, she left her family out of a desire to see more of the world and experience first-hand the wonders described in the stories she grew up hearing.</benefit>
			<benefit>She has joined several different adventuring groups during her career, and even though her displays of sarcasm and wry humor at her companions' expense would suggest otherwise, she counts each of them as a close friend.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Garret, Halfling Ranger</name>
			<benefit>Several years ago, Garret's grandfather sent him to look for a distant branch of his family that had stopped responding to messages. He found the whole clan had been killed, and he returned to bring the sad news to his family. From that time, he has been unable to stay in one place for long.</benefit>
			<benefit>He doesn't know who or what killed his relatives and doesn't dream of vengeance, but he hopes to do some good in the world that might somehow balance out the atrocity of their murders.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Verna</name>
			<benefit>Verna is a Warlock -and among the most cheerful and gregarious of halflings. The otherworldly powers she channels seem to leave no mark on her spirit or mind. She takes no delight in killing, but uses lethal powers as a practical matter, to protect herself and her allies.</benefit>
			<benefit>She doesn't often talk of the event that propelled her into a life of adventuring and a pact with an otherworldly powers: A creature appeared in a a vision and offered her power, in exchange for a favor to be named later. In what she still regards as a moment of folly, she accepted. Nightmares of her unknown future haunt her sleep, but she never speaks of them.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A tiefling can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>
		
		<power>
			<title>Happy Feet</title>
			<class>Halfling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>It's hard to keep your feet under control, and sometimes they feel as if they move of their own accord</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Opportunity</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>A creature you can see starts its turn</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You shift up to 2 squares.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Minor Threat</title>
			<class>Halfling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>Clearly you're no threat to your enemies, injured as you are and doing your best to seem small and harmless</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must be bloodied.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Until you are no longer bloodied, you have a +2 power bonus to all defenses and to Stealth checks.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Pay Your Debts</title>
			<class>Halfling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>You acknowledge an ally's assistance by making a feint to keep your enemy off balance</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
				<keyword>Martial</keyword>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Special</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An enemy flanked by you moves out of the flanked position</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>One ally who was also flanking the triggering enemy</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The target gains combat advantage against the enemy until the start of the enemy's next turn.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Underfoot Hustle</title>
			<class>Halfling</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>You roll between your enemy's legs and spring up on the other side</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You shift up to your speed +2. You can move through squares occupied by enemies, but you must end your movement in an unoccupied square.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Enemies whose space you move through during this move grant combat advantage to you until the end of your next turn.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
</race>
