<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Dragonborn</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Proud, honorable warriors, born from the blood of an ancient dragon god</shortfluff>

	<height>6'2" - 6'8"</height>
	<weight>220 - 320</weight>

	<ability>Charisma</ability>
    <ability>Strength</ability>
    <ability>Constitution</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Normal</vision>

	<language>Common</language> <language>Draconic</language>

	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
        <description>+2 History, +2 Intimidate</description>
	</trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Draconic Heritage</name>
        <description>You add your Constitution modifier to your healing surge value.</description>
    </trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Dragonborn Fury</name>
		<description>While you're bloodied, you gain a +1 racial bonus to attack rolls.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Dragonborn Racial Power Selection</name>
        <description>Choose an option for your character:</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Dragon Breath:</i> You have the <i>dragon breath</i>]]> racial power.</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Dragonfear:</i> You have the <i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>

	<fluff>Born to fight, dragonborn are a race of wandering mercenaries, soldiers, and adventurers. Long ago, their empire contended for worldwide dominion, but now only a few rootless clans of these honorable warriors remain to pass on their legends of ancient glory.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a dragonborn if you want to: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to look like a dragon.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be the proud heir of an ancient, fallen empire.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to breathe acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison, or to inspire fear.</fluff>

	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Dragon Breath</title>
			<class>Dragpnborn</class> <category>Attack</category>
			<fluff>With a roar, you release the power of your draconic kin to engulf your foes</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Varies</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Close</type> <range>blast 3</range>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Each creature in the blast</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Ability +2 vs. Reflex</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +4</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +6</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>1d6 + Ability modifier damage.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>2d6 + ability modifier damage.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>3d6 + ability modifier damage.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>When you gain this power, choose Strength or Constitution. You use the chosen ability score for attack rolls and damage rolls.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<text>Also, choose one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison. Your <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i>]]> deals damage of the chosen type, and has the corresponding keyword.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Dragonfear</title>
			<class>Dragonborn</class> <category>Attack</category>
			<fluff>Your presence causes your enemies to quake and tremble</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Fear</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
				<section>
					<indent>4</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text><![CDATA[<b>Close</b>]]> burst 10</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Each enemy in the burst</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Ability +2 vs. Will</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +4</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>Ability +6</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The target is stricken with fear until the end of your next turn.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>While stricken, the target takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls and grants combat advantage.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>When you gain this power, choose Strength or Charisma. You use the chosen ability for attack rolls.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Dragonborn resemble humanoid dragons. They're covered in scaly hide, but they don't have tails. They are tall and strongly built, often standing close to 6½ feet in height and weighing up to 300 pounds or more. Their hands and feet are strong, talonlike claws with three fingers and a thumb on each hand. A dragonborn's head features a blunt snout, a strong brow, and distinctive frills at the cheek and ear. Behind the brow, a crest of hornlike scales of various lengths resembles thick, ropy hair. Their eyes are shades of red or gold.</benefit>
		<benefit>A typical dragonborn's scales can be scarlet, gold, rust, ocher, bronze, or brown. Rarely do an individual's scales match the hue or metallic dragon, and scale color gives no indication of the type of breath weapon a dragonborn might have. Most dragonborn have very fine scales over most of their body, giving their skin a leathery texture, with regions of larger scales on the forearms, lower legs and feet, shoulders, and thighs.</benefit>
		<benefit>Young dragonborn grow faster than human children do. They walk hours after hatching, reach the size and development of a 10-year-old human child by the age of 3, and reach adulthood by 15. They live about as long as humans do.</benefit>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Dragonborn</name>
		<benefit>To a dragonborn, honor is more important than life itself. First and foremost, honor is tied to a battlefield conduct. Adversaries should be treated with courtesy and respect, even if they are bitter enemies. Caution and discretion are key to a warrior's survival, but fear is a disease and cowardice is a moral failing.</benefit>
		<benefit>The drive to behave honorably extends into the rest of a dragonborn's life: Breaking an oath is the height of dishonor, and attention to honesty extends to every world. A commitment made must be carried out. Ultimatey, a dragonborn takes responsibility for his or her actions and their consequences.</benefit>
		<benefit>A continual drive for self-improvement reveals an additional aspect of dragonborn honor. Dragonborn value skill and excellence in all endeavors. They have to fail, and they push themselves to extreme efforts before they give up on something. A dragonborn holds mastery of a particular skill as a lifetime goal. Members of other races who share the same commitment find it easy to earn the respect of a dragonborn.</benefit>
		<benefit>The dragonborn dedication to honor and ecellence sometimes leads others to view dragonborn as arrogant and proud. Most dragonborn share a great pride in their race's past and present accomplishments, but they are also quick to admire the accomplishments of others. Even though the tiefling empire of Bael Turath was the enemy of the ancient dragonborn empire of Arkhosia, dragonborn recognize tieflings as worthy companions or opponents, admiring their strength and tenacity as friends or enemies.</benefit>
		<benefit>Dragonborn seek adventure for the chance to prove their worth, win renown, and perhaps become champions about whom stories will be told for generations. To win everlasting glory through mighty deeds, daring exploits, and supreme skill -that is the dragonborn dream.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Dragonborn Charasteristics:</b>]]> Driven, honor-bound, noble, perfectionist, proud, reliable, reserved, rooted in ancient history</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Arjhan, Balasar, Bharash, Donaar, Ghesh, Heskan, Kriv, Medrash, Nadarr, Patrin, Rhogar, Shamash, Shedinn, Torinn</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Akra, Biri, Daar, Harann, Kava, Korinn, Mishann, Nala, Perra, Raiann, Sora, Surina, Thava</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Sample Dragonborn Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Bharash, Dragonborn Warlord</name>
			<benefit>Bharash leads a group of adventurers in search of riches and glory. Inspired by tales of the ancient heroes of Arkhosia, he seeks his destiny in battle.</benefit>
			<benefit>He dreams of someday leading a mighty army against an orc horde or hobgoblin host, but he is content in the meantime to coordinate strikes against the lesser forces of evil he encounters in dungeons and ruins. He reveres Bahamut as the god of honor.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Harann, Dragonborn Fighter</name>
			<benefit>Harann is dedicated to the mastery of her chosen weapon, the khopesh. She rises early every morning to practice combat maneuvers and constantly strives to master new techniques.</benefit>
			<benefit>Excellence with her weapon is symbolic to her; it represents excellence of character, the perfection of her spirit. When she has achieved perfect mastery of the blade, she believes she will be perfect herself.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Donaar, Dragonborn Paladin</name>
			<benefit>Donaar follows Erathis, the god of cities and civilization. He believes that the dragonborn race is destined to rise from the ashes of its ancient empire and to form a new nation carved from the wilderness. And he intends to be instrumental in that process.</benefit>
			<benefit>As a reminder of his heritage, he keeps a piece of the shell from which he hatched in an amulet around his neck. Although he sometimes thinks that pillaging dungeons is a waste of his effort, he occasionally unearths a remnant of the long-lost dragonborn empire. He believes he can put such items to use one day in laying the foundation for a new empire for his people.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A dragonborn can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>

		<power>
			<title>Baleful Glance</title>
			<class>Dragonborn</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>You single out an enemy, holding the foe's gaze with your menacing stare</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Fear</keyword>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Special</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must have the <![CDATA[<i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You hit an enemy with your <![CDATA[<i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<indent>1</indent>
					<text>If you targeted more than one enemy, you can wait until you know which of the targets you hit</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The triggering enemy</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The target is dazed (save ends).</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Breath Retaliation</title>
			<class>Dragonborn</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>When your blood is drawn, the draconic energies inside you are eager to come forth</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must have the <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i>]]> racial power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Your <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i>]]> racial power must be available.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You become bloodied</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You use your <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i>]]> racial power without spending an action.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Dragon's Dive</title>
			<class>Dragonborn</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>You set your sights on your foe and dive through the fray, heedless of the threats</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You make a charge attack</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Your movement made as part of the triggering charge attack does not provoke <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i>]]>.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>If you jump down as part of the triggering attack, you gain resist against the fall damage equal to your level.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Arkhosian Resilience</title>
			<class>Dragonborn</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>You call forth the draconic power inside you to shield you from harm</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must have the <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i> racial power or the <i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You take damage of a type that matches the type of damage you chose for your <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i>]]> racial power, or you take psychic damage if you have the <![CDATA[<i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You gain resist against the triggering damage type until the end of the encounter. The resist equals 5 + one-half your level.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Triumphant Roar</title>
			<class>Dragonborn</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>Your success gives you such enthusiasm that you loose a roar that brings forth the draconic power within you</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must have the <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i> racial power or the <i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You either bloody a nonminion enemy or reduce a nonminion enemy to 0 hit points or less</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You use your <![CDATA[<i>dragon breath</i> racial power or your <i>dragonfear</i>]]> racial power, even if that power is already expended.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>

</race>
