<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
	<collection>Monk Lvl 2 Utility Disciplines</collection>

	<power>
		<title>Careful Stride</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>You walk with such precision and control that broken ground or even bodies water cannot impede you</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, you ignore difficult terrain and can both move across liquid and stand on it as if it were solid ground. You also don't trigger traps or hazards that would trigger based on weight if you are aware of them, at your DM's discretion.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>You move up to you speed.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Cat and Mouse</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>You step into your enemy's bind spot after a successful attack and leave it casting about to find you</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
            <text>You hit an enemy with a melee attack</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>You shift up to 3 squares to a space adjacent to the triggering enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>Until the start of your next turn or until you take damage from an attack, whichever comes first, you have total concealment against the triggering enemy.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>If the triggering attack was a critical hit, you can also make a Stealth check to hide from the triggering enemy as part of the shift, though any other enemies are still fully aware of you and likely to break your hiding.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Deflect Arrow</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>Your foe attempts to strike you from afar, so you focus your energy and spin away from their attacks</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
            <text>A ranged Weapon attack hits or misses you</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, you gain the following benefits:</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <name style="bullet" />
            <text>Superior cover against ranged Weapon attacks, generally meaning those attacks have a -5 penalty to attack rolls against you from cover.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <name style="bullet" />
            <text>When a ranged Weapon attack misses you, you can shift 1 square as a free reaction.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>This effect immediately ends if you cannot take actions.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <name style="bold">Sustain Minor:</name>
            <text>The effect persists until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name style="bold">Special:</name>
            <text>Your DM might allow you to trigger and apply this power's effects against non-Weapon attacks that are physical in nature.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Fall of Wind</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>You have meditated on the nature of the air around you and can control it to cushion your fall</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
            <text>You fall</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>You reduce the damage you take from the fall by 5 + one-half your level.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Fighting Fury Stance</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>Your discipline and control let you channel your anger into each blow</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic, Stance</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>You assume the Fighting Fury stance.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>Until the stance ends, your unarmed melee attacks, including your monk melee Implement attacks, deal additional damage equal to one-half your Strength modifier or one-half your Charisma modifier, whichever is higher. This increases to your Strength modifier or your Charisma modifier, whichever is higher, if the attack is or counts as a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Grasp the Wind</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>Before your enemy can force you back, you whirl around, using the power of the attack to propel you where you want to go</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
            <text>You are pulled, pushed, or slid</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>Instead of being affected by the triggering forced movement, you shift up to the number of squares it would have moved you. If you shifd outside the range of the triggering attack or other effect, you take half damage from it but it is not invalidated.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Harmonious Discipline</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>A specific sequence of disciplined breathing enhances both your defense and subsequent offense</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>You gain temporary hit points equal to one-third your level + your Wisdom modifier or your Constitution modifier, whichever is higher.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>When you have no temporary hit points remaining, you gain a bonus to the first damage roll for a melee attack you make before the end of your following turn. The bonus equals your Wisdom modifier or your Constitution modifier, whichever is higher.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Reed in the Wind</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>You get ready to spin with a blow and then snap back with a quick threat of your own</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section>
            <name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
            <text>An enemy targets you with an attack</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>You take half damage from the triggering attack.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>Once the triggering attack has been resolved, you gain combat advantage against he triggering enemy until the end of your next turn. If the triggering attack missed you, you also gain a bonus to the first damage roll you make against the triggering enemy. The bonus equal your Strength modifier, Constitution modifier, Wisdom modifier, or Charisma modifier, whichever is highest.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Supreme Flurry</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>Your speed is a blur that makes it impossible to tell where one strike ends and another begins</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Prerequisite:</name>
            <text>You must have a Flurry of Blows class power.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
            <text>You use your Flurry of Blows class power</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>After resolving both the Flurry of Blows power as well as the power that triggered it, you shift up to half your speed and use your Flurry of Blows class power again.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Swift Flight</title>
      <class>Monk</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
      <fluff>Channeling psionic energy through palms pointed at the ground, your simple leap becomes a smooth glide across the battlefield</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Psionic</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section shade="true">
            <name style="bold">Effect:</name>
            <text>You fly up to a number of squares equal to 1 + one-half your speed + your Strength modifier, Constitution modifier, Wisdom modifier, or Charisma modifier, whichever is highest. If you don't land at the end of this movement, you fall.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
</catalog>
