<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
   <name>Warlock</name>
   <subname>Scourge</subname>
   <role>Striker</role>
   <source>Arcane</source>
   <shortfluff>You have forged a pact with a powerful, supernatural force or an unnamed entity, allowing you to sling attacks damaging, weakening and hampering alike and to elude attacks through flight, teleportation and invisibility.</shortfluff>
   <keyability>Charisma</keyability>
   <keyability>Constitution</keyability>
   <keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
   <keyability>Intelligence</keyability>

   <proficiency>
      <type>Armor</type>
      <name>Cloth</name>
      <name>Leather</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Weapon</type>
      <name>Simple melee</name>
      <name>Simple ranged</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Implement</type>
      <name>Rod</name>
      <name>Wand</name>
   </proficiency>

   <defense>
      <name>Fortitude</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
   <defense>
      <name>Will</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>

   <hpbase>12</hpbase>
   <hpgain>5</hpgain>
   <surgebase>9</surgebase>

   <skills>
      <trained>Arcana, Bluff, Intimidate or Religion</trained>
      <number>3</number>
   </skills>

   <fluff>Warlocks channel arcane might wrested from otherworldly entities. They commune with infernal intelligences and fey spirits, scour enemies with potent blasts of eldritch power, and bedevil foes with hexing curses. Armed with esoteric secrets and dangerous lore, Warlocks are clever and resourceful foes.</fluff>
   <fluff>No matter how a Warlock came to gain arcane knowledge, he or she need not accept the poor reputation Warlocks oftentimes endure. He or she could also be a libram-toting scholar captivated by ominous lore, a foot-loose wanderer searching for elusive ultimate truths, a devil-touched hunter using infernal spells to eliminate evil, or even a black-clad mercenary who uses sinister trappings to discourage prying strangers and unwanted attention. On the other hand, she might just as well be a true diabolist using his or her gifts to tyrannize the weak - some Warlocks are exactly that.</fluff>
   <fluff>While most common folk might be suspicious of Wizards doing their research in isolation, they are outright mistrusting of known Warlocks, who came by their power through an easier path. Some of the greatest villains to scour the land have been Warlocks who stumbled across the rituals and incantations needed to contant and forge a bargain.</fluff>
   <fluff>The entities that grant power to Scourges care little for how such a gift is used. Their interest is focused on the souls and the power provided to them by those who have gained their power through a pact.</fluff>

   <feature>
      <name>Combat Style</name>
      <benefit>Many spells granted to a Scourge through their pact are versatile, working both in melee combat and at range. All Scourges also have a personal style of casting those spells that favours one over the other.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose either Prime Shot or Prime Strike to show your personal combat style.</benefit>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Prime Shot</name>
         <benefit>You favour attacking from a safe distance. And as long as your allies are not there to distract you, your spells usually find their mark.</benefit>
         <benefit>If none of your allies are nearer to your target than you are, you gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls with ranged attacks against that target. When determining if an ally is closer to the target, ignore allies that are helpless, stunned, dominated, unconscious or petrified.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Prime Strike</name>
         <benefit>You enjoy the thick of combat, reveling in the suffering you can see in your enemy's eyes when you have isolated it.</benefit>
         <benefit>If no other creature is adjacent to your target, you gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls with melee attacks against that target. Creatures that are helpless, stunned, dominated, unconscious or petrified do not count as being adjacent to the target.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Eldritch Combat</name>
      <benefit>The first spell a Scourge wields after forging a pact is always rudimentary, but still effective.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose either <![CDATA[<i>eldritch blast</i>, <i>eldritch bolt</i>, or <i>eldritch strike</i>]]>. You gain the chosen power as a 1st-level at-will attack power in addition to those you normally gain.</benefit>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Eldritch Pact</name>
      <benefit>All Warlocks gain access to their power by entering into a pact with some force or entity in which that power rests. In return for their continuing loyalty and service to the source of their power, Warlocks become more adept at their craft.</benefit>
      <benefit>The pact you choose gives you following benefits and class feature:</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; <![CDATA[<i>Affinity:</i>]]> The pacts have affinities related to casting certain types of spells or casting spells under specific circumstances, with different benefits depending on the pact.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; <![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i>]]> Your pact determines one of the at-will attack powers you gain from your class.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; <![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon:</i>]]> Each pact has a specific Pact Boon feature that triggers when the Scourge reduces a target under their curse to 0 hit points or less. The boon does not trigger if the enemy was reduced to 0 hit points with a nonlethal attack.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; Some of your Warlock attack powers have additional or enhanced effects based on your pact.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose either Dark Pact, Elemental Pact, Fey Pact, Infernal Pact, Sorcerer-King Pact, Star Pact, or Vestige Pact to determine the type of entity you forged a pact with.</benefit>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Dark Pact</name>
         <benefit>A Dark Pact is forged with the dark beings that lurk in the shadows and in the hearts of people. Spells of darkness, poison, madness, and spite fill the Scourge's mind. He or she might might turn the power to noble ends, but will always face the temptation to enhance the spells by hurting his or her friends - just a little.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Debilitation Affinity:</i>]]> You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls with Necrotic powers against targets that are taking ongoing poison damage. Also, you deal +1 damage with Poison powers against bloodied targets. This increases to +2 at 11th level, and to +3 at 21st level.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i>]]> You must choose either <![CDATA[<i>mind shadows</i> or <i>spiteful glamor</i>]]> as one of the at-will attacks you gain from your class.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon feature:</i>]]> You gain your choise of either the <![CDATA[<i>dark spiral</i> class power or the <i>shadow warp</i>]]> class power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Dark Spiral</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>As your cursed enemies fall in battle, a dark energy spiral grows in power until you unleash it on an enemy</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or less</text>
               </section>
               <section personal=""/>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>The strength of your dark energy spiral increases by 1.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>The strength increases by 2.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>Your dark energy spiral resets to 0 when you take a short rest or an extended rest, or 5 minutes after you have last increased its strength, whichever comes first.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>While the strength of your dark energy spiral is at least 1, you can use the Dark Spiral Release attack.</text>
               </section>
            <part>
               <part-name>Dark Spiral Release</part-name>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane, Necrotic, Psychic</keyword>
               <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy in the burst targets you with a melee or ranged attack</text>
               </section>
               <section><name>Target:</name><type>Close</type><range>burst 10</range><target>the triggering enemy</target></section>
               <section indent="1"><name>Level 11:</name><type>Close</type><range>burst 15</range></section>
               <section indent="1"><name>Level 21:</name><type>Close</type><range>burst 20</range></section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>The target takes necrotic and psychic damage. The damage equals a number of 1d6 equal to the strength of your dark energy spiral.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>A number of 1d8.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>If this deals less than 12 damage, the strength of your dark energy spiral is reduced by 1, to a minimum of 1.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>If this deals 12 damage or more, you can choose one of the following two options:</text>
               </section>
               <section indent="1">
                  <shade>true</shade> <bullet/>
                  <text>The target is weakened until the end of its current turn, including on the triggering attack. The strength of your dark energy spiral becomes 0.</text>
               </section>
               <section indent="1">
                  <shade>true</shade> <bullet/>
                  <text>Reduce the strength of your dark energy spiral by half.</text>
               </section>
            </part>
         </power>

         <power>
            <title>Shadow Warp</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>When your foe falls, you draw strength from its death to carry another creature across the battlefield</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or less</text>
               </section>
               <section><name>Target:</name><type>Close</type><range>burst 5</range><target>you or one creature in the burst</target></section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You slide the target up to a number of squares equal to 2 + one-half your Dexterity modifier.</text>
               </section>
         </power>

      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Elemental Pact</name>
         <benefit>The Elemental Chaos's power can lure a Warlock into forging a pact that reaches into the roiling Plane Below and steals power from the inscrutable primordials. The stolen magic is random, changing to suit the whims of whichever primordial is closest to the Prime Material. </benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Chaotic Affinity:</i>]]> After each rest, roll a d10 to determine your current elemental affinity:<![CDATA[<br />
            &#9658; <b>1 or 2:</b> Acid.<br />
            &#9658; <b>3 or 4:</b> Cold.<br />
            &#9658; <b>5 or 6:</b> Fire.<br />
            &#9658; <b>7 or 8:</b> Lightning.<br />
            &#9658; <b>9 or 10:</b>]]> Thunder.</benefit>
         <benefit>You can choose a specific affinity when you use your <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]>, but it still changes when you rest again.</benefit>
         <benefit>On your turn, when you use an arcane attack power that deals force, necrotic, poison, or psychic damage, you can change the damage type and keyword to match your current affinity.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i> You must choose <i>chromatic bolt</i> or <i>fascinating patterns</i>]]> as one of the at-will attack powers you gain from your class.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon feature:</i>]]> You gain the <![CDATA[<i>accursed affinity</i>]]> utility power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Accursed Affinity</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>The elemental power fueling your spells overwhelm your enemies with the seemingly random energy loosed against them</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer</text>
               </section>
               <section personal=""/>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>The next enemy you place your curse on gains vulnerable 5 to the damage type matching your current elemental affinity. This vulnerability is cumulative with the enemy's existing vulnerability to the same damage type, if any, and lasts until the curse ends.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Vulnerable 10</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Vulnerable 15</text>
               </section>
         </power>

      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Fey Pact</name>
         <benefit>There are bargains to be struck with ancient, amoral powers of the Feywild. Some are primitive earth spirits, grim and menacing; some are capricious wood, sky, or water spirits; and others are incarnations of seasons or natural forces who roam the faerie realm like wild gods.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Trickster Affinity:</i>]]> You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls when you are invisible from a target or against targets affected by an Illusion or Charm effect.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i>]]> You must choose either <![CDATA[<i>echoing dirge</i> or <i>eyebite</i>]]> as one of the at-will attack powers you gain from your class.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon feature:</i>]]> You gain the <![CDATA[<i>misty step</i>]]> class power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Misty Step</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>You instantly transform into silver mist that streams a short distance and reforms, allowing you to flee or maneuver to set up a deadly attack</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer</text>
               </section>
               <section personal=""/>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You teleport up to a number of squares equal to 1 + one-half your Dexterity modifier.</text>
               </section>
         </power>

      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Infernal Pact</name>
         <benefit>Long ago a forgotten group of devils created a secret path to power and taught it to tieflings of Bael Turath to weaken their fealty to Asmodeus. In his wrath, Asmodeus destroyed the scheming devils and struck their very names from the memory of all beings - but some Scourges dare to study their perilous secret ways anyway.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Infernal Affinity:</i>]]> You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls with Fear powers against bloodied targets. Also, you gain a +1 bonus to damage rolls with Fire powers against targets affected by a Fear power. This increases to +2 at 11th level, and to +3 at 21st level.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i> You must choose either <i>hellish rebuke</i> or <i>gift of Avernus</i>]]> as one of the at-will attack powers you gain from your class.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon feature:</i> You gain the <i>Dark One's blessing</i>]]> class power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Dark One's Blessing</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>You instantly gain vitality as a cursed enemy falls</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or less</text>
               </section>
               <section personal=""/>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You gain temporary hit points equal to your level + your Constitution modifier.</text>
               </section>
         </power>

      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Sorcerer-King Pact</name>
         <benefit>On the desert world or Athas, Scourges pledge themselves to the service of a sorcerer-king. In return, their master transforms him or her into an arcane spellcaster by means of an eldritch ritual. What the Warlock does with this new power is up to them - the sorcerer-king has no special ability to observe or strip the Scourge of power. However, all sorcerer-kings are suspicious and ruthless, so defying will ultimately lead to peril.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Withering Affinity:</i>]]> On your turn, when you use an arcane attack power that deals force, poison, or psychic damage, you can change the damage type to necrotic and the keyword to Necrotic. Also, you gain a +1 bonus to damage rolls with powers that normally deal necrotic damage. This increases to +2 at 11th level, and to +3 at 21st level.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i>]]> You must choose <![CDATA[<i>hand of blight</i>]]> as one of the at-will attack powers you gain from your class.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon feature:</i>]]> Each time you finish a rest, you gain a Fell Might that you can use to enhance some of your powers. You must decide whether or not to spend your Fell Might when you use a power, before making any decisions concerning the power or resolving any of its effects.</benefit>
         <benefit>You also gain the <![CDATA[<i>fell might recovery</i>]]> class power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Fell Might Recovery</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>The fall of a cursed enemy renews your might</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or less</text>
               </section>
               <section personal=""/>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You recover your Fell Might.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>If you already have your Fell Might, you don't gain a second use - you can only have one use of Fell Might available at one time.</text>
               </section>
         </power>

      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Star Pact</name>
         <benefit>A number of Warlocks master the astrologer's art, learning the secret names of stars and gazing into the Far Realm beyond, gaining great power thereby. The scourge calls upon powers that madden or terrify enemies, manipulate chance and fate, and scour foes with icy banes and curses drawn from beyond the night sky.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Unearthly Glow Affinity:</i>]]> While you are bloodied, you are closer to glimpsing the truth beyond the stars, and gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls with Psychic powers and a +1 bonus to damage rolls with Radiant powers and Cold powers. The bonus to damage rolls increases to +2 at 11th level, and to +3 at 21st level.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i>]]> You must choose either <![CDATA[<i>dire radiance</i> or <i>mind shadows</i>]]> as one of the at-will attack powers you gain from your class.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon feature:</i>]]> You gain the <![CDATA[<i>fate of the void</i>]]> class power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Fate of the Void</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>Your curse intermingles with the lost vitality of a cursed enemy to reveal a glimpse of the future to you</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or less</text>
               </section>
               <section personal=""/>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You gain a +1 bonus to any single attack roll, saving throw, skill check, or ability check you make. If you don't use this bonus before the end of your next turn, it is lost.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>This bonus is cumulative; if this power triggers three times before your next turn, you gain a +3 bonus to a single roll of your choice.</text>
               </section>
         </power>

      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Vestige Pact</name>
         <benefit>Pacts are at times also forged with vestiges - the remnants of powerful forces and entities that once excercised great authority or demonstrated awful capabilities. These remants are diverse in their backgrounds and motives. A Vestige Pact is fluid, allowing the Scourge to change which vestige fuels his or her arcane power.</benefit>
         <benefit>See the Using Vestiges section at the end of the class description for the rules concerning vestiges.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Changing Affinity:</i>]]> After you have changed to a different vestige, you gain a +4 bonus to the next damage roll you make before the end of your next turn. This bonus increases +7 at 11th level, and to +10 at 21st level.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>At-Will Attack:</i>]]> You must choose <![CDATA[<i>eyes of the vestige</i>]]> as one of the at-will attack powers you gain from your class.</benefit>
         <benefit><![CDATA[<i>Pact Boon feature:</i>]]> You gain the <![CDATA[<i>vestige pact boon</i>]]> class power. The effects vary based on your active vestige. Listed below are the effects for the two primary vestiges; Other powers that give you access to vestiges, will list the benefit that vestige confers.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Vestige Pact Boon</title>
            <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>Power swells from your pact - what form it takes depends on your vestige</fluff>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
               <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>An enemy under your curse is reduced to 0 hit points or less</text>
               </section>
               <section personal=""/>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You gain an effect depending on your active vestige:</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>King Elidyr:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <type>Close</type> <range>burst 1</range>
                  <target>one ally adjacent to you</target>
                  <text>The target gains a +2 bonus to all defenses until the end of the the ally's next turn.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Zutwa:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <type>Personal; </type>
                  <text>If you have the Prime Shot class feature, the bonus to attack rolls increases to +3 until the end of your next turn. If you do not have it, you gain it until the end of your next turn.</text>
               </section>
         </power>

      </subfeature>

   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Shadow Walk</name>
      <benefit>In combat, a Warlock's spells leak eldritch energies even before they are cast. When the Warlock moves, these energies swirl around him or her, creating a coruscating patterns of shadow, flames or starlight that conceal his or her true position.</benefit>
      <benefit>On your turn, if you move at least 3 squares away from where you started your turn, you gain concealment until the end of your next turn.</benefit>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Warlock's Curse</name>
      <benefit>The spells wielded by a Scourge are usually desctructive in their own right. But by attuning an enemy to his or her magic, a Scourge can make it even more painful to be on the receiving end. This attunement is known as being cursed by a Warlock.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>warlock's curse</i>]]> class power that allows you to place your curse on your enemies. Other benefits can also allow you to place your curse on enemies. You can have more than one creature under your curse. You can't place your curse on a creature that is already under your curse or the curse of another Warlock.</benefit>
      <benefit>A cursed enemy is more vulnerable to your attacks. If you hit a cursed enemy with an attack, you deal +1d6 extra damage. You decide whether to apply the extra damage after making the damage roll, and when you use an area or close attack, you can choose who to apply it to after determining which targets you hit with the attack. You can deal this extra damage only once per turn.</benefit>
      <benefit>The extra damage increases to +2d6 at 11th level, and to +3d6 at 21st level.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Warlock's Curse</title>
         <class>Warlock</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <fluff>With a quick word, you place a hex on an enemy close to you</fluff>
            <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
            <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
            <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <section auto="no-opportunity"/>
            <section><name>Target:</name><type>Ranged</type><range>sight</range><target>the enemy closest to you that you can see</target></section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You place the target under your curse until the end of the encounter or until it is reduced to 0 hit points or less, whichever comes first.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You can use this power only once per turn.</text>
            </section>
      </power>

   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Using Vestiges</name>
      <benefit>You always have one active vestige. At first level when you choose the Vestige Pact, you gain access to the two primary vestiges: <![CDATA[<i>King Elidyr</i> and <i>Zutwa</i>]]>. You select one of these as your active vestige after completing a short rest or an extended rest.</benefit>
      <benefit><![CDATA[<b>Changing Your Vestige:</b>]]> You can gain temporary access to other vestiges by using certain daily attack powers - for ease of identification, all these powers have names that begin with “Vestige.” When you use a power that gives you access to a daily power vestige, you can choose for that vestige to immediately become your active vestige. If you do so, it remains your active vestige until you gain access to a different vestige by using another daily attack power or until the end of the encounter. If you don't immediately choose to change to that daily power vestige, your access to that vestige is lost until the next time you use that power.</benefit>
      <benefit>After a short rest or an extended rest, you again select one of the two primary vestiges to be your active vestige. That vestige remains active until you change to a daily power vestige or until you take another short rest or extended rest.</benefit>
      <benefit>In addition, certain benefits allow you to change your vestige at a different time or under different circumstances, as detailed in the specific benefit.</benefit>
   </feature>

</class>
