<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   
   <power>
      <title>Able Companion</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You conjure a creature of many hands and feet that aids your allies</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Conjuration</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You conjure an able companion in an unoccupied square within range until the end of the encounter. The companion occupies its square, though you and your allies can pass through it.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>When you or an ally enter the companion's space by walking or shifting, that character can immediately move to another space adjacent to the companion, using the same movement but not expending squares of movement.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>When you or an ally starts his or her turn adjacent to the companion, that character can either stand from prone or shift 1 square as a free reaction. An ally that is knocked prone while adjacent to the companion can attempt a saving throw to remain standing on a success.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>While the companion persists, you can use the following two actions at-will.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Minor Action:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You move the companion up to 2 squares.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Move Action:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You move the companion up to 6 squares.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Conjure Fortification</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>A low stone wall rises from the ground, offering cover against attack or passage over an obstacle</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Conjuration</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Area</type> <range>wall 5 within 10 squares.</range>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You conjure a wall of stone that lasts until the end of the encounter.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The wall can be up to 1 square high, and at least 2 squares of it must rest on a solid surface.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The wall is blocking terrain. A creature can climb the wall with a DC 15 Athletics chceck.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Darklight</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>Purple flame appears over your head and remains floating in the air, though only you and your companions can see it and the illumination it casts</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Nethermancy, Zone</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Close</type> <range>burst 2</range>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The burst creates a zone of dark light that lasts until the end of the encounter.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>For you and your allies, the zone is brightly lit, and all squares within 3 squares of the zone are dimly lit.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If you or an ally starts his or her turn in the zone, that character has darkvision until the start of his or her next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
   <power>
      <title>Dimension Door</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You trace the outline of a doorway in front of you, step through the portal, and reappear somewhere else nearby</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <type2>Melee</type2> <range2>touch</range2>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You, or you and one ally you touch</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Choose one of the following effects:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; You teleport up to 20 squares to a space you can see and have line of effect to.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; You teleport up to 10 squares. You do not need to see the destination space or have line of effect to it. If the destination is not one where you can teleport to, such as if it is occupied or inside a solid object, the power is expended without effect.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; You and one ally you touch teleport. You teleport 10 squares to a space you can see and have line of effect to, and teleport the ally to any space adjacent to you.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
   
</catalog>
