<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <collection>Wizard Lvl 6 Utility Spells</collection>

   <power>
      <title>Able Companion</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You conjure a creature of many hands and feet that aids your allies</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Conjuration</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <text>You conjure an able companion in an unoccupied square within range until the end of the encounter. The companion occupies its square, though you and your allies can pass through it.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>When you or an ally enter the companion's space by walking or shifting, that character can immediately move to another space adjacent to the companion, using the same movement but not expending squares of movement.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>When you or an ally starts his or her turn adjacent to the companion, that character can either stand from prone or shift 1 square as a free reaction. An ally that is knocked prone while adjacent to the companion can attempt a saving throw to remain standing on a success.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>While the companion persists, you can use the following two actions at-will.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Minor Action:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You move the companion up to 2 squares.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Move Action:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You move the companion up to 6 squares.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Conjure Fortification</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>A low stone wall rises from the ground, offering cover against attack or passage over an obstacle</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Conjuration</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Area</type> <range>wall 5 within 10 squares.</range>
            <text>You conjure a wall of stone that lasts until the end of the encounter.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The wall can be up to 1 square high, and at least 2 squares of it must rest on a solid surface.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The wall is blocking terrain. A creature can climb the wall with a DC 15 Athletics chceck.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Special:</name>
            <text>You can choose to use this power as an encounter power.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <text>If you do, the area is only wall 3, and the wall only lasts until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Darklight</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>Purple flame appears over your head and remains floating in the air, though only you and your companions can see it and the illumination it casts</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Nethermancy, Zone</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>burst 2</range>
            <text>The burst creates a zone of dark light that lasts until the end of the encounter.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>For you and your allies, the zone is brightly lit, and all squares within 3 squares of the zone are dimly lit.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If you or an ally starts his or her turn in the zone, that character has darkvision until the start of his or her next turn.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Dimension Door</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You trace the outline of a doorway in front of you, step through the portal, and reappear somewhere else nearby</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Personal</type>
            <type2>Melee</type2> <range2>touch</range2>
            <target>you, or you and one ally you touch</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Choose one of the following effects:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            <text>You teleport up to 20 squares to a space you can see and have line of effect to.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            <text>You teleport up to 10 squares. You do not need to see the destination space or have line of effect to it.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <text>If the destination is not one where you can teleport to, such as if it is occupied or inside a solid object, the power is expended without effect.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            <text>You and one ally you touch teleport. You teleport 10 squares to a space you can see and have line of effect to, and teleport the ally to any space adjacent to you.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Disguise Self</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>With a snap of your fingers, you suddenly look like someone else</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Illusion</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You make yourself, your clothing, and your equipment look different. The illusion lasts for 1 hour, although you can end it as a minor action. You must keep the same appearance for the entire duration.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>You can take on the appearance of any creature of similar build and size, including a specific individual whom you've seen. You gain neither the abilities or mannerisms of the chosen form, nor the tactile or audible properties of your form or gear. For example, if you took on the illusion of a dwarf in plate armor, anyone touching you would realize you weren't wearing plate armor, and you would not clank, creak, or jingle as you walked.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Anyone who attempts to see through your ruse makes an Insight check against a DC equal to 10 + your Bluff check modifier with a +5 power bonus.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Dispel Magic</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You send out a crackling ray of arcane energy that destroys a magical effect created by an opponent</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Implement</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <target>one effect that has the Arcane, Divine, Elemental, Primal or Psionic keyword</target>
            <text>Intelligence vs. Will</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <text>Use the Will defense of the creator of the target effect if the target does not have one</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <text>If the target effect is one that normally ends on a save, the attack automatically hits</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target effect immediately ends. No aftereffects or similar effects are triggered.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>DM Note:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>Will be keeping an eye on whether this needs to be adjusted.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Fun Fact:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>Can dispel Barbarian Rage power effects.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Evanesce</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>The instant you feel your enemy's attack, you vanish in a puff of black smoke</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Zone</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You are damaged by an attack</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You are removed from play until the start of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The space you vacate becomes a zone of black smoke until the end of the encounter. The zone is heavily obscured.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>At the start of your next turn, you reappear in a square of your choice up to 5 squares from the zone.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Familiar's Call</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You teleport yourself to where your familiar is</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have a familiar.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Your familiar must be in active mode, and within 20 squares of you.</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You teleport to the square occupied by your familiar, and your familiar enters passive mode.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Fire Shield</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You are swatched in rippling flames that turn away both fire and chill, but scorch anyone who strikes you</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Fire</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You gain the following benefits until the end of the encounter:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; Resist 10 cold and resist 10 fire.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>&#9658; Any creature that makes a melee attack against you takes fire damage equal to 3 + your Intelligence modifier. No creature can take this damage more than once per turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>2</indent>
            <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>Equal to 6 + your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>2</indent>
            <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>Equal to 10 + your Intelligence modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Force Ladder</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You create a shimmering ladder to aid your ascent</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Conjuration</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <text>You conjure a ladder of arcane force in an unoccupied square within range until the end of the encounter.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The ladder can be up to 8 squares tall, stands firmly, and does not need to be attached to anything. The ladder cannot be moved unless you permit it.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Climbing the ladder requires a DC 5 Athletics check.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>While the ladder persists, you can use the following action at-will. Using the action provokes an <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attack</i>]]>.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Opportunity Interrupt:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text><![CDATA[<i>Trigger:</i>]]> A creature attempts to climb the ladder; You increase or decrease the DC for the Athletics check by 5. If the creature has a climb speed, you force it make an Athletics check to climb when you increase the DC.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Glowering Wrath</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>Your voice thunders above the din of the battlefield, casting fear and doubt into your foes</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <name>Effect:</name> <shade>true</shade>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, you gain the following benefits:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            <text>The DC to hear your voice is lowered by 5.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            <text>You are considered trained in Intimidate. If you are already trained, you instead gain a +3 power bonus to Intimidate checks.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            <text>You gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls with Fear powers.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>  <bullet/>
            <text>You increase the distance of any forced movement you cause with Fear powers by 2 squares.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent> <bullet/>
            <text>If you cause a Fear effect that a save can end, the target takes a -2 penalty to the first saving throw it makes against it.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Invisibility</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>A creature you choose vanishes from sight</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Illusion</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Personal</type>
            <type2>Ranged</type2> <range2>5</range2>
            <target>you, or one creature</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target becomes invisible until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the target makes an attack, the effect ends after the attack has been resolved.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Sustain Standard:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text><![CDATA[<i>Requirement:</i>]]> The target is within 5 squares of you; The effect persists until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If you use this power outside of combat, you can sustain the power for up to 1 hour and the target does not need to be within 5 squares of you.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Levitate</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You rise off the ground a short distance</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You move up to 4 squares vertically and hover there until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>While aloft, you are unsteady, taking a -2 penalty to AC and Reflex, and to Weapon attack rolls.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If something, such as a pit opening below you, causes you to be more than 4 squares above the ground, you descend down to 4 squares above the ground at the end of the turn where the change occurred. You do not take damage from such a fall.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>When the levitation ends, you descend to the ground without taking falling damage.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Sustain Move:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You move up to 3 squares up or down, or 1 square horizontally, and you hover until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <text>If you moved more than 4 squares above the ground, you descend to 4 squares above the ground at the end of your current turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You can also use this power as a standard action to target an unattended object of Medium size or smaller. If you do, the power is ranged 5 instead of personal, and sustaining it is a standard action instead of a move action.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Oracular Maneuver</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You witnessed this encounter in a dream, and you told your companions that it would come to pass</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy ends a movement within 5 squares of you</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
            <target>you, and each ally in the burst; You must have finished a rest with the target in the last 24 hours</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Each target can shift 1 square as a free reaction.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Refocus</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You take a deep breath and picture the pages of your spellbook in your mind</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have the Arcane Spellbook class feature.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You must have perused your spellbook in the last 48 hours.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>In the last week.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>In the last month.</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Choose one unexpended Wizard encounter attack, daily attack or utility power.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>You replace the chosen power with a different power that is in your spellbook. The new power must be of the same kind, and of the same level or lower. You gain a +1 power bonus to attack rolls with the new power until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>When you next take a short rest, you can choose to make the new power your prepared power, provided it is one you could have normally prepared (isn't the same level as another power of the same kind, for example). Otherwise you return to the previous prepared power. If the new power was a daily power and you expended it, the previous power is also expended until you finish a long rest even if it was an encounter utility power.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You can expend this power as part of preparing spells as outlined in your Arcane Spellbook feature. If you do so, you do not need to have access to your spellbook. You must still meet this power's requirement.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Revitalizing Charm</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You crumble enchanted herbs between your fingers and command your flagging companion to steel herself or himself for battle</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Ranged</type> <range>5</range>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You, or one ally</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You remove one effect from the target that a save can end. No aftereffects or similar effects are triggered.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Shadow Investiture</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You draw energy from shadow stuff to help others navigate in darkness</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Nethermancy</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>burst 1</range>
            <target>you and each ally in the burst</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of the encounter, each target has darkvision, and resist necrotic equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>Equal to 5 + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>Equal to 10 + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Spectral Hound</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>You summon a ghostly image of a powerful mastiff that follows you protectively</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Illusion</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <text>You create the illusion of a spectral hound in a square within range until the end of the encounter. The hound does not occupy its square, but does count as an ally for the purposes of flanking.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>As long as the hound remains within 10 squares of you, it warns you of approaching danger, granting you a +1 power bonus to all defenses, and a +2 power bonus to Perception checks.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The effect immediately ends if the hound is not within your line of sight at the end of your turn. While the illusion persists, you can use the following action at-will:</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Minor Action:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You can move the spectral hound up to 5 squares.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Summon Iron Cohort</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>A dwarf-sized humanoid creature of earth and iron ore assembles near you and when you come under attack, it steps in to absorb the force of the blow</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Summoning</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="no-opportunity"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>2</range>
            <text> You summon a Small iron cohort in an unoccupied space within range.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>The iron cohort remains until the end of the encounter, or until you take a minor action to dismiss it.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the iron cohort is reduced to 0 hit points or less, it disappears and you lose a healing surge.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Watery Double</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>Creating a duplicate of yourself from elemental water lets you cast spells frrom unexpected directions</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Conjuration</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <text>You conjure a watery double of yourself in an unoccupied square within range. The double occupies its space, and it lasts until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>While the conjuration remains, you can use your space or the double's space as the origin of your Wizard attack powers.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Wizard's Escape</title>
      <class>Wizard</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
      <fluff>With a flash, you are gone</fluff>
         <frequency>Daily</frequency>
         <keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
         <action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An enemy hits you with a melee attack</text>
         </section>
         <section auto="personal"/>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You teleport up to 5 squares to a space that is not adjacent to an enemy.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

</catalog>
