<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="deity.xsl"?>
<deity>
   <name>Asmodeus</name>
   <title>Supreme Master of the Nine Hells</title>

   <type>Greater God</type>
   <alignment>Evil</alignment>
   <gender>Male</gender>
   <domain>Civilization</domain> <domain>Tyranny</domain>

   <text>Asmodeus is the evil god of tyranny and domination. He rules the Nine Hells with an iron fist and a silver tongue. Aside from devils, evil creatures such as rakshasas pay him homage, and evil tieflings and warlocks are drawn to his dark cults. His rules are strict and his punishments harsh:</text>
   <text>&#9658; Seek power over others, that you might rule with strength as the Lord of Hell does.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Repay evil with evil. If others are kind to you, exploit their weakness for your own gain.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Show neither pity not mercy to those who are caught underfoot as you climb your way to power. The weak do not deserve compassion.</text>

   <power>
      <title>Asmodeus's Fiery Command</title>
      <class>Class</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <fluff>Asmodeus rewards those who please him and destroys those who fail</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Divine, Fire</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
         <section>
            <name>Channel Divinity:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You can only use one Channel Divinity power per encounter</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>One ally in the burst</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>If the target hits and enemy with an attack before the end of his or her next turn, the attack deals an additional 5 fire damage, and the target gains 5 temporary hit points.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the target does not hit with an attack before the end of his or her next turn, the target and each creature adjacent to him or her take 5 fire damage.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>10 fire damage or temporary hit points.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
            <text>15 fire damage or temporary hit points.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
</deity>
