<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="deity.xsl"?>
<deity>
   <name>Avandra</name>

   <type>God</type>
   <alignment>Good</alignment>
   <gender>Female</gender>
   <domain>Change</domain> <domain>Freedom</domain> <domain>Luck</domain>

   <text>The god of change, Avandra delights in freedom, trade, travel, adventure, and the frontier. Her temples are few in civilized lands, but her wayside shrines appear throughout the land. Halflings, merchants, and all types of adventurers are drawn to her worship, and many people raise a glass in her honor, viewing her as a the god of luck. Her commandments are few:</text>
   <text>&#9658; Luck favors the bold. Take your fate into your own hands, and Avandra smiles upon you.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Strike back against those who would rob you of your freedom and urge others to fight for their of liberty.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Change is inevitable, but it takes the work of the faithful to ensure that change is for the better.</text>

   <power>
      <title>Avandra's Rescue</title>
      <class>Channel Divinity</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <fluff>Avandra smiles upon you and helps you rescrue a friend in need</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Divine</keyword>
         <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="channeldivinity"/>
         <section><name>Target:</name><type>Melee</type><range>1</range><target>one ally who is the same size as you or smaller</target></section>
         <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>You slide both you and the target 1 square, swapping positions.</section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Traveler's Celerity</title>
      <class>Channel Divinity</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <frequency>Encounter</frequency> <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
      <fluff>Avandra blesses those in a bind with an easy escape and fleet feet</fluff>
      <section auto="no-opportunity"/>
      <section><name>Prerequisite:</name>You must be at least 11th level.</section>
      <section auto="channeldivinity"/>
      <section><name>Target:</name><type>Ranged</type><range>5</range><target>you or one ally</target></section>
      <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>The target gains a +2 bonus to speed until the end of your next turn.</section>
      <section shade="">Also, the target can make a saving throw against each effect that slows, immobilizes or restrains it, even if that effect does not normally end on a save.</section>
   </power>
</deity>
