<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="deity.xsl"?>
<deity>
   <name>Erathis</name>

   <type>God</type>
   <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
   <gender>Female</gender>
   <domain>Civilization</domain> <domain>Creation</domain> <domain>Justice</domain>

   <text>Erathis is the god of civilization. She is the muse of great invention, founder of cities, and author of laws. Rulers, judges, pioneers, and devoted citizens revere her, and her temples hold prominent places in most of the world's major cities. Her laws are many, but their purpose is straightforward:</text>
   <text>&#9658; Work with others to achieve your goals. Community and order are always stronger than the disjointed efforts of lone individuals.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Tame the wilderness to make it fit for habitation and defend the light of civilization against the encroaching darknes.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Seek out new ideas, new inventions, new lands to inhabit, new wilderness to conquer. Build machines, build cities, build empires.</text>

      <power>
      <title>Harmony of Erathis</title>
      <class>Channel Divinity</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <fluff>Erathis brings harmony of purpose to like-minded allies</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Divine</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="channeldivinity"/>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <target>one ally</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target gains a +2 power bonus to the first attack roll he or she makes before the start of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Progress of Erathis</title>
      <class>Channel Divinity</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <fluff>With a quick prayer to Erathis, you call your allies to move forward through the wilderness</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Divine</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section auto="channeldivinity"/>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
            <target>you and each ally in the burst</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target ignores difficult terrain until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Once per day, you can use this power outside of combat. When you do, each target treats the distance multiplier for exploration speed as one step better for 1 hour (for example, x0.5 as x0.75).</text>
         </section>
   </power>
</deity>
