<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="deity.xsl"?>
<deity>
   <name>Ioun</name>

   <type>God</type>
   <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
   <gender>Female</gender>
   <domain>Fate</domain> <domain>Knowledge</domain> <domain>Skill</domain>

   <text>Ioun is the god of knowledge, skill, and prophecy. Sages, seers, and tacticians revere her, as do all who live by their knowledge and mental power. Corellon is the patron of arcane magic, but Ioun is the patron of its study. Libraries and wizard academies are built in her name. Her commands are also teachings:</text>
   <text>&#9658; Seek the perfection of your mind by bringing reason, perception, and emotion into balance with one another.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Accumulate, preserve, and distribute knowledge in all forms. Pursue education, build libraries, and seek out lost and ancient lore.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Be watchful at all times for the followers of Vecna, who seek to control knowledge and keep secrets. Oppose their schemes, unmask their secrets, and blind them with the light of truth and reason.</text>

   <power>
      <title>Ioun's Poise</title>
      <class>Channel Divinity</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <fluff>Ioun grants strength of will to those she favors</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Divine</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Ranged</type> <range>5</range>
         <section auto="channeldivinity" />
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>You or one ally</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target gains a +5 power bonus to Will until the start of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Ioun's Recall</title>
      <class>Channel Divinity</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <fluff>You call upon Ioun for a flash of divine inspiration, so nothing can remain hidden from you for long</fluff>
      <part>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Divine</keyword>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <type>Personal</type>
         <section auto="channeldivinity" />
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>Until the end of your next turn, you gain a +5 power bonus to all checks to recall knowledge.</text>
         </section>
      </part>
   </power>
</deity>
