<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="deity.xsl"?>
<deity>
   <name>Zehir</name>
   <title>Lord of Darkness</title>

   <type>God</type>
   <alignment>Evil</alignment>
   <gender>Male</gender>
   <domain>Darkness</domain> <domain>Poison</domain>

   <text>Zehir is the evil god of darkness, poison, and assassins. Snakes are his favored creation, and the yuan-ti revere him above all other gods, offering sacrifice to him in pits full of writhing serpents. He urges his followers to:</text>
   <text>&#9658; Hide under the cloak of night, that your deeds might be kept in secret.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Kill in Zehir's name and offer each murder as a sacrifice.</text>
   <text>&#9658; Delight in poison, and surround yourself with snakes.</text>

   <power>
      <title>Zehir's Dark Blessing</title>
      <class>Channel Divinity</class> <category>Utility</category>
      <fluff>An ally's attack becomes an offering to Zehir, and darkness cloaks him or her, granting vigor</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Divine</keyword>
         <action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
         <section auto="channeldivinity"/>
         <section>
            <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>An ally within 5 squares of you drops a creature to 0 hit points or fewer; the creature must be granting combat advantage to the ally</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <type>Close</type> <range>burst 5</range>
            <target>the triggering ally in the burst</target>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
            <text>The target gains concealment until the end of his or her next turn, and gains temporary hit points equal to 5 + one-half the level of the creature that he or she dropped to 0 or fewer hit points.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <text>If the triggering attack has the Poison keyword or was made using a poisoned weapon, the target can choose to regain hit points equal to the amount of temporary hit points that he or she would have gained. If he or she does, this power gains the Healing keyword.</text>
         </section>
   </power>
</deity>
