<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="spell.xsl"?>

<catalog>
   <category>
      <catename>Cantrips</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Blade Ward</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>Abjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Self</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>1 round</duration>
         
         <section>You extend your hand and trace a sigil of warding in the air. Until the end of your next turn, you have resistance against bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage deals by weapon attacks.</section>         
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Light</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>Evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, M (a firefly or phosphorescent moss)</components>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>You touch one object that is no larger than 10 feet in any dimension. Until the spell ends, the object sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet. The light can be colored as you like. Completely covering the object with something opaque blocks the light. The spell ends if you cast it again or dismiss it as an action.</section>
         <section>If you target an object held or worn by a hostile creature, that creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw to avoid the spell.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Sacred Flames</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>Evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>Flame-like radiance descends on a creature that you can see within range. The target must succeeds on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d8 radiant damage. The target gains no benefit from cover for this saving throw.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (2d8), 11th level (3d8), and 17th level (4d8).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>True Strike</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>Divination</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>30 feet</range>
         <components>S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 round</duration>
         
         <section>You extend your hand and point a finger at a target in range. Your magic grants you a brief insight into the target's defenses. On your next turn, you gain advantage on your first attack roll against the target, provided that this spell hasn't ended.</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
   <category>
      <catename>1st-level Spells</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Cure Wounds</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>Evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <component>V, S</component>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>A creature you touch regains a number of hit points equal to 1d8 + your spellcasting ability modifier. This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<ib>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the healing increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Guiding Bolt</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>Evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>1 round</duration>
         
         <section>A flash of light streaks toward a creature of your choice within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 4d6 radiant damage, and the next attack roll made against this target before the end of your next turn has advantage, thanks to the mystical dim light glittering on the target until then.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Protection from Evil and Good</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>Abjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S, M (holy water or powdered silver and iron, which the spell consumes)</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
         
         <section>Until the spell ends, one willing creature you touch is protected against certain types of creatures: aberrations, celestials, elementals, fey, fiends, and undead.</section>
         <section>The protection grants several benefits. Creatures of those types have disadvantage on attack rolls against the target. The target also can't be charmed, frightened, or possessed by them. If the target is already charmed, frightened or possessed by such a creature, the target has advantage on any new saving throw against the relevant effect.</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
         
</catalog>
