<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="spell.xsl"?>

<catalog>
   <category>
      <catename>Cantrips</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Acid Splash</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You hurl a bubble of acid. Choose one creature within range, or choose two creatures within range that are within 5 feet of each other. A target must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d6 acid damage.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Create Bonfire</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You create a bonfire on ground that you can see within range. Until the spell ends, the magic bonfire fills a 5-foot cube. Any creature in the bonfire's space when you cast this spell must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d8 fire damage. A creature must also make the saving throw when it moves into the bonfire's space for the time on a turn or ends its turn there.</section>
         <section>The bonfire ignites flammable objects in its area that aren't being worn or carried.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (2d8), 11th level (3d8), and 17th level (4d8).</section>
      </spell>
         
      <spell>
         <title>Dancing Lights</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a bit of phosphorus or wychwood, or a glowworm)</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You create up to four torch-sized lights within range, making them appear as torches, langerns, or glowing orbs that hover in the air for the duration. You can also combine the four lights into one glowing vaguely humanoid form of Medium size. Whichever for you choose, each light sheds dim light in a 10-foot radius.</section>
         <section>As a bonus action on your turn, you can move the lights up to 60 feet to a new spot within range. A light must be within 20 feet of another light created by this spell, and a light winks out if it exceeds the spell's range.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Fire Bolt</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You hurl a mote of fire at a creature or object within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d10 fire damage. A flammable object hit by this spells ignites if it isn't being worn or carried.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d10 when you reach 5th level (2d10), 11th level (3d10), and 17th level (4d10).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Frostbite</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <component>V, S</component>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You cause numbing frost to form on one creature that you can see within range. The target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 1d6 cold damage, and has disadvantage on the next weapon attack roll it makes before the end of its next turn.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Guidance</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>divination</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>touch</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You touch one willing creature. Once before the spell ends, the target can roll a d4 and add the number rolled to one ability check of its choice. It can roll the die before or after making the ability check. The spell then ends.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Light</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, M (a firefly or phosphorescent moss)</components>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>You touch one object that is no larger than 10 feet in any dimension. Until the spell ends, the object sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet. The light can be colored as you like. Completely covering the object with something opaque blocks the light. The spell ends if you cast it again or dismiss it as an action.</section>
         <section>If you target an object held or worn by a hostile creature, that creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw to avoid the spell.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Mage Hand</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>30 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>A spectral, floating hand appears at a point you choose within range. The hand lasts for the duration or until you dismiss it as an action. The hand vanishes if it is ever more than 30 feet away from you or if you cast this spell again.</section>
         <section>You can use your action to control the hand. You can use the hand to manipulate an object, open an unlocked door or container, stow or retrieve an item from an open container, or pour the contents out of a vial. You can move the hand up to 30 feet each time you use it.</section>
         <section>The hand can't attack, activate magic items, or carry more than 10 pounds.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Magic Stone</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 bonus action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You touch one to three pebbles and imbue them with magic. You or someone else can make a ranged spell attack with one of the pebbles by throwing it or hurling it with a sling. If thrown, a pebble has a range of 60 feet. If someone else attacks with a pebble, that attacker adds your spellcasting ability modifier, not the attacker's, to the attack roll. On a hit, the target takes bludgeoning damage equal to 1d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier. Whether the attack hits or misses, the spell then ends on the stone.</section>
         <section>If you cast this spell again, the spell ends on any pebbles still affected by your previous casting.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Mending</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 minute</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S, M (two lodestones)</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>This spell repairs a single break or tear in an object you touch, such as a broken chain link, two halves of a broken key, a torn cloak, or a leaking wineskin. As long as the break or tear is no longer than 1 foot in any dimension, you mend it, leaving no trace of the former damage.</section>
         <section>This spell can physically repair a magic item or construct, but the spell can't restore magic to such an object.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Message</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a short piece of copper wire)</components>
         <duration>1 round</duration>
         
         <section>You point your finger toward a creature within range and whisper a message. The target (and only the target) hears the message and can reply in a whisper that only you can hear.</section>
         <section>You can cast this spell through solid objects if you are familiar with the target and know it is beyond the barrier. Magical silence, 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood blocks the spell. The spell doesn't have to follow a straight line and can travel freely around corners or through openings.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Poison Spray</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>10 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You extend your hand toward a creature you can see within range and project a puff of noxious gas from your palm. The creature must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 1d12 poison damage.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d12 when you reach 5th level (2d12), 11th level (3d12), and 17th level (4d12).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Prestidigitation</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>Transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>10 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Up to 1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>This spell is a minor magical trick that novice spellcasters use for practice. You create one of the following effects within range:</section>
         <section>&#8226; You create an instantaneous, harmless sensory effect, such as a shower of sparks, a puff of wind, faint musical notes, or an odd odor.</section>
         <section>&#8226; You instantaneously light or snuff out a candle, a torch, or a small campfire.</section>
         <section>&#8226; You instantaneously clear or soil an object no larger than 1 cubic foot.</section>
         <section>&#8226; You chill, warm, or flavour up to 1 cubic foot of nonliving material for 1 hour.</section>
         <section>&#8226; You make a color, a small mark, or a symbol appear on an object or a surface for 1 hour.</section>
         <section>&#8226; You create a nonmagical trinket or an illusory image that can fit in your hand and that lasts until the end of your next turn.</section>
         <section>If you cast this spell multiple times, you can have up to three of its non-instantaneous effects active at a time, and you can dismiss such an effect as an action.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Ray of Frost</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>A frigid beam of blue-white light streaks toward a creature within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, it takes 1d8 cold damage, and its speed is reduced by 10 feet until the start of your next turn.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (2d8), 11th level (3d8), and 17th level (4d8).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Resistance</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>abjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>touch</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a miniature cloak)</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You touch one willing creature. Once before the spell ends, the target can roll a d4 and add the number rolled to one saving throw of its choice. It can roll the die before or after making the saving throw. The spell then ends.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Shocking Grasp</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>touch</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>Lightning springs from your hand to deliver a shock to a creature you try to touch. Make a spell attack against the target. You have advantage on the attack roll if the target is wearing armor made of metal. On a hit, the target takes 1d8 lightning damage, and it can't take reactions until the start of its next turn.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (2d8), 11th level (3d8), and 17th level (4d8).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Spare the Dying</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>necromancy</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You touch a living creature that has 0 hit points. The creature becomes stable. This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Thorn Whip</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>30 feet</range>
         <components>V, S, M (the stem of a plant with thorns)</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You create a long, vine-like whip covered in thorns that lashes out at your command toward a creature in range. Make a melee spell attack against the target. If the attack hits, the creature takes 1d6 piercing damage, and if the creature is Large or smaller, you pull the creature up to 10 feet closer to you.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Thunderclap</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>5 feet</range>
         <components>S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You create a burst of thunderous sound that can be heard up to 100 feet away. Each creature within range, other than you, must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 1d6 thunder damage.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
</catalog>
