<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="spell.xsl"?>

<catalog>
   <category>
      <catename>Cantrips</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Acid Splash</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You hurl a bubble of acid. Choose one creature within range, or choose two creatures within range that are within 5 feet of each other. A target must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d6 acid damage.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Create Bonfire</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You create a bonfire on ground that you can see within range. Until the spell ends, the magic bonfire fills a 5-foot cube. Any creature in the bonfire's space when you cast this spell must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d8 fire damage. A creature must also make the saving throw when it moves into the bonfire's space for the time on a turn or ends its turn there.</section>
         <section>The bonfire ignites flammable objects in its area that aren't being worn or carried.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (2d8), 11th level (3d8), and 17th level (4d8).</section>
      </spell>
         
      <spell>
         <title>Dancing Lights</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a bit of phosphorus or wychwood, or a glowworm)</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You create up to four torch-sized lights within range, making them appear as torches, langerns, or glowing orbs that hover in the air for the duration. You can also combine the four lights into one glowing vaguely humanoid form of Medium size. Whichever for you choose, each light sheds dim light in a 10-foot radius.</section>
         <section>As a bonus action on your turn, you can move the lights up to 60 feet to a new spot within range. A light must be within 20 feet of another light created by this spell, and a light winks out if it exceeds the spell's range.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Fire Bolt</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You hurl a mote of fire at a creature or object within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d10 fire damage. A flammable object hit by this spells ignites if it isn't being worn or carried.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d0 when you reach 5th level (2d10), 11th level (3d10), and 17th level (4d10).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Frostbite</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <component>V, S</component>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You cause numbing frost to form on one creature that you can see within range. The target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 1d6 cold damage, and has disadvantage on the next weapon attack roll it makes before the end of its next turn.</section>
         <section>The spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Guidance</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>divination</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>touch</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You touch one willing creature. Once before the spell ends, the target can roll a d4 and add the number rolled to one ability check of its choice. It can roll the die before or after making the ability check. The spell then ends.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Light</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, M (a firefly or phosphorescent moss)</component>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>You touch one object that is no larger than 10 feet in any dimension. Until the spell ends, the object sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet. The light can be colored as you like. Completely covering the object with something opaque blocks the light. The spell ends if you cast it again or dismiss it as an action.</section>
         <section>If you target an object held or worn by a hostile creature, that creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw to avoid the spell.</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
</catalog>
