<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="spell.xsl"?>

<catalog>
   <category>
      <catename>1st-level Spells</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Absorb Elements</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>abjuration</school>
         <casting>1 reaction, which you take when you take acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder damage</casting>
         <range>Self</range>
         <components>S</components>
         <duration>1 round</duration>
         
         <section>The spell captures some of the incoming energy, lessening its effects on you and storing it for your next melee attack. You have resistance to the triggering damage type until the start of your next turn. Also, the first time you hit with a melee attack on your next turn, the target takes an extra 1d6 damage of the triggering type, and the spell ends.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Alarm</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>abjuration (ritual)</school>
         <casting>1 minute</casting>
         <range>30 feet</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a tiny bell and a piece of fine silver wire)</components>
         <duration>8 hours</duration>
         
         <section>You set an alarm against unwanted intrusion. Choose a dor, a window, or an area within range that is no larger than a 20-foot cube. Until the spell ends, an alarm alerts you whenever a Tiny or larger creature touches or enters the warded area. When you cast the spell, you can designate creatures that won't set off the alarm. You also choose whether the alarm is mental or audible.</section>
         <section>A mental alarm alerts you with a ping in your mind if you are within 1 mile of the warded area. This ping awakens you if you are sleeping.</section>
         <section>An audible alarm produces the sound of a hand bell for 10 seconds within 60 foot.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Arcane Weapon</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 bonus action</casting>
         <range>Self</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>You channel arcane energy into one simple or martial weapon you're holding, and choose one damage type: acid, cold, fire, lightning, poison, or thunder. Until the spell ends, you deal an extra 1d6 damage of the chosen type to any target you hit with the weapon. If the weapon isn't magical, it becomes a magic weapon for the spell's duration.</section>
         <section>As a bonus action, you can change the damage type, choosing from the options above.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, you can maintain your concentration on the spell for up to 8 hours.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Catapult</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>Choose one object weighing 1 to 5 pounds within range that isn't being worn or carried. The object flies in a straight line up to 90 feet in a direction you choose before falling to the ground, stopping early if it impacts against a solid surface. If the object would strike a creature, that creature must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the object strikes the target and stops moving. When the object strikes something, the object and what it strikes each take 3d8 bludgeoning damage.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the maximum weight of objects that you can target with this spell increases by 5 pounds, and the damage increases by 1d8, for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Cure Wounds</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>A creature you touch regains a number of hit points equal to 1d8 + your spellcasting ability modifier. This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the healing increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Detect Magic</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>divination (ritual)</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Self</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
         
         <section>For the duration, you can sense the presence of magic within 30 feet of you. If you sense magic in this way, you can use your action to see a faint aura around any visible creature or object in the area that bears magic, and you learn its school of magic, if any.</section>
         <section>The spell can penetrate most barriers, but it is blocked by 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, 3 feet of wood or dirt.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Disguise Self</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>illusion</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Self</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>You make yourself -including your clothing, armor, weapons, and other belongings on your person- look different until the spell ends or until you use your action to dismiss it. You can seem 1 foot shorter or taller and can appear thin, fat, or in between. You can't change your body type, so you must adopt a form that has the same basic arrangement of limbs. Otherwise, the extent of the illusion is up to you.</section>
         <section>The changes wrought by this spell fail to hold up to physical inspection. For example, if you use this spell to add a hat to your outfit, objects pass through the hat, and anyone who touches it would feel nothing or would feel your head and hair. If you use this spell to appear thinner than you are, the hand of someone who reaches out to touch you would bump into you while it was seemingly still in midair.</section>
         <section>To discern that you are disguised, a creature can use its action to inspect your appearance and must succeed on an Intelligence (Investigation) check against your spell save DC.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Expeditious Retreat</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 bonus action</casting>
         <range>Self</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
         
         <section>This spell allows you to move at an incredible pace. When you cast this spell, and then as a bonus action on each of your turns until the spell ends, you can take the Dash action.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Faerie Fire</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V</components>
         <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>Each object in a 20-foot cube within range is outlined in blue, green, or violet light (your choice). Any creature in the area when the spell is cast is also outlined in light if it fails a Dexterity saving throw. For the duration, objects and affected creatures shed dim light in a 10-foot radius.</section>
         <section>Any attack roll against an affected creature or object has advantage if the attacker can see it, and the affected creature or object can't benefit from being invisible.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>False Life</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>necromancy</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Self</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a small amount of alcohol or distilled spirits)</components>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>Bolstering yourself with a necromantic facsimile of life, you gain 1d4 + 4 temporary hit points for the duration.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you gain 5 additional temporary hit points for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Feather Fall</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 reaction>, which you take when you or a creature within 60 feet of you falls</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, M (a small feather or piece of down)</components>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>Choose up to 5 falling creatures within range. A falling creature's rate of descent slows to 60 feet per round until the spell ends. If the creature lands before the spell ends, it takes no falling damage and can land on its feet, and the spell ends for that creature.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Grease</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a bit of pork rind or butter)</components>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>Slick grease covers the ground in a 10-foot square centered on a point within range and turns it into difficult terrain for the duration.</section>
         <section>When the grease appears, each creature standing in its area must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or fall prone. A creature that enters the area or ends its turn there must also succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or fall prone.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Identify</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>divination (ritual)</school>
         <casting>1 minute</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a pearl worth at least 100 gp and an owl feather)</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You choose one object that you must touch throughout the casting of the spell. If it is a magic item or some other magic-imbued object, you learn its properties and how to use them, whether it requires attunement to use, and how many charges it has, if any. You learn whether any spells are affecting the item and what they are. If the item was created by a spell, you learn which spell created it.</section>
         <section>If you instead touch a creature throughout the casting, you learn what spells, if any, are currently affecting it.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Jump</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a grasshopper's hind leg)</components>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You touch a creature. The creature's jump distance is tripled until the spell ends.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Longstrider</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Touch</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a pinch of dirt)</components>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>You touch a creature. The target's speed increases by 10 feet until the spell ends.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Sanctuary</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>abjuration</school>
         <casting>1 bonus action</casting>
         <range>30 feet</range>
         <components>V, S, M (a small silver mirror)</components>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You ward a creature within range against attacks. Until the spell ends, any creature who targets the warded creature with an attack or a harmful spell must first make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature must choose a new target or lose the attack or spell. The spell doesn't protect the warded creature from area effects, such as the explosion of a fireball.</section>
         <section>If the warded creature makes an attack or casts a spell that effects an enemy creature, this spell ends.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Snare</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>abjuration</school>
         <casting>1 minute</casting>
         <range>touch</range>
         <components>S, M (25 feet of rope, which the spell consumes)</components>
         <duration>8 hours</duration>
         
         <section>As you cast this spell, you use the rope to create a circle with a 5-foot radius on the ground or the floor. When you finish casting, the rope disappears and the circle becomes a magic trap.</section>
         <section>This trap is nearly invisible, requiring a successful Intelligence (Investigation) check against your spell save DC to be discerned.</section>
         <section>The trap triggers when a Small, Medium, or Large creature moves onto the ground or the floor in the spell's radius. That creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or be magically hoisted in the air, leaving it hanging upside down 3 feet above the groun or the floor. The creature is restrained there until the spell ends.</section>
         <section>A restrained creature can make a Dexterity saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. Alternatively, the creature or someone else who can reach it can use an action to make an Intelligence (Arcana) check against your spell save DC. On a success, the restrained effect ends.</section>
         <section>After the trap is triggered, the spell ends when no creature is restrained by it.</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
</catalog>
