<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="spell.xsl"?>

<catalog>
   <category>
      <catename>Racial Cantrip</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Prestidigitation</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>Transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>10 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Up to 1 hour</duration>
         
         <section>This spell is a minor magical trick that novice spellcasters use for practice. You create one of the following effects within range:</section>
         <section style="bullet">You create an instantaneous, harmless sensory effect, such as a shower of sparks, a puff of wind, faint musical notes, or an odd odor.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You instantaneously light or snuff out a candle, a torch, or a small campfire.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You instantaneously clear or soil an object no larger than 1 cubic foot.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You chill, warm, or flavour up to 1 cubic foot of nonliving material for 1 hour.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You make a color, a small mark, or a symbol appear on an object or a surface for 1 hour.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You create a nonmagical trinket or an illusory image that can fit in your hand and that lasts until the end of your next turn.</section>
         <section>If you cast this spell multiple times, you can have up to three of its non-instantaneous effects active at a time, and you can dismiss such an effect as an action.</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
   <category>
      <catename>Warlock Cantrips</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Green-Flame Blade</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>5 feet</range>
         <components>V, M (a weapon)</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>As part of the action to cast this spell, you must make a melee attack with a weapon against one creature within the spell's range, otherwise the spell fails. On a hit, the target suffers the attack's normal effects, and green fire leaps from the target to a different creature of your choice that you can see within 5 feet of it. The second creature takes fire damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases when you reach higher levels. At 5th level, the melee attack deals an extra 1d8 fire damage to the target, and the fire damage to the second creature increases to 1d8 + your spellcasting ability modifier. Both damage rolls increase by 1d8 at 11th level and 17th level.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Sword Burst</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>5 feet</range>
         <components>V</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You create a momentary circle of spectral blades that sweep around you. Each creature within range, other than you, must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d6 force damage.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
</catalog>
