<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="spell.xsl"?>

<catalog>
   <category>
      <catename>Racial Cantrip</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Thaumaturgy</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>30 feet</range>
         <components>V</components>
         <duration>Up to 1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>You manifest a minor wonder, a sign of supernatural power, within range. You create one of the following magical effects within range:</section>
         <section style="bullet">Your voice booms up to three times as loud as normal for 1 minute.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You cause flames to flicker, brighten, dim, or change color for 1 minute.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You cause harmless tremors in the ground for 1 minute.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You create an instantaneous sound that originates from a point of your choice within range, such as a rumble of thunder, the cry of a raven, or ominous whispers.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You instantaneously cause an unlocked door or window to fly open or slam shut.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You alter the appearance of your eyes for 1 minute.</section>
         <section>If you cast this spell multiple times, you can have up to three of its 1-minute effects active at a time, and you can dismiss such an effect as an action.</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
   <category>
      <catename>Sorcerer Cantrips</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Control Flames</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>transmutation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>60 feet</range>
         <components>S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous or 1 hour (see below)</duration>
         
         <section>You choose a nonmagical flame that you can see within range and that fits within a 5-foot cube. You affect it in one of the following ways:</section>
         <section style="bullet">You instantaneously expand the flame 5 feet in one direction, provided that wood or other fuel is present in the new location.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You instantaneously extinguish the flames within the cube.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You double or halve the area of bright light and dim light cast by the flame, change its color, or both. The change lasts for 1 hour.</section>
         <section style="bullet">You cause simple shapes -such as the vague form of a creature, an inanimate object, or location- to appear within the flames and animate as you like. The shapes last for 1 hour.</section>
         <section>If you cast this spell multiple tiimes, you can have up to three non-instantaneous effects created by it activate at a time, and you can dismiss such an effect as an action.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Fire Bolt</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You hurl a mote of fire at a creature or object within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d10 fire damage. A flammable object hit by this spells ignites if it isn't being worn or carried.</section>
         <section>This spell's damage increases by 1d10 when you reach 5th level (2d10), 11th level (3d10), and 17th level (4d10).</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Mage Hand</title>
         <level>Cantrip</level> <school>conjuration</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>30 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         
         <section>A spectral, floating hand appears at a point you choose within range. The hand lasts for the duration or until you dismiss it as an action. The hand vanishes if it is ever more than 30 feet away from you or if you cast this spell again.</section>
         <section>You can use your action to control the hand. You can use the hand to manipulate an object, open an unlocked door or container, stow or retrieve an item from an open container, or pour the contents out of a vial. You can move the hand up to 30 feet each time you use it.</section>
         <section>The hand can't attack, activate magic items, or carry more than 10 pounds.</section>
      </spell>
      
   </category>
   
   <category>
      <catename>1st-level Sorcerer Spells</catename>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Burning Hands</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>Evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>Self (15-foot cone)</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>As you hold your hands with thumbs touching and fingers spread, a thin sheet of flames shoots forth from your outstrecthed fingertips. Each creature in a 15-foot cone must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 3d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</section>
         <section>The fire ignites any flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
      
      <spell>
         <title>Magic Missile</title>
         <level>1st</level> <school>evocation</school>
         <casting>1 action</casting>
         <range>120 feet</range>
         <components>V, S</components>
         <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
         
         <section>You create three glowing darts of magical force. Each dart hits a creature of your choice that you can see within range. A dart deals 1d4 + 1 force damage to its target. The darts all strike simultaneously, and you can direct them to hit one creature or several.</section>
         <section><![CDATA[<b>At Higher Levels.</b>]]> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the spell creates one more dart for each slot level above 1st.</section>
      </spell>
   
</catalog>
