<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
   <name>Druid</name>
	<subname>Protector</subname>
	<role>Leader</role>
	<source>Primal</source>
	<shortfluff>Through careful study of and communion with the natural world, you have mastered the power and magic of nature, using it to create a line of defense between the natural world and those that would harm it.</shortfluff>
	<keyability>Wisdom</keyability>
	<keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
	<keyability>Constitution</keyability>

	<proficiency>
		<type>Armor</type>
		<name>Cloth</name>
      <name>Leather</name>
      <name>Hide</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Weapon</type>
		<name>Simple melee</name>
		<name>Simple ranged</name>
	</proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Implement</type>
      <name>Staff</name>
      <name>Totem</name>
   </proficiency>

   <defense>
      <name>Reflex</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
	<defense>
		<name>Will</name>
		<value>+1</value>
	</defense>

	<hpbase>12</hpbase>
	<hpgain>5</hpgain>
	<surgebase>7</surgebase>

	<skills>
		<trained>Nature</trained>
		<number>3</number>
	</skills>

	<fluff>Secretive and enigmatic, Druids call the wilderness their home. They are capable of running with a wolf pack, speaking with the most ancient trees, and watching thunderstorms from atop the clouds themselves. They regard challenges as tests, both of their fitness and of their connection with the wild places of the world. And though many druids project an outward calm, they have the cunning of the beast and the fury of the storm.</fluff>
   <fluff>Whether he or she was born to the wilds or retreated from civilization, whether he or she chose the path or answered a call that was whispered in the heart, a Protector shares a bond with the primal spirits of nature. A Protector is neither their servant nor their master, but winds, trees, and beasts heed his or her words, for they recognize him or her as kin.</fluff>
   <fluff>A Druid can call to the spirits, and they will entangle his or her foes or smite his or her enemies with the storm. A druid can unleash his or her spirit, becoming a Primal Beast, uncaged and untamed.</fluff>

	<feature>
		<name>Balance of Nature</name>
      <benefit>Some Druids favor being in beast form, while others prefer being in humanoid form. However, just as Druids seek balance in the world between divine and primordial forces, they pursue balance within their own minds and bodies.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain an additional 1st-level at-will attack power from your class. This additional power must have the <key>Beast Form</key> keyword. Also, you must know at least one 1st-level at-will attack power from your class that does not have the Beast Form keyword.</benefit>
      <benefit>This means that you always have access to attacks in either beast form or humanoid form.</benefit>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Druid Circle</name>
      <benefit>Each Protector belongs to a druidic circle, a group of like-minded servants of nature. A druidic circle bears similarity to the orders of clerics and other servants of gods. However, the druids of your circle revere and protect the natural world.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose either Circle of Elements, Circle of Providence, Circle of Renewal, or Circle of the Swarm to determine the kind of druidic circle you belong to.</benefit>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Circle of Elements</name>
         <benefit>Underlying primal magic are the elemental forces at the heart of its creation. Here and there, one can find the hallmarks of the primordials' handiwork, places steeped in ancient magic that warps and transforms the spirits bound to those sites. Although Protectors of the Circle of Elements confer with elemental-touched spirits in the same way they interact with other primal entities, the magic wielded by them bears a striking similarity to that wielded by those that master magic from the Elemental Chaos.</benefit>
         <benefit><name>Primal Wrath:</name> While you are not wearing heavy armor, you gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls with druid attacks that have the <key>Cold</key>, <key>Fire</key>, <key>Lightning</key>, or <key>Thunder</key> keywords.</benefit>
         <benefit>When you enter beast form, choose one of cold, fire, lightning or thunder. You gain resist against the chosen damage type equal to one-third your level + your Dexterity modifier. You lose the resist when you are no longer in beast form.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Circle of Providence</name>
         <benefit>A Protector who chooses the Circle of Providence has made a pledge to defend the bounty of nature. Members of this druidic circle watch over forests, plains, and grasslands, keeping them safe from monsters, uncaring humanoids, and dark magic.</benefit>
         <benefit><name>Primal Predator:</name> While you are not wearing heavy armor, you gain a +1 bonus to speed.</benefit>
         <benefit>While you are in beast form, you gain a +2 bonus to all defenses against attacks triggered by your movement.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Circle of Renewal</name>
         <benefit>As a member of the Circle of Renewal, a Protector's mission is to restore places ravaged by war and unnatural threats. Such Druids make it their cause to bring life back to parched deserts and scrublands, or to seed life for the first time in areas that have never known it.</benefit>
         <benefit><name>Primal Guardian:</name> While you are not wearing heavy armor, you can use Constitution instead of Dexterity or Intelligence to determine your AC.</benefit>
         <benefit>While you are in beast form, you gain a +2 bonus to attacks rolls with <![CDATA[<i>reactive strikes</i>]]>.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Circle of the Swarm</name>
         <benefit>Members of the Circle of the Swarm see great strength in the unity of purpose and combined might of a colony of ants or a nest of hornets. Most Druids assume the forms of creatures such as bears, panthers, and rams, but a member of the Circle of the Swarm splinters into hundreds of insects, all driven towards a single purpose by the Druid's mind. He or she is at once all the creatures in the swarm and none of them.</benefit>
         <benefit><name>Primal Swarm:</name>While you are not wearing heavy armor, you gain a +1 shield bonus to AC and Reflex.</benefit>
         <benefit>While you are in beast form, you gain resist all against melee attacks and ranged attacks. The resist equals one-third your level + your Constitution modifier.</benefit>
      </subfeature>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Nature's Bounty</name>
      <benefit>As keepers of nature, Druids learn to draw knowledge from the bountiful flora and fauna.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose Alchemical Bounty or Ritual Bounty as the kind of knowledge you draw from nature.</benefit>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Alchemical Bounty</name>
         <benefit>You have learned to brew remedies and afflictions alike from the various ingredients found in nature.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain the Alchemist feat.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain a formula book  containing the formula for two 1st-level alchemical items that have Nature as a key skill.</benefit>
         <benefit>At 5th level and every five levels thereafter, you learn two additional formulas of your level or lower for items that have Nature as a key skill.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Ritual Bounty</name>
         <benefit>You have mastered rites that allow you to borrow nature's power.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain the Ritual Caster feat.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain a ritual book that contains two 1st-level rituals of your choice. Both rituals must have Nature as a key skill.</benefit>
         <benefit>At 5th level and every five levels threreafter, you learn two additional rituals of your level or lower that have Nature as a key skill.</benefit>
      </subfeature>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Nature's Growth</name>
      <benefit>One of the fundamental evocations brings life even the harshest conditions and climates. The power of nature erupts at a Protector's command to hinder his or her foes, even as he or she slips through the hindrance with ease.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>nature's growth</i>]]> class power.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Nature's Growth</title>
         <class>Druid</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <fluff>A thicket of vines, plants, and tough shrubs erupts as if from nowhere to clutch at your foes</fluff>
         <keyword>Primal</keyword> <keyword>Zone</keyword>
         <section><type>Area</type> <range>burst 1 within 10 squares</range></section>
         <section indent="1"><name>Level 11:</name><type style="bold">Area</type><range>burst 2 within 10 squares</range></section>
         <section indent="1"><name>Level 21:</name><type style="bold">Area</type><range>burst 3 within 10 squares</range></section>
         <section shade="true">
            <name>Effect:</name>
            <text>The burst creates a zone of vegetation that lasts until the end of the encounter.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true">
            <text>The zone is difficult terrain for all creatures other than you. You can dismiss the zone as a minor action.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <name>Circle of Elements:</name>
            <text>Choose one of the following when you use this power: cold, fire, lightning, or thunder.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <text>Enemies in the zone have vulnerable to the chosen type of damage. The vulnerable equals one-half your Dexterity modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="2">
            <name style="italic">Level 11:</name>
            <text>Equals your Dexterity modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="2">
            <name style="italic">Level 21:</name>
            <text>Equals 2 + your Dexterity modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <name>Circle of Providence:</name>
            <text>Your allies ignore the difficult terrain created by this zone.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <name>Circle of Renewal:</name>
            <text>When an ally in the zone or adjacent to the zone spends a healing surge to regain hit points, he or she regains additional hit points equal to your Constitution modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="2">
            <name style="italic">Level 11:</name>
            <text>Equal to 3 + your Constitution modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="2">
            <name style="italic">Level 21:</name>
            <text>Equal to 6 + your Constitution modifier.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="true" indent="1">
            <name>Circle of the Swarm:</name>
            <text>Squares in the zone are lightly obscured to your enemies.</text>
         </section>
      </power>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Primal Attunement</name>
      <benefit>A Protector's innate connection to the power of primal spirits grants him or her a measure of control over the surrounding world. With his or her magic, a Protector manipulates the surroundings to his or her advantage.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain your choice of three of the following powers.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Air Spirit</title>
         <class>Druid</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <fluff>With a flick of your fingers, the air stirs before you to lift object with ease</fluff>
         <keyword>Conjuration</keyword> <keyword>Primal</keyword>
         <section><type>Ranged</type><range>5</range></section>
         <section indent="1"><name>Level 11:</name><type style="bold">Ranged</type><range>7</range></section>
         <section indent="1"><name>Level 21:</name><type style="bold">Ranged</type><range>10</range></section>
         <section shade="">
            <name>Effect:</name>
            <text>You conjure an air spirit in an unoccupied square within range. The spirit lasts until the end of your next turn or until you use this power again.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>When the spirit appears, it can pick up or manipulate an object weighing 20 pounds or less.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <name style="italic">Level 11:</name>
            <text>30 pounds or less.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <name style="italic">Level 21:</name>
            <text>40 pounds or less.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>While the spirit persists, you can take the following actions:</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <name>Minor Action:</name>
            <text>The spirit picks up or manipulates an object. The spirit can only hold one object at a time.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <name>Minor Action:</name>
            <text>You cause the spirit to shed bright light in a 4-square radius, and dim light for a further 4 squares. You can end this effect as a free action.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <name>Move Action:</name>
            <text>The spirit moves up to 5 squares in any direction, carrying the object it holds.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <name>Free Action:</name>
            <text>The spirit drops the object it is holding.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <name>Sustain Minor:</name>
            <text>The spirit persists until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
      </power>

      <power>
         <title>Call the Spirits</title>
         <class>Druid</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <fluff>Even the least of the primal spirits can prove useful in your everyday life</fluff>
         <keyword>Primal</keyword>
         <section auto="no-opportunity"/>
         <section><type>Ranged</type><range>5</range></section>
         <section shade="">
            <name>Effect:</name>
            <text>You produce one of the following effects in range:</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>Instantly light (or snuff out) a candle, torch, or campfire.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>Cause one candle, torch, or campfire to burn more brightly, increasing the radius of its illumination by 1.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>Open or close a door that is not latched, locked, or stuck.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>Create a light gust of wind that can blow small, unattended objects that weigh less than 1 pound to any other location in range.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>Create a brief, harmless sensory effect, such as a shower of sparks, a puff of wind, faint animal sounds, or a strong odor.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Special:</name>
            <text>Nathing you create with this power can deal damage, serve as a weapon or tool, or hinder another creature's actions. This power cannot duplicate the effet of any other power.</text>
         </section>
      </power>

      <subfeature>

      <power>
         <title>Senses of the Wild</title>
         <class>Druid</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <fluff>You close your eyes, so that you might sense the upheavals in the balance of nature that otherwise cannot be seen</fluff>
         <keyword>Primal</keyword>
         <section><type>Close</type><range>burst 5</range></section>
         <section shade="">
            <name>Effect:</name>
            <text>You produce one of the following effects:</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>You sense the presence of any disease or diseased plant or creature in the burst.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>You sense the presence or absence of a type of mundane plant or animal of your choice in the burst.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>You sense the presence of corpses in the burst.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="" indent="1">
            <bullet/>
            <text>You gain a +5 power bonus to Perception checks and Insight checks to detect poison or hozards that deal poison damage. This bonus lasts until the end of your current turn.</text>
         </section>
      </power>

      <power>
         <title>Verdant Touch</title>
         <class>Druid</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <fluff>You lay your hands on the flora that surrounds you, granting it a momentary semblance of life as it shifts and grows at your command</fluff>
         <keyword>Primal</keyword>
         <section><type>Close</type><range>burst 1</range></section>
         <section indent="1"><name>Level 11:</name><type style="bold">Close</type><range>burst 2</range></section>
         <section indent="1"><name>Level 21:</name><type style="bold">Close</type><range>burst 3</range></section>
         <section shade="">
            <name>Effect:</name>
            <text>You can turn difficult terrain in the burst into normal terrain until the end of your next turn, but only if the terrain is composed of grass, underbrush, vines, or similar growth. This cannot affect difficult terrain created by powers or similar abilities.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>Alternatively, you can use this power to cause plants in the burst to blossom with flowers and cause small plants or grass in the burst to begin growing in barren terrain.</text>
         </section>
      </power>

      <power>
         <title>Vine Rope</title>
         <class>Druid</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
         <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <fluff>With a twist of your hands, you draw a fast-growing vine from the ground before you, then watch as it waves itself into a resilient rope</fluff>
         <keyword>Primal</keyword>
         <section special=""/>
         <section shade="">
            <name>Effect:</name>
            <text>You draw a vine from the ground that is up to 50 feet in length. The vine functions as a silk rope and lasts until the end of the encounter or until you use this power again.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">
            <text>You can cause the vine to vanish as a minor action.</text>
         </section>
      </power>
   </subfeature>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Wild Shape</name>
      <benefit>A Druid has the ability to channel the primal energy of beasts into his or her physical form and transform into a beast.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>wild shape</i>]]> class power, which allows you to assume the form of a beast. This beast form is your size, resembles a natural beast or fey beast, and normally does not change your game statistics. Your equipment becomes part of your beast borm, but you drop anything you are holding, except immplements you can use.</benefit>
      <benefit>While you are in beast form, you can't use Weapon powers or Implement powers that lack the <key>Beast Form</key> keyword, although you can sustain such powers. You continue to gain the benefits of equipment you wear, except a shield. You can use the properties and powers of implements as well as magic items you wear, but not the properties or powers or weapons or the powers of wondrous items. Equipment that is part of your beast borm cannot be removed, and anything in a container that is part of your beast form is inaccessible.</benefit>
      <benefit>When you use your <![CDATA[<i>wild shape</i>]]> class power, you choose a specific form, usually a four-legged mammalian predator such as a bear, a boar, a panther, a wolf, or a wolverine. The form could also resemble a more exotic beast such as a rage drage or a crocodile, or a fantastic beast such as an owlbear or a bulette. Your beast form might even be an indistinct shape of shadowy fur and claws, an incarnation of the Primal Beast of which all earthly beasts are fractured images.</benefit>
      <benefit>Many druid powers have the <key>Beast Form</key> keyword, meaning they can be used only while you are in beast form.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Wild Shape</title>
         <class>Druid</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <frequency>At-Will</frequency> <action>Minor</action> <subaction/>
         <fluff>You assume an aspect of the Primal Beast or return to your humanoid form</fluff>
         <keyword>Polymorph</keyword> <keyword>Primal</keyword>
         <section personal=""/>
         <section shade=""><name>Effect:</name>You change from your humanoid form to beast form or vice versa. When you change from beast form back to your humanoid form, you can shift 1 square. You can remain in beast form until you change back to your humanoid form.</section>
         <section><name>Special:</name>You can use this power once per round.</section>
      </power>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Wilderness Knocks</name>
      <benefit>Druids are experts om outdoor survival. As primal adepts, they have learned several mundane tricks and techniques that aid in traveling through the wolds.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain two of the following abilities of your choice.</benefit>

      <subfeature>
			<name>Beast Empathy</name>
			<benefit>You gain a +2 bonus to Bluff, Diplomacy, and Intimidate checks against beasts.</benefit>
			<benefit>Also, you can communicate simple concepts and commands to such creatures, though they are under no compulsion to obey you.</benefit>
			<benefit>In addition, you can read a beast's body language and vocalization enough to understand basic messages from it with a successful Insight check (DC determined by the DM).</benefit>
		</subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Herb Lore</name>
         <benefit>If you take a short rest in an area that offers easy access to plants, you can prepare healing herbs as part of that rest. You and each ally can add +1 to his or her healing surge value when spending healing surges during that short rest. The additional hit points increase to 2 at 6th level, to 3 at 11th level, to 4 at 16th level, ro 5 at 21st level, and to 6 at 26st level.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
			<name>Mountain Guide</name>
			<benefit>You gain a +2 bonus to Athletics checks to climb and jump.</benefit>
			<benefit>If you are trained in Athletics, you can choose to not gain the bonus when climbing to instead reduce the DC of any climb check that covers the same route that you successfully climb. This reduction applies until the end of the encounter, and an ally must either see or hear you when you make your climb check to gain this benefit. The reduction to the DC equals 2, and increases to 3 starting at 11th level, and to 4 starting at 21st level. </benefit>
		</subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Watchful Rest</name>
         <benefit>When you take an extended rest, you can set up camp so that you do not take the -5 penalty to Perception checks for sleeping, and your allies only take a -2 penalty.</benefit>
         <benefit>If you are trained in Perception, your allies do not take the penalty to Perception checks for sleeping.</benefit>
         <benefit>You can choose this knack a second time. If you do, you and your allies gain a power bonus to Perception checks made during the extended rest. The power bonus equals 1 + one-half your Wisdom modifier.</benefit>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
			<name>Wilderness Tracker</name>
			<benefit>During a short rest, you can make a Perception check (DC determined by the DM) to inspect the area around you, up to 10 squares on a side.</benefit>
			<benefit>If your check succeeds, you determine the number and nature of the creatures that have moved through the area in the past 24 hours. You ascertain when and where they entered the area, as well as when and where they left.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
   </feature>

</class>
