<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>1st-level Elf Ancestry Feats</category>
      <title>Ancestral Linguistics</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>
      <prereq>at least 100 years old</prereq>

      <line>Over your extensive lifespan, you've studied many languages. During your daily preparations, you can recede into old memories to become fluent in one common language or one language you have access to. You know this language until you prepare again. Since this knowledge is temporary, you can't use it as a prerequisite for a permanent character option.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ancestral Longevity</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>
      <prereq>at least 100 years old</prereq>

      <line>You have accumulated a vast array of lived knowledge over the years. During your daily preparations, you can reflext upon your life experiences to gain the trained proficiency rank in one skill of your choice. This proficiency lasts until you prepare again. Since this proficiency is temporary, you can't use it as a prerequisite for a skill increase or a permanent character option.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Demonbane Warrior</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to damage with weapons and unarmed attacks against demons. If your attack would deal more than one die of damage (as is common at higher levels than 1st), the bonus is equal to the number of weapon dice or unarmed attack dice.</line>
      <line>If your actions force a demon to take damage from its sin vulnerability, increase that damage by 2.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elemental Wrath</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You are so attuned to the land that you can call forth a bolt of energy from your surroundings. When you gain this feat, select acid, cold, electricity, or fire. You can call to the land to cast the <![CDATA[<i>acid splash</i>]]> cantrip as an innate primal spell at will, except the spell has only verbal components and deals the type of damage you chose instead of acid damage; the spell gains the trait appropriate to its damage instead of the acid trait. A cantrip is heightened to a spell rank equal to half your level rounded up.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elven Aloofness</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>As much as you might care for them, you've come to terms with the ephemeral nature of non-elves, and it makes their threats feel less troublesome. If a non-elf rolls a failure on a check to Coerce you using Intimidation, it gets a critical failure instead (meaning it can't try to Coerce you again for 1 week). When a non-elf attempts to Demoralize you, you become temporarily immune for 1 day, instead of 10 minutes.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elven Lore</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You've studied in traditional elven arts, learning about arcane magic and the world around you. You gain the trained proficiency rank in Arcana and Nature. If you would automatically become trained in one of those skills (from your background or class, for example), you instead become tained in a skill of your choice.</line>
      <line>You also gain the Additional Lore general feat for Elf Lore.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elven Verve</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>While all elves are immune to the paralyzing touch of ghouls, you can shake off flesh-numbing magic of all kinds. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to saves against effect that would impose the immobilized, paralyzed, or slowed conditions. When you would be immobilized, paralyzed, or slowed for at least 2 rounds, reduce that duration by 1 round.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elven Weapon Familiarity</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You favor bows and other elegant weapons. You gain access to all uncommon weapons with the elf trait.</line>
      <line>You have familiarity with weapons with th elf trait plus longbows, composite longbows, rapiers, shortbows, and composite shortbows; for the purposes of proficiency, you treat any of these that are martial weapons as simple weapons, and any that are advanced weapons as martial weapons.</line>
      <line>At 5th level, whenever you get a critical hit with one of these weapons, you get its critical specialization effect.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Forlorn</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Watching your friends age and die fills you with moroseness that protects you agianst harmful emotions. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to saving throws against emotion effects. If you roll a success on a saving throw against an emotion effect, you get a critical success instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Know Your Own</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You've spent countless hours studying the history of the elves on your world and beyond and are a studied expert in your people's ways. If you critically fail a check to Recall Knowledge about elves, elven society, or elven history, you get a failure instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Nimble Elf</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Your muscles are tightly toned. Your Speed increases by 5 feet.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Otherworldly Magic</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Your elven magic manifests as a simple arcane spell, even if you aren't formally trained in magic. Choose one cantrip from the arcane spell list. You can cast this cantrip as an arcane innate spell at will. A cantrip is heighened to a spell level equal to half your level rounded up. Since this magic is innate, you can replace any material component with a somatic component.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Share Thoughts</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>
      <prereq>You must come from a line of elves where this ability is common</prereq>

      <line>You have an uncanny knack of communicating with other elves without speaking, though this habit is often uncomfortable to observers. You can cast <![CDATA[<i>mindlink</i>]]> as an innate occult spell once per day, but you can target only other elves or half-elves.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Unwavering Mien</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Your mystic control and meditations allow you to resist external influences upon your consciousness. Whenever you are affected by a mental effect that lasts at least 2 rounds, you can redue the duration by 1 round.</line>
      <line>You still require natural sleep, but you treat your saving throws against effects that would cause you to fall asleep as one degree of success better. This protects only against sleep effects, not against other forms of falling unconscious.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Wildborn Magic</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You have learned to access the old magic of wild places. Choose one cantrip from the primal spell list. You can cast this cantrip as an innate primal spell at will. A cantrip is heighened to a spell level equal to half your level rounded up. Since this magic is innate, you can replace any material component with a somatic component.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Woodcraft</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You have an innate familiarity with forested areas. When in a forest or jungle environment, if you roll a critical failure on a Survival check to Sense Direction, Subsist, or Cover Tracks, you get a failure instead, and if you roll a success, you get a critical success instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <category>5th-level Elf Ancestry Feats</category>
      <title>Ageless Patience</title>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You work at a pace born from longevity that enhances your thoroughness. You can voluntarily spend twice as much time as normal on a Perception check or skill check to gain a +2 circumstance bonus to that check. You also don't treat a natural 1 as worse than usual on these checks; you get a critical failure only if your result is 10 lower than the DC. For example, you could get these benefits if you spent 2 actions to Seek, which normally takes 1 action.</line>
      <line>You can get these benefits during exploration by taking twice as long exploring as normal, or in downtime by spending twice as much downtime. The GM might determine a situation doesn't grant you a benefit if a delay would be directly counterproductive to your success, such as a tense negotiation with an impatient creature.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ancestral Suspicion</title>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Long-lived elves have seen civilizations rise and fall, often at the hands of outside forces. As a result, they have developed a wariness of others who might seek to influence or control them. You've been trained to resist such manipulation, gaining a +2 circumstance bonus to saving throws against effects that would make you controlled, such as <![CDATA[<i>dominate</i>]]>, and to Perception checks to Sense Motive when trying to determine if a creature is under the influence of such an effect.</line>
      <line>When you roll a success on a saving throw against such an effect, you get a critical success instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Defiance Unto Death</title>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Elf</trait>
      <access>You come from a community agonized by alghollthus or their pawns</access>

      <line>You loathe the algholtthus and their mind magic, and you've been trained to be willing to die rather than give into mental manipulation. If you would start your turn confused, controlled, or fleeing due to a failed Will save, you can attempt a Will save against the same DC; on a success, you become paralyzed until the start of your next turn, rather than act against your will.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elven Instincts</title>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Your senses let you react rapidly. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to Perception checks made as initiative rolls.</line>
      <line>Additionally, if your initiative roll result is tied with that of an opponent, you go first, regardless of whether you rolled Peception or not.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Forest Stealth</title>
      <trait>Elf</trait>
      <prereq>expert in Stealth</prereq>
      <requirements>You are in a forest or jungle environment near an environmental feature that would allow you to Take Cover.</requirements>

      <line>You are skilled at quickly hiding behind bits of underbrush or foliage. You Take Cover and then use that cover to Hide.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Martial Experience</title>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>You've crossed blades with a wide variety of foes wielding a wide variety of weapons, and you've learned the basics of fighting with nearly of them. When wielding a weapon you aren't proficient with, treat your level as your proficiency bonus.</line>
      <line>At 11th level, you become trained in all weapons.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Wildborn Adept</title>
      <trait>Elf</trait>
      <prereq>Wildborn Magic feat</prereq>

      <line>The whispers of the jungle grant you more diverse access to simple primal magic. You can cast <![CDATA[<i>dancing lights</i>, <i>disrupt undead</i>, and <i>tanglefoot</i>]]> as innate primal spells at will. If you chose one of those spells with Wildborn Magic, you can select a new spell for Wildborn Magic.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
