<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>1st-level Human Ancenstry Feats</category>
      <title>Adapted Cantrip</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>
      <prereq>spellcasting class feature</prereq>

      <line>Through study of multiple magical traditions, you've altered a spell to suit your spellcasting style. Choose one cantrip from a magical tradition other than your own.</line>
      <line>If you prepare spells, you can choose this spell when you prepare your cantrips, in addition to your other options. If you have a spell repertoire, replace one of your cantrips known with the chosen spell. You can cast this cantrip as a spell of your class's tradition.</line>
      <line>If you swap or retrain this cantrip later, you can choose its replacement from the same alternate tradition or a different one.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cooperative Nature</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>The short human life span lends perspective and has taught you from a young age to set aside differences and work with others to achieve greatness. You gain a +4 circumstance bonus on checks to Aid.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Courteous Comeback</title> <action>F</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Fortune</trait> <trait>Human</trait>
      <trigger>You critically fail a Diplomacy check</trigger>
      <requirements>You're in a settlement or community, and you haven't used Courteous Comeback in this settlement or community within the past month.</requirements>

      <line>You grew up in a proud settlement, where even insults have a certain poetic wit. Reroll the triggering Diplomacy check, using the second result.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Devil's Advocate</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from community that commonly deals with devils</access>

      <line>You know more about the habits of devils than is entirely safe. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to Perception checks against devils and saving throws against their abilities.</line>
      <line>In addition, whenever you meet a devil in a social situation, you can immediately attempt a Diplomacy check to Make an Impression on that creature rather than needing to converse for 1 minute, though you take a -5 penalty to the check. If you fail, you can engage in 1 minute of conversation and attempt a new check at the end of that time rather than accepting the failure or critical failure result.</line>
      <special>If you have the Glad-Hand skill feat, you don't take the -5 penalty to your immediate Diplomacy check if the target is a devil.</special>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dragon Spit</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/><trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You have dragon blood</access>

      <line>Many claim to have dragon blood in your veins, and in your case, this is true — you can spit energy, and you might have an especially visible sign of your draconic heritage. Choose one of the following cantrips: <![CDATA[<i>acid splash</i>, <i>electric arc</i>, <i>produce flame</i>, or <i>ray of frost</i>]]>.</line>
      <line>You can cast the chosen spell as an innate arcane spell at will, and when you cast it, the spell's energy emerges from your mouth. You use your Charisma as your spellcasting ability for this spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fetish Carver</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <prereq>You have a spellcasting class feature with the divine or primal tradition</prereq>
      <access>You come from a community that creates whalebone fetishes</access>

      <line>You know the truth behind old stories that tell of sending a fetish of bone and sinew to seek vengeance. These old magics allow you to conjure constructs with ease.</line>
      <line>Add the <![CDATA[<i>summon construct</i>]]> spell to your spell list. The constructs you summon have a distinct ivory scrimshaw appearance, and if you include a drop of blood, lock of hair, or other portion of a creature's body as part of the spell's material component, the summoned construct gains a +4 status bonus to Perception checks to sense or locate that creature.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>General Training</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>Your adaptability manifests in your mastery of a range of useful abilities. You gain a 1st-level general feat. You must meet the feat's prerequisites, but if you select this feat during character creation, you can select the feat later in the process in order to determine which prerequisites you meet.</line>
      <special>You can select this feat multiple times, choosing a different 1st-level general feat each time.</special>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gloomseer</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from a place where supernatural darkness is prevalent</access>

      <line>Gloom holds few terrors for you, and the pall of darkness over your home has made you comfortable in dim light. You gain low-light vision.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Haughty Obstinacy</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>Your powerful ego makes it harder for others to order you around. If you roll a success on a saving throw against a mental effect that attempts to directly control your actions, you critically succeed instead.</line>
      <line>If a creature rolls a failure on a check to Coerce you using Intimidatioon, it gets a critical failure instead (meaning it can't try to Coerce you again for 1 week).</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Keep Up Appearances</title> <action>R</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from a community where showing emotions is forbidden</access>
      <trigger>You are affected by an emotion effect</trigger>

      <line>Your pride means you never show weakness. Roll a Deception check and compare the result to any observing creatures' Perception DCs. On a success, that creature believes you were unaffected by the triggering emotion effect. A creature tricked in this manner can't benefit from the emotion effect and can't use abilities that require you to be under this emotion effect; for example, if you successfully use this ability to trick a will-o'-wisp into believing you aren't under a fear effect, it can't use its Feed on Fear ability on you.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Know Oneself</title> <action>R</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Fortune</trait> <trait>Human</trait>
      <frequency>once per hour</frequency>
      <access>You come from a community that holds self-knowledge in high value</access>
      <trigger>You roll a critical failure on a saving throw against an emotion effect</trigger>

      <line>You center yourself and call to mind the monastic ideals of mindfulness and self-knowledge. You fail the triggering save instead of critically failing.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Natural Ambition</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>You were raised to be ambitious and always reach for the stars, leading you to progress quickly in your chosen field. You gain a 1st-level class feat for your class. You must meet the prerequisites, but you can select the feat later in the character creation process in order to determine which prerequisites you meet.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Natural Skill</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>Your ingenuity allows you to learn a wide variety of skills. You gain the trained proficiency rank in two skills of your choice.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Quah Bond</title>>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from a community that reveres the the quah spirits</access>

      <line>You grup among a people where the spirits watched over you and offer you guidance. You gain the trained proficiency rank in the skill listed for your quah (or another skill of your choice, if you're already trained in that skill). You gain the Assurance skill feat in that skill, as the spirits' help guides your actions.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Lyrune-Quah — Religion</entry>
         <entry>Shadde-Quah — Athletics</entry>
         <entry>Shriikirri-Quah — Nature</entry>
         <entry>Shundar-Quah — Diplomacy</entry>
         <entry>Sklar-Quah — Intimidation</entry>
         <entry>Skoan-Quah — Medicine</entry>
         <entry>Tamiir-Quah — Acrobatics</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Saoc Astrology</title> <action>1</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Human</trait>
      <frequency>3 times per day</frequency>
      <access>You come from a community that consults the stars</access>
      <requirements>You must spend 10 minutes just after your daily preparations examining the sky or consulting a star chart or you can't use this action that day</requirements>

      <line>The ancient Saoc Brethren were the masters of astrology, and while your knowledge may be put a pale shadow of their wisdom, it still comes in handy. You recall the stars' predictions about your current situation. If your next action requires you to attempt one or more skill checks, roll a 1d8.</line>
      <line>On a result of 6, 7, or 8, you gain a +2 circumstance bonus to the first such check you attempt. On a 3, 4, or 5, you gain a +1 circumstance bonus. On a 2, you gain nothing. On a 1, you take a -1 circumstance penalty to the skill check.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Unconventional Weaponry</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>You've familiarized yourself with a particular weapon, potentially from another ancestry or culture. Choose an uncommon simple or martial weapon with a trait corresponding to an ancestry (such as the dwarf, goblin, or orc trait) or that is common in another culture (such as the aldori dueling sword). You gain access to that weapon, and for the purpose of proficiency, you treat it as a simple weapon.</line>
      <line>If you are trained in all martial weapons, you can instead choose an uncommon advanced weapon that has an acnestry trait or is common in another culture. You gain access to that weapon and have familiarity with that weapon. For the purpose of proficiency, you treat it as a martial weapon.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Viking Shieldbearer</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from a viking community</access>

      <line>You trained with shields and weapons as soon as you were old enough to hold them, eager to win honor and glory for yourself. You gain the Shield Block feat, and are trained in your choice of the battle axe or longsword.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Witch Warden</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from a community agonized by witches or hags</access>

      <line>You and your family have fough long and hard against witches or hags, perhaps even both, and you've learned to be wary of their curses and the otherworldly powers their patrons grant. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to saving throws against curses, and to saving throws against spells cast by a witch or hag. If you roll a success on a saving throw against a curse or a spell cast by a witch or hag, you get a critical success instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <category>5th-level Human Ancestry Feats</category>
      <title>Adaptive Adept</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>
      <prereq>Adapted Cantrip feat; can cast 3rd-level spells</prereq>

      <line>You've continued adapting your magic to blend your class's tradition with your adapted tradition. Choose a cantrip of 1st-rank spell from the same magical tradition as your cantrip from Adapted Cantrip. You gain that spell, adding it to your spell options just like the cantrip from Adapted Cantrip.</line>
      <line>If you choose a 1st-rank spell, you don't gain access to the heightened versions of that spell, meaning you can't prepare them if you prepare spells and you can't select the spell as a signature spell if you have a spell repertoire.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Clever Improviser</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>You've learned how to handle situations when you're out of your depth. You gain the Untrained Improvisation general feat. In addition, you can attempt skill actions that normally require you to be trained, even if you are untrained.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Darkseer</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>5</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from a place where supernatural darkness is prevalent</access>
      <prereq>Gloomseer feat</prereq>

      <line>Zon-Kuthon smiles upon you -even if you curse his name- granting you pitch-black eyes that allow you to see in shadows an darkness. You gain darkvision.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sense Allies</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Human</trait>

      <line>Like many humans raised in a close-knit community, you have always been strongly attuned to the presence of others. Willing allies that you are aware of within 60 feet that would otherwise be undetected by you are instead hidden from you. The flat check DC for you to target willing allies within 60 feet that are hidden from you is 5 instead of 11.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Wavetouched Paragon</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>5</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Human</trait>
      <access>You come from a community of waterfaring people</access>

      <line>You have been blessed by the sea, granting you the ability to swim like a fish. You gain a 15-foot swim Speed.</line>
      <special>If your background grants you the Underwater Madauder skill feat, you can take this feat at 1st level instead of 5th.</special>
   </rule>

</catalog>
