<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Low-Light Vision</title>

      <line>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the concealed condition due to dim light.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Arctic Elf</title>

      <line>You dwell deep in the frozen north and have gained incredible resilience against cold environments, granting you cold resistance equal to half your level (minimum 1).</line>
      <line>You treat environmental cold effects as if they were one step less extreme (incredible cold becomes extreme cold, extreme cold becomes severe, and so on).</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Nimble ELf</title>
      <type>Feat</type>
      <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Your muscles are tightly toned. Your Speed increases by 5 feet.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elven Instincts</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Your senses let you react rapidly. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to Perception checks made as initiative rolls.</line>
      <line>Additionally, if your initiative roll result is tied with that of an opponent, you go first, regardless of whether you rolled Peception or not.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Diehard</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>It takes more to kill you than most. You die from the dying condition at dying 5, rather than dying 4.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cat Fall</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Acrobatics</prereq>

      <line>Your catlike aerial acrobatics allow you to cushion your falls. Treat falls as 10 feet shorter.</line>
      <line>If you're an expert in Acrobatics, treat falls as 25 feet shorter. If you're a master in Acrobatics, treat them as 50 feet shorter. If you're legendary in Acrobatics, you always land on your feet and don't take damage, regardless of the distance of the fall.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Falling</title>

      <line>When you fall more than 5 feet, you take bludgeoning damage equal to half the distance you fell when you land. Treat falls longer than 1,500 feet as though they were 1,500 feet (750 damage). If you take any damage from a fall, you land prone. You fall about 500 feet in the first round of falling and about 1,500 feet each round thereafter.</line>
      <line>You can Grab an Edge as a reaction to reduce the damage from some falls. In addition, if you fall into water, snow, or another relatively soft substance, you can treat the fall as though it were 20 feet shorter, or 30 feet shorter if you intentionally dove in. The effective reduction can't be greater than the depth (so when falling into 10-foot-deep water, you treat the fall as 10 feet shorter).</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Grab an Edge</title>
      <action>R</action>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <trigger>You fall from  or past an edge or handhold</trigger>
      <requirements>You hands are not tied behind your back or otherwise restrained</requirements>

      <line>When you fall off or past an edge or other handhold, you can try to grab it, potentially stopping your fall. You must succeed at a Reflex save, usually at the Climb DC. If you grab the edge or handhold, you can them Climb up using Athletics.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You grab the edge or handhold, whether or not you have a hand free, typically by using a suitable held item to catch yourself (catching a battle axe on a ledge, for example). You still take damage from the distance fallen so far, but you treat the fall as though it were 30 feet shorter.</critsuccess>
         <success>If you have at least one hand free, you grab the edge or handhold, stopping your fall. You still take damage from the distance fallen so far, but you treat the fall as though it were 20 feet shorter. If you have no hands free, you continue to fall as if you had failed the check.</success>
         <critfail>You continue to fall, and if you've fallen 20 feet or more before you use this reaction, you take 10 bludgeoning damage from the impact for every 20 feet fallen.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Leap</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <trait>Move</trait>

      <line>You take a careful, short jump. You can Leap up to 10 feet horizontally if your Speed is at least 15 feet, or up to 15 feet horizontally if your Speed is at least 30 feet. You land in the space when your Leap ends (meaning you can typically clear a 5-foot gap, or a 10-foot gap if your Speed is 30 feet or more).</line>
      <line>If you Leap vertically, you can move up to 3 feet vertically and 5 feet horizontally onto an elevated surface.</line>
      <line>Jumping a greater distance requires using the Athletics skill, either the High Jump or Long Jump action.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>High Jump</title>
      <action>2</action>
      <type>Athletics</type>

      <line>You Stride, then make a vertical Leap and attempt a DC 30 Athletics check to increase the height of your jump. If you didn't Stride at least 10 feet, you atomatically fail your check. This DC might be increased or decreased due to the situation, or as determined by the GM.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You Leap up to 8 feet vertically and 10 feet horizontally.</critsuccess>
         <success>You Leap up to 5 feet vertically and 5 feet horizontally.</success>
         <fail>You Leap normally.</fail>
         <critfail>You fall prone in your space.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Long Jump</title>
      <action>2</action>
      <type>Athletics</type>

      <line>You Stride, then attempt a DC 15 Athletics check to make a long jump in the direction were Striding. If you didn't Stride at least 10 feet, you automatically fail your check. The GM might increase or decrease this DC depending on the situation.</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>You Leap up to a distance equal to your check result rounded down to the nearest 5 feet. You can't jump further than your land Speed.</success>
         <fail>You make a normal horizontal Leap.</fail>
         <critfail>You make a normal horizontal Leap, then fall and land prone.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Wall Jump</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>7</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>master in Athletics</prereq>

      <line>You can use your momentum from a jump to proper yourself off a wall. If you're adjacent to a wall at the end of jump (whether High Jump, Long Jump, or Leap), you don't fall as long as your next action is another jump. Your previous jump gives you moment, letting you use High Jump or Long Jump as a single action, but you don't get to Stride as part of the activity.</line>
      <line>You can use Wall Jump only once in a turn, unless you're legendary in Athletics, in which case you can use it as many times as you can use consecutive jump actions in that turn.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Impressive Performance</title>
      <type>Feat</type>
      <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Performance</prereq>

      <line>Your performances inspire admiration and win you fans. You can Make an Impression using Performance instead of Diplomacy.</line>
      <line>If you spend at least 10 minutes performing in front of an audience, you can Make an Impression targeting up to 10 members of the audience who were there for the whole performance, without taking the normal penalty. The number of targets increases to 20 for a 1-hour performance and 50 for a 2-hour performance.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Make an Impression</title>
      <type>Diplomacy</type>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Linguistic</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>

      <line>With at least 1 minute of conversation, during which you engage in charismatic overtures, flatter, and other acts of goodwill, you seek to make a good impression on someone to make them temporarily agreeable. At the end of the conversation, attempt a Diplomacy check against the Will DC of one target. You can instead choose up to five targets if you take a -2 penalty. The GM might add other bonuses or penalties based on the situation.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target's attitude toward you improves by two steps (such as from indifferent to helpful).</critsuccess>
         <success>The target's attitude toward you improves by one step (such as from indifferent to friendly).</success>
         <critfail>The target's attitude toward you decreases by one step (such as from indifferent to unfriendly).</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>Any impression you make lasts for only the current social interaction unless the GM decides otherwise.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Demoralize</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Intimidation</type>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>

      <line>With a sudden shout, a well-timed taunt, or a cutting putdown, you can shake an enemy's resolve.</line>
      <line>Choose a creature within 30 feet of you who you're aware of. Attempt an Intimidation check against that target's Will DC. If the target does not understand the language you are speaking, or you're not speaking a language, you take a -4 circumstance penalty to the check. Regardless of your result, the target is temporarily immune to your attempts to Demoralize it for 10 minutes.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target becomes frightened 2.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target becomes frightened 1.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Coerce</title>
      <type>Intimidation</type>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Linguistic</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>

      <line>With threats veiled or overt, you attempt to bully a creature into doing what you want. You must spend at least 1 minute of conversation with a creature you can see and that can either see or sense you. At the end of the conversation, attempt an Intimidation check against the target's Will DC, modified by circumstances the GM determines.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target gives you the information you seek or agrees to follow your directives so long as they aren't likely to harm the target in any way. The target continues to comply for an amount of time determined by the GM but not exceeding 1 day, at which point the target becomes unfriendly (if they weren't already unfriendly or hostile). However, the target is too scared of you to retaliate — at least in the short term.</critsuccess>
         <success>As critical success, but once the target becomes unfriendly, they might decide to act against you — for example, by reporting you to the authorities or assisting your enemies.</success>
         <fail>The target doesn't do what you say, and if they were not already unfriendly or hostile, they become unfriendly.</fail>
         <critfail>The target refuses to comply, becomes hostile if they weren't already, and can't be Coerced by you for at least 1 week.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>With greater proficiency, you can strong-arm people even when you don't have them isolated. You can compare your Intimidate check result against the Will DCs of two creatures without penalty if you're an expert, five creatures if you're a master, and 10 if you're legendary. It is possible to get a different degree of success for each target.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Instinct</title>
      <line>Your rage wells up from a dominant instinct -one you learned from a tradition or that comes naturally to you.</line>
      <line name="Dragon Instinct">You summon the fury of a mighty dragon and manifest incredible abilities. Perhaps your culture reveres draconic majesty, or you gained insighty be drinking or bathing in dragon's blood or watching a marauding wyrm burn your village.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Furious Footfalls</title>
      <line>The urge to fight drives you ever forward. You gain a +5-foot status bonus to your Speed. This bonus increases to +10 feet while you're raging.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Rage</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <trait>Barbarian</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
      <requirement>You aren't fatigued or raging.</requirement>

      <line>You tap into your inner fury and begin raging. You gain a number of temporary Hit Points equal to your level plus your Constitution modifier. While you are raging:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>You deal 2 additional damage with melee Strikes. This additional damage is halved if your weapon or unarmed attack is agile.</entry>
         <entry>You can't use actions with the <u>concentrate</u> trait unless they also have the <u>rage</u> trait. You can Seek while raging.</entry>
      </line>
      <line>Rage lasts for 1 minute, until you fall unconscious, or until the encounter ends, whichever comes first. You can't voluntarily stop raging.</line>
      <line>When you stop raging, you lose any remaining temporary Hit Points from Rage, and you can't gain remporary Hit Points from using Rage again for 1 minute.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Draconic Rage (White Dragon)</title>

      <line>When you you Rage, you can increase the additional damage from 2 to 4 and change it to cold damage instead of the damage type of your weapon or unarmed attack. If you do this, your Rage action gains the <u>arcane</u> and <u>cold</u> traits.</line>
      <line name="Specialization Ability">When you use Draconic Rage, you increase the additional damage from Rage to 8. If you have greater weapon specialization, instead increase the damge from Rage to 16.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Quick-Tempered</title> <action>R</action>
      <trait>Barbarian</trait>
      <trigger>You roll initiative</trigger>
      <requirements>You are not encumbered or wearing heavy armor</requirements>

      <line>So long as you are able to move freely, your fury is instinctive and instantaneous. You Rage.</line>
   </rule>

    <rule>
      <title>Acute Vision</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Barbarian</trait>

      <line>When you are raging, your visual senses improve, granting you darkvision.</line>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <title>Brutality</title>
      <line>Your fury makes your weapons lethal. While raging, you gain access to the critical specialization effects for melee weapons and unarmed attacks.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weapon Specialization, Axe</title>
      <line>Choose one creature adjacent to the initial target and within reach. If its AC is lower than your attack roll result for the critical hit, you deal damage to that creature equal to the result of the weapon damage die you rolled (including extra dice for the <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune, if any). This amount isn't doubled, and no bonus or other additional dice apply to this damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weapon Specialization, Brawling</title>
      <line>The target must succeed at a Fortitude save against your class DC or be slowed 1 until the end of your next turn.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weapon Specialization, Hammer</title>
      <line>The target is knocked prone unless they succeed at a Fortitude save against your class DC.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weapon Specialization, Spear</title>
      <line>The weapon pierces the target, weakening its attacks. The target is clumsy 1 until the start of your next turn.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Juggernaut</title>
      <line>Your body is accustomed to physical hardship and resistant to ailments. When you roll a success on a Fortitude save, you get a critical success instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Slippery Prey</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Acrobatics or Athletics</prereq>

      <line>You're able to escape bonds more easily than others. When you attempt to Escape using Acrobatics or Athletics, you reduce the multiple attack penalty for repeated attempts to -4 and -8 if you're trained in the skill. The penalty becomes -3 and -6 if you're a master in the appropriate skill.</line>
      <line>If you're legendary in the skill, you don't take penalties for multiple Escape attempts in the same turn. Your attempts still have the <u>attack</u> trait and incur a multiple attack penalty for other actions.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Escape</title>
      <trait>Attack</trait>

      <line>You attempt to escape from being grabbed, immobilized, or restrained. Choose one creature, object, spell effect, hazard, or other impediment imposing any of those conditions on you. Attempt a check using your unarmed attack modifier against the DC of the effect. This is typically the Athletics DC of a creature grabbing you, the Thievery DC of a creature who tied you up, the spell DC of a spell effect, or the listed Escape DC of an object, hazard, or other impediment. You can attempt an Acrobatics or Athletics check instead of using your attack modifier if you choose.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You get free and remove the grabbed, immobilized, or restrained condition imposed by your chosen target. You can then Stride up to 5 feet.</critsuccess>
         <success>You get free and remove the grabbed, immobilized, or restrained conditions imposed by your chosen target.</success>
         <critfail>You don't get free, and you can't attempt to Escape again until your next turn.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

    <rule>
      <title>Titan Wrestler</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Athletics</prereq>

      <line>You can attempt to Disarm, Grapple, Reposition, Shove, or Trip creatures up to two sizes larger than you, or up to three sizes larger than you if you're legendary in Athletics.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Disarm</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Athletics</type>
      <trait>Attack</trait>
      <requirement>You have at least one free hand. Your target isn't more than one size larger than you.</requirement>

      <line>You try to knock something out of a creature's grasp. Attempt an Athletics check against the target's Reflex DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You knock the item out of the target's grasp. It falls to the ground in the target's space.</critsuccess>
         <success>You weaken your target's grasp on the item. Further attempts to Disarm the target of that item gain a +2 circumstance bonus, and the target takes a -2 circumstance penalty to attacks with the item or other checks requiring a firm graps on the item. The creature can end the effect by Interacting to change its grip on the item; otherwise, it lasts as long as the creature holds the item.</success>
         <critfail>You lose your balance, and become flat-footed until the start of your next turn.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Grapple</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Athletics</type>
      <trait>Attack</trait>
      <requirement>You have at least one free hand or have your target grappled or restrained. Your target isn't more than one size larger than you.</requirement>

      <line>You attempt to grab a creature or object with your free hand. Attempt an Athletics check against the target's Fortitude DC. You can Grapple a target you already have grabbed or restrained without having a hand free.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>Your target is restrained until the end of your next turn unless you move or your target Escapes.</critsuccess>
         <success>Your target is grabbed until the end of your next turn unless you move or your target Escapes.</success>
         <fail>You fail to grab your target. If you already had the target grabbed or restrained using a Grapple, those conditions on that creature or object end.</fail>
         <critfail>If you already had the target grabbed or restrained, it breaks free. Your target can either grab you, as if it succeed at using the Grapple action against you, or force you to fall and land prone.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Reposition</title> <action>1</action>
      <type>Athletics</type>
      <trait>Attack</trait>
      <requirement>You have at least one free hand, or you're grabbing or restraining the target; The target can't be more than one size larger than you</requirement>

      <line>You muscle a creature or object around. Attempt an Athletics check against the target's Fortitude DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You move the creature up to 10 feet.</critsuccess>
         <success>You move the target up to 5 feet.</success>
         <critfail>The target can move you up to 5 feet as though it successfully Repositioned you.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>The target must remain within your reach during this movement, and you can't move it through or into obstacles.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Trip</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Athletics</type>
      <trait>Attack</trait>
      <requirement>You have at least one free hand. Your target isn't more than one size larger than you.</requirement>

      <line>You try to knock a creature to the ground. Attempt an Athletics check against the target's Reflex DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target falls and lands prone and takes 1d6 bludgeoning damage. The damage increases to 2d6 if you are a master in Athletics, and to 3d6 if you're legendary.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target falls and lands prone.</success>
         <critfail>You lose your balance, and fall prone.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shove</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Athletics</type>
      <trait>Attack</trait>
      <requirement>You have at least one free hand. Your target isn't more than one size larger than you.</requirement>

      <line>You push a creature away from you. Attempt an Athletics check against your target's Fortitude DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You push the target up to 10 feet away from you. You can Stride after it, but you must move the same distance and in the same direction.</critsuccess>
         <success>You push the target back 5 feet. You can Stride after it, but you must move the same distance and in the same direction.</success>
         <critfail>You lose your balance, and fall prone.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sudden Charge</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <action>2</action>
      <trait>Barbarian</trait> <trait>Flourish</trait>

      <line>With a quick sprint, you dash up to your foe and swing. Stride twice. If you end your movement within melee reach of at least one enemy, you can make a melee Strike against that enemy.</line>
      <line>You can use Sudden Charge while Burrowing, Climbing, Flying, or Swimming instead of Striding if you have the corresponding movement type.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Swipe</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>4</level>
      <action>2</action>
      <trait>Barbarian</trait> <trait>Flourish</trait>

      <line>You make a wide, arcing swing. Make single melee Strike and compare the attack roll result to the ACs of up to two foes, each of whom must be within your melee reach and adjacent to the other. Roll damage only once and apply it to each creature you hit. A Swipe counts as two attacks for your multiple attack penalty.</line>
      <line>If you're using a weapon with the <u>sweep</u> trait, its modifier applies to all your Swipe attacks.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dragon's Rage Breath</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>6</level>
      <trait>Arcane</trait> <trait>Barbarian</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Rage</trait>
      <frequency>once per 10 minutes</frequency>

      <line>You breathe deeply and exhale powerful energy in a 30-foot cone, dealing 1d6 damage per level to each creature in the area with a basic Reflex save against your class DC.</line>
      <line name="Draconic Rage (White Dragon)">Your breath deals cold damage, and this action has the <u>arcane</u> trait.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Reactive Strike</title> <action>R</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>6</level>
      <trait>Barbarian</trait>
      <trigger>A creature within your reach uses a <u>manipulate</u> action or a <u>move</u> action, makes a ranged attack, or leaves a square during a move action it's using</trigger>

      <line>You lash out at a foe that leaves an opening. Make a melee Strike against the triggering creature. If your attack is a critical hit and the trigger was a <u>manipulate</u> action, you disrupt that action.</line>
      <line>This Strike doesn't count toward your multiple attack penalty, and your multiple attack penalty doesn't apply to this Strike.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
