<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Potion</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1+</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Potion</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>healing potion</i>]]> is a vial of ruby-red liquid that imparts a tingling sensation as the drinker's wounds heal rapidly. When you drink a <![CDATA[<i>healing potion</i>]]>, you regain the listed number of Hit Points.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Minor</type> <level>1</level>
         <price>4 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 1d8 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Lesser</type> <level>3</level>
         <price>12 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 2d8+5 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Moderate</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>50 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 3d8+10 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Greataxe</title>
      <trait>Sweep</trait>
      <price>2 gp</price> <damage>1d12 S</damage>
      <hands>2</hands> <bulk>2</bulk>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Martial</weapcat> <weapgroup>Axe</weapgroup>

      <line>This large axe is too heavy to wield with one hand. Many greataxes incorporate two blades, and they are often "bearded", having a hook at the bottom to increase the strength of their chopping power.</line>

      <traittext><name>Sweep</name>This weapon makes wide sweeping or spinning attacks, maknig it easier to attack multiple enemies. When you attack with this weapon, you gain a +1 circumstance bonus to your attack roll if you already attempted to attack a different target this turn using this weapon.</traittext>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">+1 Potency</rune> <level>2</level>
         <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>35 gp</price>

         <line>Magical enhancements make this weapon strike true. Attack rolls with this weapon gain a +1 item bonus, and the weapon can be etched with one property rune.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">Striking</rune> <level>4</level>
         <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>65 gp</price>

         <line>A <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune stores destructive magic in the weapon, increasing the weapon damage dice it deals to two instead of one.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">Fearsome</rune> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>160 gp</price>

         <line>When you critically hit with this weapon, the target becomes frightened 1.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hide Armor</title>
      <price>2 gp</price>
      <ac>03</ac> <dexcap>+2</dexcap> <checkpenalty>-2</checkpenalty> <spdpenalty>-5 ft.</spdpenalty>
      <strreq>14</strreq> <bulk>2</bulk>
      <armorcat>Medium</armorcat> <armorgroup>Leather</armorgroup>

      <line>A mix of furs, sturdy hide, and sometimes molded boiled leather, this armor provides protection due to its layers of leather, though its bulkiness slows the wearer down and decreases mobility.</line>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">+1 potency</rune> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>160 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto the armor</usage>

         <line>Magic wards deflect attacks. Increase the armor's item bonus to AC by 1. The armor can be etched with a property rune.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Trident</title>
      <trait>Thrown 20 ft.</trait>
      <price>1 gp</price> <damage>1d8 P</damage>
      <hands>1</hands> <bulk>1</bulk>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Martial</weapcat> <weapgroup>Spear</weapgroup>

      <line>This three-pronged, spear-like weapon typically has a 4-foot shaft. Like a spear, it can be wielded with one hand and thrown.</line>

      <traittext><name>Thrown 20 ft.</name>You can throw this weapon as a ranged attack, and it is a ranged weapon when thrown. A thrown weapon adds your Strength modifier to damage, just like a melee weapon does.</traittext>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dagger</title>
      <trait>Agile</trait> <trait>Finesse</trait> <trait>Thrown 10 ft.</trait> <trait>Versatile S</trait>
      <price>2 sp</price> <damage>1d4 P</damage>
      <hands>1</hands> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Simple</weapcat> <weapgroup>Knife</weapgroup>

      <line>This small, bladed weapon is held in one hand and used to stab a creature in close combat. It can also be thrown.</line>

      <traittext><name>Agile</name>The multiple attack penalty you take with this weapon on the second attack is -4 instead of -5, and -8 instead of -10 on the third and subsequent attacks in the turn.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Finesse</name>You can use your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier on attack rolls using this weapon. You still use your Strength modifier when calculating damage.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Thrown 10 ft.</name>You can throw this weapon as a ranged attack, and it is a ranged weapon when thrown. A thrown weapon adds your Strength modifier to damage, just like a melee weapon does.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Versatile S</name>A versatile weapon can be used to deal a different type of damage than that listed in the Damage entry. You choose the damage type each time you make an attack.</traittext>

      <variant>
         <material>Low-grade silver</material> <level>2</level>
         <price>40 gp</price>

         <line>This weapon has been plated in silver, making it more effective against some creatures.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Flask of Fellowship</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>25 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This is a metal drinking flask, 4 inches in diameter and 10 inches tall. Its screw top is covered by four simple metal cups that nest together.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name>
         <type>Make an Impression</type>
         <part><name>Effect</name>If you share drinks from a flask of fellowship as part of your Make an Impression action, the drink that pours from the flask happens to be exactly what the target of your efforts would most like to have a dram or two of—wine, spirits, hot ginger tea, or ice cold water with lemon, for example. You gain a +1 item bonus on your Diplomacy check.</part>
         <part>The GM can disallow the flask's use if it doesn't make sense in the moment for you to pull out a flask and start pouring, if drinks are inappropriate for the occasion, or if your target is absolutely not interested in sharing a drink with you. Drinks from the <![CDATA[<i>flask of fellowship</i>]]> are entirely social; they won't intoxicate anyone, nor alleviate serious thirst.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Adventurer's Pack</title>
      <price>1 gp, 5 sp</price>
      <bulk>1 in the backpack</bulk>

      <line>This is the starter kit for an adventurer, containing the essential items for exploration and survival.</line>
      <line>The pack contains the following items: backpack (containing the other goods), bedroll, 10 pieces of chalk, flint and steel, 50 feet of rope, 2 weeks' rations, soap, 5 torches, and a waterskin.</line>

      <variant>
         <container>Backpack</container>
         <bulk>-</bulk>

         <line>A backpack holds up to 4 Bulk of items, and the first 2 Bulk of these items don't count against your Bulk limits. If you're carrying or stowing the pack rather than wearing it, its Bulk is light instead of negligible and the Bulk reduction does not apply.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>
</catalog>
