<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Potion</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1+</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Potion</trait> <trait>Vitality</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>(manipulate)</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A <i>healing potion</i> is a vial of ruby-red liquid that imparts a tingling sensation as the drinker's wounds heal rapidly. When you drink a <i>healing potion</i>, you regain the listed number of Hit Points.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Minor</type> <level>1</level>
         <price>4 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 1d8 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Lesser</type> <level>3</level>
         <price>12 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 2d8+5 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Moderate</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>50 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 3d8+10 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scimitar</title>
      <trait>Forceful</trait> <trait>Sweep</trait>
      <price>1 gp</price>
      <damage>1d6 S</damage>
      <bulk>1</bulk>
      <hands>1</hands>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Martial</weapcat> <weapgroup>Sword</weapgroup>

      <line>This one-handed curved blade is sharp on one side.</line>

      <traittext><name>Forceful</name>This weapon becomes more dangerous as you build momentum. When you attack with it more than once on your turn, the second attack gains a circumstance bonus to damage equal to the number of weapon damage dice, and each subsequent attack gains a circumstance bonus to damage equal to double the number of weapon damage dice.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Sweep</name>This weapon makes wide sweeping or spinning attacks, making it easier to attack multiple enemies. When you attack with this weapon, you gain a +1 circumstance bonus to your attack roll if you already attempted to attack a different target this turn using this weapon.</traittext>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">+1 Potency</rune> <level>2</level>
         <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>35 gp</price>

         <line>Magical enhancements make this weapon strike true. Attack rolls with this weapon gain a +1 item bonus, and the weapon can be etched with one property rune.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">Striking</rune> <level>4</level>
         <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>65 gp</price>

         <line>A <i>striking</i> rune stores destructive magic in the weapon, increasing the weapon damage dice it deals to two instead of one.</line>
      </variant>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">flaming</rune> <level>8</level>
         <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>500 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto a weapon</usage>

         <line>A weapon with this rune is empowered by flickering flame. The weapon deals an additional 1d6 fire damage on a successful Strike, plus 1d10 persistent fire damage on a critical hit.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Full Plate</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <ac>+6</ac> <dexcap>+0</dexcap> <checkpenalty>-3</checkpenalty> <spdpenalty>-10 ft.</spdpenalty>
      <strreq>+4</strreq>
      <bulk>4</bulk>
      <armorcat>Heavy</armorcat> <armorgroup>Plate</armorgroup>

      <line>Plate mail consists of interlocking plates that encase nearly the entire body in a carapace of steel. It is costly and heavy, and the wearer often requires help to don it correctly, but it provides some of the best defense armor can supply. A suit of this armor comes with an undercoat of padded armor and a pair of gauntlets.</line>

      <traittext><name>Bulwark</name>The armor covers you so completely that it provides benefits against some damaging effects. On Reflex saves to avoid a damaging effect, such as a <![CDATA[<i>fireball</i>]]>, you add a +3 modifier instead of your Dexterity modifier.</traittext>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">+1 potency</rune> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>160 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto the armor</usage>

         <line>Magic wards deflect attacks. Increase the armor's item bonus to AC by 1. The armor can be etched with a property rune.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">resilient</rune> <level>8</level>
         <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>340 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto the armor</usage>

         <line><i>Resilient</i> runes imbue armor with additional protective magic. This grants the wearer a +1 item bonus to saving throws.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Adamantine Shield</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>8+</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Precious</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>
      <base item="Shield">Steel Shield</base>

      <line>Adamantine shields are particularly sturdy, and when used for a shield bash, they're adamantine weapons.</line>

      <variant>
         <grade>standard</grade> <level>8</level>
         <price>440</price>

         <line>A standard-grade adamantine shield has Hardness 10, HP 40, and BT 20.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">lesser reinforcing</rune> <level>4</level>
         <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>75 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto the shield</usage>

         <line><i>Reinforcing runes</i> make a shield significantly more durable, allowing it to effectively block more powerful attacks.</line>
         <line>A <i>lesser reinforcing rune</i> increases the shield's Hardness by 3, Hit Points by 52, and its BT by 26 (maximum 10 Hardness, 80 HP, 40 BT).</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Doubling Rings</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn</usage> <bulk/>
      <price>50</price>

      <line>This item consists of two magically linked rings: an intricate, gleaming golden ring with a square-cut ruby, and a thick, plain iron ring. When you wield a melee weapon in the hand wearing the golden ring, the weapon's fundamental runes (<![CDATA[<i>potency</i> and <i>striking</i>]]>) are replicated onto any melee weapon you wield in the hand wearing the iron ring. Any fundamental runes normally on the weapon in the hand wearing the iron ring are suppressed.</line>
      <line>The replication functions only if you wear both rings, and it ends as a soon as you cease wielding a melee weapon in one of your hands. Consequently, the benefit doesn't apply to thrown attacks or if you're holding a weapon but not wielding it (such as holding in one hand a weapon that requires two hands to wield).</line>
   </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Eternal Eruption</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>5+</level>
         <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

         <line>This blueberry-sized bead appears to be a sphere of glass with a flickering light at its core. An <i>eternal eruption</i> resembles <i>frozen lava</i> and is made with the same type of time magic used to suspend lava at the exact point before a volcanic eruption, but it reforms itself after it's used. Determining the difference between the two requires a close examination to see a fain, repeating pattern of red runes.</line>
         <block>
            <name activate="">Lava Bomb</name> <action>2</action> <type>(concentrate, manipulate)</type>
            <part><name>Effect</name>You fling the <i>eternal eruption</i>, which detonates into a 20-foot burst ball of fire where it lands. Your toss can place the center anywhere within 70 feet, though at the GM's discretion, you might need to make a ranged attack roll if the throw is unusually challenging.</part>
            <part>After 2d4 hours, the <i>eternal eruption</i> reforms itself in a container on your person, typically the one you most recently stored it in.</part>
         </block>

         <variant>
            <name italic="">eternal eruption of blackpeak</name> <level>7</level>
            <price>360 gp</price>

            <line>7d6 fire damage, with a DC 25 basic Reflex save.</line>
         </variant>
      </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Obsidian Goggles</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>150 gp</price>
      <usage>worn eyepiece</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>

      <line>The sleek, black lenses of these goggles somehow make everything seem more brightly lit. While wearing the goggles, you gain a +1 item bonus to Perception checks involving sight.</line>
      <block>
         <name activate="">Darkvision</name> <action>1</action> <type>(manipulate)</type>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>Adjusting the goggles, you gain darkvision for 1 hour.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Charm of Resistance</title>
      <type>Item</type><level>6+</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait><trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn</usage><bulk/>

      <line>This charm, normally hung from the belt or worn around the neck, grants you resistance against one type of energy damage: acid, cold, electricity, fire, or sonic.
         Each charm is crafted to protect against a particular type of energy damage, and its design usually embodies the type of energy it protects the wearer from in some way.
         For instance, a charm of cold resistance could be carved in the shape of a yeti, whereas a charm of fire resistance would be made from volcanic glass.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>cold</type>
         <price>245 gp</price>

         <line>The charm grants resistance 5 to cold.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Backfire Mantle</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3+</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn cloak</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>This vivid red cloak of sturdy fabric is favored by aggressive battle alchemists and mages, as well as those cautious warriors who need to advance into the fray ahead of the blast-happy back line. The mantle interposes to protect you from your own and allies' magic, granting you a circumstance bonus to Reflex saves against your own spells as well as those of your allies. You also gain resistance to splash damage from your own alchemical items and those of your allies.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Greater</type> <level>8</level>
         <price>430 gp</price>

         <line>The mantle grants a +2 circumstance bonus and resistance 10.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shining Symbol</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3+</level>
      <trait>Divine</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Light</trait>
      <usage>worn</usage> <bulk/>

      <line>If you worship a deity, this golden amulet transforms into your deity's religious symbol when you invest it. You gain an item bonus to Religion. The symbol casts dim light in a 20-foot emanation. </line>

      <block>
         <name activate="">Spiritual Light</name><action>2</action><type>(concentrate, light, revelation)</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>The light cast by the symbol becomes bright light for 10 minutes and shines through bodies to reveal hints of the spirits within. Creatures within the light receive a status penalty to Deception and Stealth checks.</part>
         <part>You can Dismiss this activation.</part>
      </block>

      <variant>
         <type>regular</type> <level>3</level>
         <price>55 gp</price>

         <line>The item bonus to Religion is +1, and the status penalty from Spiritual Light is -1.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Pendant of the Occult</title>
      <type>Item</type><level>3+</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait><trait>Occult</trait>
      <usage>worn</usage><bulk/>

      <line>This amulet is hollow and shaped in the form of an unblinking eye. Its cavity typically holds some fragment of occult text. While wearing the pendant, you gain an item bonus to Occultism checks, and you can cast the <i>guidance</i> cantrip as an occult innate spell.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>greater</type>
         <level>9</level>
         <price>650 gp</price>

         <line>The pendant grants a +2 item bonus, and can be activated.</line>
         <block>
            <name activate="">Dream Message</name><type>(concentrate, manipulate)</type>
            <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
            <part><name>Effect</name>You cast a 4th-rank <i>dream message</i> spell.</part>
         </block>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Guidance</title> <action>1</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Occult</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>Until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You ask for the guidance of supernatural entities, granting the target a +1 status bonus to one attack roll, Perception check, saving throw, or skill check the target attempts before the duration ends. The target chooses which roll to use the bonus on before rolling. If the target uses the bonus, the spell ends. Either way, the target is then temporarily immune for 1 hour.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dream Message</title>
      <type>Spell</type><level>3</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait><trait>Mental</trait><trait>Occult</trait>
      <cast>10 minutes</cast>
      <range>planetary</range><targets>1 creature you know by name and have met in person</targets>
      <duration>until your next daily preparations</duration>

      <line>You send a message to your target's dream. The message is one-way, up to 1 minute of speech (roughly 150 words). If the target is asleep, they receive the message instantly. If not, they receive it the next time they sleep. As soon as they receive it, the spell ends, and you know the message was sent.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">You can target up to 10 creatures you know by name and have met in person. You must send the same message to all of them; the spell ends for each target individually.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Everburning Torch</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Light</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>15 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>An <i>everburning torch</i> is one of the most common applications of permanent magic. This torch sheds light constantly, requiring no oxygen and generating no heat. The flame can be covered or hidden, but can't be smothered or quenched.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Adventurer's Pack</title>
      <price>1 gp, 5 sp</price>
      <bulk>1 in the backpack</bulk>

      <line>This is the starter kit for an adventurer, containing the essential items for exploration and survival.</line>
      <line>The pack contains the following items: backpack (containing the other goods), bedroll, 10 pieces of chalk, flint and steel, 50 feet of rope, 2 weeks' rations, soap, 5 torches, and a waterskin.</line>

      <variant>
         <container>Backpack</container>
         <bulk>-</bulk>

         <line>A backpack holds up to 4 Bulk of items, and the first 2 Bulk of these items don't count against your Bulk limits. If you're carrying or stowing the pack rather than wearing it, its Bulk is light instead of negligible and the Bulk reduction does not apply.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healer's Toolkit</title>
      <price>5 gp</price>
      <hands>1 or 2</hands> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>This kit of bandages, herbs, and suturing tools is necessary for Medicine checks to Administer First Aid, Treat Disease, Treat Poison, or Treat Wounds. If you wear your healer's tools, you can draw and replace them as part of the action that uses them.</line>
      <line toolkit=""/>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Repair Kit</title>
      <price>2 gp</price>
      <hands>1 or 2</hands> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>A repair kit allows you to perform simple repairs while traveling. It contains a portable anvil, tongs, woodworking tools, a whetstone, and oils for conditioning leather and wood. You can use a repair kit to Repair items using the Crafting skill. If you wear your repair kit, you can draw and replace them as part of the action to use them.</line>
      <line toolkit=""/>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Crafter's Eyepiece</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn eyepiece</usage> <bulk/>
      <price>60 gp</price>

      <line>This rugged metal eyepiece etched with sqare patterns is designed to be worn over a single eye. Twisting the lens reveals a faint three-dimensional outline of an item you plan to build or repair, with helpful labels on the component parts. You gain a +1 item bonus to Crafting checks.</line>
      <line>When you Repair an item, increase the Hit Points restored to 10 + 10 per proficiency rank on a success or 15 + 15 per proficiency rank on a critical success.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
