@ -0,0 +1,131 @@
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>All About Tricks</category>
      <line>A trick has three main components: its level, its traits, and the associated skill. It also has a description that ties all these components together narratively, and might have a name.</line>
      <line>The higher a trick's level, the harder it is to successfully perform, but also the more Exctiement and Anticipation it has the potential to generate. A character can not Perform a Trick of a higher level than he or she is.</line>
      <line list="Standard DC by level">
         <entry name="1 -">15</entry>
         <entry name="2 -">16</entry>
         <entry name="3 -">18</entry>
         <entry name="4 -">19</entry>
         <entry name="5 -">20</entry>
         <entry name="6 -">22</entry>
      </line>
      <line>The trick's traits and associated skill are somewhat connected; Some traits allow you to use skills that otherwise wouldn't be allowed. Some traits, like <![CDATA[<u>injury</u>]]>, have specific rules attached to them.</line>
      <line>You can choose up to any two basic traits when Performing a Trick if you are trained in Performance or an applicable Lore. If you are an expert, you can choose a specialized trait in place of one basic trait. If you are a master, you can choose up to two specialized traits, and if you are legendary, you can choose up to three basic or specialized traits.</line>
      <line>By default, a trick uses Performance or an applicable Lore as its associated skill. If you have a feat or ability, such as Acrobatic Performer, that allows you to use another skill instead of Performance when you Perform, you can use that skill. Otherwise, you need to use a trait that allows you to change the skill.</line>
      <line name="Special">Feel free to suggest new traits and work with your GM to determine what the effects of that trait should be.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <category>Basic Traits</category>
      <trait>Aerial</trait>
      <line>This trick involves flight, whether magical or mundane, or otherwise defying gravity. You can use Acrobatics instead of Performance.</line>
      <line>You can choose to add the <![CDATA[<u>injury</u>]]> trait to the trick without it counting against how many traits it has.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Agile</trait>
      <line>The penalty for performing this trick a second or third time in the same act is -4 or -8, respecitvely, instead of -5 and -10.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Animal</trait>
      <line>This trick utilizes trained animals. You can use Nature instead of Performance.</line>
      <line>If you have an animal companion that is trained in an appropriate skill, once per show, your companion can Costar one of your <![CDATA[<u>animal</u>]]> tricks.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Audience</trait>
      <line>The audience participates in the trick. You can use Diplomacy instead of Performance.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Dangerous</trait>
      <line>Something in the trick, such as the use of pyrotechnics or dangerous spells, puts the audience in danger. You can use Intimidate instead of Performance.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Group</trait>
      <line>This trick involves dancing or other choreographed movements. The circumstance bonuses from other performers Costarring or a stagehand Assisting a Performer stack for this trick.</line>
      <line>If this trick has the <![CDATA[<u>injury</u>]]> trait, you generate 1 additional Excitement on a success or critical success for each performer Costarring or stagehand Assisting a Performer, but each of them must also roll the flat check to see if they are injured.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Injury</trait>
      <line>The trick involves a great chance of injury to the performer. You can use a saving throw instead of Performance, unless this trait was added by another trait or the Take a Risk action.</line>
      <line>An <![CDATA[<u>injury</u>]]> trick counts as 2 levels higher for all purposes other than determining its DC. After performing the trick, make a flat check unless you critically succeeded on the trick. The DC is 5 if the trick was successful, 10 if the trick was a failure, or 15 if it was a critical failure. On a failure, you are injured, but generate Excitement equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum 1 Excitement). On a critical failure, you are injured and lose 2 Excitement.</line>
      <line>A performer who Costars or a stagehand who Assists a Performer with this trick must also make a flat check with the same DC.</line>
      <line>An injured performer can not Perform a Trick or Costar.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Juggling</trait>
      <line>This trick involves keeping multiple objects in the air at the same time. You can use Acrobatics or Thievery instead of Performance.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Prop</trait>
      <line>Props are the draw for this trick, whether it's outfits, special effects, or some special construction on the stage. You can use Craft instead of Performance.</line>
      <line>If you use a consumable item, this trait does not count towards how many traits the trick has. If the item is at least 3rd level, you gain a +1 item bonus to your check, or a +2 item bonus for an item of at least 11th level, or a +3 item bonus for an item of at least 17th level.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Sleight of Hand</trait>
      <line>This trick involves quick fingers, fast talk, or other feats of legerdemain. You can use Deception or Thievery instead of Performance.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Strength</trait>
      <line>This trick involves feats of strength, such as power-lifting or wrestling. You can use Athletics instead of Performance.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Weapon</trait>
      <line>The trick shows off your skill with a weapon, such as archery, fencing, or knife-throwing. You can use an attack roll in place of Performance.</line>
      <line>If another performer Costars this trick or a stagehand Assists a Performer, this trick gains the <![CDATA[<u>injury</u>]]> trait without it counting against how many traits it has.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <category>Specialized Traits</category>
      <trait>Attention-grabber</trait>
      <line>This trick commands such attention from the audience that it can even cover up for mistakes in other performers' routine. As long as you don't critically fail your Perform a Trick, other performers in the same act gain a -1 to the DC to Perform a Trick.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Continuation</trait>
      <requirement>you must have Performed a Trick in this act</requirement>
      <line>The trick is designed to continue on from a previous trick. You generate additional Excitement equal to one-half the trick's level on a success, or equal to the trick's level on a critical success.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Magical</trait>
      <requirement>You must be able to use an action with the <![CDATA[<u>arcane</u>, <u>divine</u>, <u>occult</u> or <u>primal</u>]]> trait</requirement>

      <line>This trick incorporates actual magic. Each magical tradition counts as its own trait, and you can use the magical tradition's skill instead of Performance.</line>
      <line>If you expend a spell slot, you gain a +1 status bonus to your check. This increases to a +2 status bonus if you expend a spell slot of at least 2nd rank, a +3 status bonus for a spell slot of at least 5th, a +4 status bonus for a spell slot of at least 8th rank, or a +5 status bonus for a spell slot of 10th rank.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Professional</trait>
      <frequency>you can only use one trick with this trait per show</frequency>
      <requirement>trained in an appropriate Lore</requirement>

      <line>This trick has been honed to perferction through endless hours. The trick must use an appropriate Lore instead of Performance.</line>
      <line>This trick does not take the penalty for making multiple Perform a Trick checks in an act, and does not count towards increasing the penalty for other tricks.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Setup</trait>
      <line>This trick sets up your follow-up tricks to be even more impressive. With each successive trick in the same act, as long as you don't critically fail to Perform that Trick, you gain either 2 Anticipation or 2 maximum Anticipation, your choice.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Supportive</trait>
      <line>This trick is designed to augment another performer's trick. As long as you don't critically fail to Perform this Trick, you grant one performer in the same act a +1 circumstance bonus to his or her next Perform a Trick check. You can grants this bonus to a given performer only once per show.</line>
   </rule>

</catalog>
