<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Earn Income</title>
      <type>Varies</type>
      <trait>Downtime</trait>

      <line>You use one of your skills to make money during downtime. The GM assigns a task level representing the most lucrative job available. You can search for lower-level tasks, with the GM determining whether you find any. Sometimes you can attempt to find better work than the initial offerings, though this takes time and requires using the Diplomacy skill to Gather Information, doing some research, or socializing.</line>
      <line>When you take on a job, the GM secretly sets the DC of your skill check. After your first day of work, you roll to determine your earnings. You gain an amount of income based on your result, the task's level, and your proficiency rank.</line>
      <line>You can continue working at the task on subsequent days without needing to roll again. For each day you spend after the first, you earn the same amount as the first day, up until the task's completion. The GM determines how long you can work at the task. Most tasks last a week or two, though some can take months or even years.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You do outstanding work. Gain the amount of currency listed for the task level +1 and your proficiency rank.</critsuccess>
         <success>You do compenent work. Gain the amount of currency listed for the task level and your proficiency rank.</success>
         <fail>You do shoddy work and get paid the bare minimum for your time. Gain the amount of currency listed in the failure column for the task level. The GM will likely reduce how long you can continue at the task.</fail>
         <critfail>You earn nothing for your work and are fired immediately. YOu can't continue at the task. Your reputation suffers, potentially making it difficult for you to find rewarding jobs in that community in the future.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Income earned per day</b>]]></line>
      <line list="">
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 0 task (DC 14):</b> <i>Failure</i> 1 cp; <i>Trained</i> 5 cp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 1 task (DC 15):</b> <i>Failure</i> 2 cp; <i>Trained</i> 2 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 2 task (DC 16):</b> <i>Failure</i> 4 cp; <i>Trained</i> 3 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 3 task (DC 18):</b> <i>Failure</i> 8 cp; <i>Trained</i> 5 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 4 task (DC 19):</b> <i>Failure</i> 1 sp; <i>Trained</i> 7 sp; <br /><i>Expert</i> 8 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 5 task (DC 20):</b> <i>Failure</i> 2 sp; <i>Trained</i> 9 sp; <br /><i>Expert</i> 1 gp]]></entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Subsist</title>
      <type>Varies</type>
      <trait>Downtime</trait>

      <line>You try to provide food and shelter for yourself, and possibly others as well, with a standard of living. The GM determines the DC based on the nature of the place where you're trying to Subsist. You might need a minimum proficiency rank to Subsist in particularly strange environments. Unlike most downtime activities, you can Subsist after 8 hours or less of exploration, but if you do, you take a -5 penalty.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You either provide a subsistence living for yourself and one additional creature, or you improve your own food and shelter, granting yourself a comfortable living.</critsuccess>
         <success>You find enough food and shelter with basic protection from the elements to provide you a subsistence living.</success>
         <fail>You're exposed to the elements and don't get enough food, becoming fatigued until you attain sufficient food and shelter.</fail>
         <critfail>You attract trouble, eat something you shouldn't, or otherwise worsen your situation. You take a -2 circumstance penalty to checks to Subsist for 1 week. You don't find food at all; if you don't have any stored up, you're in danger of starving or dying of thirst if you continue failing.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Sample Subsist Tasks</b>]]></line>
      <line list="">
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Untrained (DC 10):</b>]]> lush forest with calm weather or large city with plentiful resources</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Trained (DC 15):</b>]]> typical hillside or village</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Expert (DC 20):</b>]]> typical mountains or insular hamlet</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Master (DC 30):</b>]]> typical desert or city under siege</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Legendary (DC 40):</b>]]> barren wasteland or city of undead</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
