<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Low-Light Vision</title>

      <line>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the concealed condition due to dim light.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Whisper Elf</title>

      <line>Your ears are finely tuned, able to detect even the slightest whisper of sound. As long as you can hear normally, you can use the Seek action to sense undetected creatures in a 60-foot cone instead of a 30-foot cone. You also gain a +2 circumstance bonus to locate undetected creatures that you could hear within 30 feet with a Seek action.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Seek</title>
      <action>1</action>

      <line>You scan an area for signs of creatures of objects. If you're looking for creatures, choose an area you're scanning. If precision is necessary, the GM can have you select a 30-foot cone or a 15-foot burst within line of sight. You might take a penalty if you choose an area that's far away.</line>
      <line>If you're using Seek to search for objects (including secret doors and hazards), you search up to a 10-foot square adjacent to you. The GM might determine you need to Seek as an activity, taking more actions or even minutes or hours if you're searching a particularly cluttered area.</line>
      <line>The GM attempts a single secret Perception check for you and compares the result to the Stealth DCs of any undetected or hidden creatures in the area or the DC to detect each object in the area (as determined by the GM or by someone Concealing the Object). A creature you detect might remain hidden, rather than becoming observed, if you're using an imprecise sense (such as hearing) or if an effect (such as an <![CDATA[<i>invisibility</i>]]> spell) prevents it from being observed.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>If you were searching for creatures, any undetected or hidden creature you critically succeeded against becomes observed by you. If you were searching for an object, you learn its location.</critsuccess>
         <success>If you were searching for creatures, any undetected creature you succeeded against becomes hidden from you instead of undetected, and any hidden creature you succeeded against becomes observed by you. If you were searching for an object, you learn its location or get a clue to its whereabouts, as determined by the GM.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elven Verve</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>While all elves are immune to the paralyzing touch of ghouls, you can shake off flesh-numbing magic of all kinds. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to saves against effect that would impose the immobilized, paralyzed, or slowed conditions. When you would be immobilized, paralyzed, or slowed for at least 2 rounds, reduce that duration by 1 round.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Otherworldly Magic</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Elf</trait>

      <line>Your elven magic manifests as a simple arcane spell, even if you aren't formally trained in magic. Choose one cantrip from the arcane spell list. You can cast this cantrip as an arcane innate spell at will. A cantrip is heighened to a spell level equal to half your level rounded up. Since this magic is innate, you can replace any material component with a somatic component.</line>
   </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Prestidigitation</title>
         <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
         <trait>Arcane</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait>
         <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
         <range>10 feet</range> <targets>1 object (cook, lift, or tidy only)</targets>
         <duration>sustained</duration>

         <line>The simplest magic does your bidding. You can perform simple magical effects for as long as you Sustain the Spell. Each time you Sustain the Spell, you can choose one of four options.</line>
         <line list="">
            <entry><![CDATA[<b>Cook</b>]]> Cool, warm, or flavor 1 pound of nonliving material.</entry>
            <entry><![CDATA[<b>Lift</b>]]> Slowly lift an unattended object of light Bulk or less 1 foot off the ground.</entry>
            <entry><![CDATA[<b>Make</b>]]> Create a temporary object of negligible Bulk, made of congealed magical substance. The object looks crude and artificial and is extremely fragile; it can't be used as a tool, weapon, or spell component.</entry>
            <entry><![CDATA[<b>Tidy</b>]]> Color, clean, or soil an object of light Bulk or less. You can affect an object of 1 Bulk with 10 rounds of concentration, and a larger object a 1 minute per Bulk.</entry>
         </line>
         <line><![CDATA[<i>Prestidigitation</i>]]> can't deal damage or cause adverse conditions. Any actual change to an object (beyond what is noted above) persists only as long as you Sustain the Spell.</line>
         <line name="Otherwordly Magic:">You gained this cantrip from your Otherwordly Magic ancestry feat. It is an arcane innate spell.</line>
      </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Raise a Shield</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <requirement>You are wielding a shield.</requirement>

      <line>You position your shield to protect yourself. When you have Raised a Shield, you gain its listed circumstance bonus to AC. Your shield remains raised until the start of your next turn.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shield Block</title>
      <action>R</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <trigger>While you have your shield raised, you would take damage from a physical attack</trigger>

      <line>You snap your shield in place to ward off a blow. Your shield prevents you from taking an amount of damage up to the shield's Hardness. You and the shield each take any remaining damage, possibly breaking or destroying the shield.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Treat Wounds</title>
      <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <requirements>You are holding healer's tools, or you are wearing them and have a hand free</requirements>

      <line>You spend 10 minutes treating one injured living creature (targeting yourself, if you so choose). The target is then temporarily immune to Treat Wounds actions for 1 hour, but this interval overlaps with the time you spent treating (so a patient can be treated once per hour, not once per 70 minutes).</line>
      <line>The Medicine check DC is usually 15, though the GM might adjust it based on the circumstances, such as treating a patient outside in a storm, or treating magically cursed wounds. If you're an expert in Medicine, you can instead attempt a DC 20 check to increase the Hit Points regained by 10; if you're a master of Medicine, you can instead attempt a DC 30 check to increase the Hit Points regained by 30; and if you're legendary, you can instead attempt a DC 40 check to increase the Hit Points regained by 50. The damage dealt on a critical failure remains the same.</line>

      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target regains the second healing value, and its wounded condition is removed.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target regains the first healing value, and its wounded condition is removed.</success>
         <critfail>The target takes 1d8 damage.</critfail>
      </line>

      <line>If you succeed at your check, you can continue treating the target to grant additional healing. If you treat them for a total of 1 hour, double the Hit Points they regain from Treat Wounds.</line>

      <line><![CDATA[<b>Treat Wounds, healing by proficiency</b>]]></line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Trained Profiency (DC 15) - 2d8 / 4d8</entry>
         <entry>Expert Proficiency (DC 20) - 2d8 + 10 / 4d8 + 10</entry>
         <entry>Master Proficiency (DC 30) - 2d8 + 30 / 4d8 + 30</entry>
         <entry>Legendary Proficiency (DC 40) - 2d8 + 50 / 4d8 + 50</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Battle Medicine</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <action>1</action>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Medicine</prereq>
      <requirements>You are holding healder's tools, or you are wearing them and have a hand free</requirements>

      <line>You can patch up wounds, even in combat. Attempt a Medicine check with the same DC as for Treat Wounds and restore the corresponding amount of HP; this doesn't remove the wounded condition. The target is then immune to your Battle Medicine for 1 day.</line>
      <line>As with Treat Wounds, you can attempt a check against higher DCs if you have the minimum proficiency rank.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Continual Recovery</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>expert in Medicine</prereq>

      <line>You zealously monitor a patient's progress to administer treatment faster. When you Treat Wounds, your patient becomes immune only for 10 minutes instead of 1 hour. This applies only to your Treat Wounds activities, not any other the patient receives.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Experienced Tracker</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Survival</prereq>

      <line>Tracking is second nature to you, and when necessary you can follow a trail without a pause. You can Track while moving at full Speed by taking a -5 penalty to your Survival check. If you're a Master in Survival, you don't take the -5 penalty. If you're Legendary in Survival, you no longer need to roll a new Survival check every hour when tracking, though you still need to roll whenever there are significant changes in the trail</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Track</title>
      <type>Survival</type>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Move</trait>

      <line>You follow tracks, moving at up to half your travel speed. After a successful check to Track, you can continue following the tracks at half your Speed without attempting additional checks for up to 1 hour.</line>
      <line>In some cases, you might Track in an encounter. In this case, Track is a single action and doesn't have the exploration trait, but you might need to roll more often because you're in a tense situation. The GM determines how often you must attempt this check.</line>
      <line>You attempt your Survival check when you start Tracking, once every hour you continue tracking, and any time something significant changes in the trail. The GM determines the DCs for such checks, depending on the freshness of the trail, the weather, and the type of ground and whether your targets attempts to Cover Tracks.</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>You find the trail or continue to follow the one you're already following.</success>
         <fail>You lose the trail but can try again after a 1-hour delay.</fail>
         <critfail>You lose the trail and can't try again for 24 hours.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Sample Track Task Difficulties</b>]]></line>
      <line list="">
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Untrained (DC 10):</b>]]> the path of a large army following a road</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Trained (DC 15):</b>]]> relatively fresh tracks of a rampaging bear through the plains</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Expert (DC 20):</b>]]> a nimble panther's tracks through a jungle; tracks obscured by rainfall</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Master (DC 30):</b>]]> tracks obscured by winter snow; tracks of a mouse or smaller creature; tracks left on surfaces that can't hold prints like bare rock</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Legendary (DC 40):</b>]]> old tracks through a windy desert's sands; tracks after a major blizzard or hurricane</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Anathema</title>

      <line>As stewards of the natural order, druids find affronts to nature anathema. If you perform acts that are anatheme to nature, you lose your magical abilities that come from the druid class, including your primal spellcasting and the benefits of your order. These abilities can be regained only if you demonstrate your repentance by conducting an <![CDATA[<i>atone</i>]]> ritual.</line>
      <line>The following acts are anathema to all druids:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Using metal armor or shields.</entry>
         <entry>Despoiling natural places.</entry>
         <entry>Teaching the Druidic language to non-druids.</entry>
      </line>
      <line>The following acts are anathema to druids of the storm order:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Polluting the air.</entry>
         <entry>Allowing those who cause major air pollution or climate shifts to go unpunished. This doesn't force you to take action against merely potential harm to the environment or to sacrifice yourself against an obviously superior foe.</entry>
      </line>
      <line>The following act is anathema to druids of the wild order:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Becoming fully domesticated by the temptations of civilization. This doesn't prevent you from buying and using processed goods or staying in a city for an adventure, but you can never come to rely on these conveniences or truly call such a place your permanent home.</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Druidic Language</title>

      <line>You know Druidic, a secret language known only to druids, in addition to any languages you know through your ancestry. Druidic has its own alphabet.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Storm Order</title>

      <line>You carry the fury of the storm with you, channeling it to terrifying effect and riding the winds through the sky.</line>
      <line>You are trained in Acrobatics. You also gain the Storm Born druid feat. You gain the <![CDATA[<i>tempest surge</i>]]> order spell, and you increase the number of Focus Points in your focus pool by 1.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Storm Born</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Druid</trait>
      <prereq>storm order</prereq>

      <line>You are at home out in the elements, reveling in the power of nature unleashed. You do not take circumstance penalties to ranged spell attacks or Perception checks caused by weather, and your targeted spells don't require a flat check to succeed against a target concealed by weather (such as fog or rain).</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Order Explorer</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Druid</trait>

      <line>You have learned the secrets of another druidic order, passing whatever rites of initiation that order requires and gaining access to its secrets. Choose an order other than your own.</line>
      <line>You gain a 1st-level feat that lists that order as a prerequisite, and you are now a member of that order for the purpose of meeting feat prerequisites.</line>
      <line>If you commit acts anathema to your new order, you lose all feats and abilities requiring that order but retain your other druid feats and abilities. You don't gain any of the other benefits of the order you chose.</line>
      <line name="Choice">You chose the wild order, and gained the Wild Shape feat.</line>
      <special>You can take this feat multiple times. Each time you do, you must choose a different order other than your own.</special>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Wild Shape</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Druid</trait>
      <prereq>wild order</prereq>

      <line>You are one with the wild, always changing and adapting to meet any challenge. You gain the <![CDATA[<i>wild shape</i>]]> order spell, which lets you transform into a variety of forms that you can expand with druid feats.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Primal Spellcasting</title>

      <line>The power of the wild world flows through you. You can cast primal spells using the Cast a Spell activity, and you can supply material, somatic, and verbal components when casting spells. Because you're a druid, you can usually hold a primal focus (such as holly and mistletoe) for spells requiring material components instead of needing to use a material component pouch.</line>
      <line>You can prepare spells and five cantrips each morning from the common spells on the primal spell list, or from other primal spells to which you gain access. Prepared spells remain available to you until you cast them or until you prepare your spells again. The number of spells you can prepare is called your spells slots.</line>
      <line>Some of your spells require you to attempt a spell attack roll to see how effective they are, or have your enemies roll against your spell DC. Since your key ability is Wisdom, your spell attack rolls and spell DCs use your Wisdom modifier.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Cantrips</b>]]></line>
      <line>Some of your spells are cantrips. A cantrip is a special type of spell that doesnt use spell slots. You can cast a cantrip at will, any number of times per day.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cast a Spell</title>

      <line>You cast a spell you have prepared or in your repertoire. Casting a Spell is a special activity that takes a variable number of actions depending on the spell, as listed in each spell's stat block. As soon as the spellcasting actions are complete, the spell effect occurs.</line>
      <line>Some spells are cast as a reaction or free action. In those cases, you Cast the Spell as a reaction or free action (as appropriate) instead of as an activity.</line>
      <line name="Long Casting Times"> Some spells take minutes or hours to cast. The Cast a Spell activity for these spells includes the required time with the listed spell components, but it's not necessary to break down which one you're providing at a given time. You can't use other actions or reactions while casting such a spell, though at the GM's discretion, you might be able to speak a few sentences. As with other activities that take a long time, these spells have the exploration trait, and you can't cast them in an encounter. If combat breaks out while you're casting one, your spell is disrupted.</line>
      <line name="Spell Components"> Each spell lists the spell components required to cast it, such as "material, somatic, verbal". The spell components, described in detail below, add traits (listed in parenthesis) and requirements to the Cast a Spell activity. If you can't provide the components, you fail to Cast the Spell.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Material (manipulate);">A material component is a bit of physical matter consumed in the casting of the spell, and requires you to have a free hand to retrieve and manipulate the material component. The component is expended in the casting (even if the spell is disrupted).<![CDATA[<br/>]]>Except in extreme circumstances, you can assume all common components are included in a material component pouch.</entry>
         <entry name="Somatic (manipulate);">A somatic component is a specific hand movement or gesture that generates a magical nexus. You can use this component while holding something in your hand, but not if you are restrained or otherwise unable to gesture freely.<![CDATA[<br/>]]> Spells that require you to touch the target require a somatic component. You can do so while holding something as long as part of your hand is able to touch the target (even if it's through a glove or gauntlet).</entry>
         <entry name="Verbal (concentrate);">A verbal component is a vocalization of words of power. You must speak them in a strong voice, so it's hard to conceal that you're Casting a Spell. You must be able to speak to provide this component.</entry>
         <entry name="Focus (manipulate);">A focus is an object that funnels the magical energy of the spell. The spell requires you to either have a free hand to retrieve the focus listed in the spell or already holding the focus in your hand. As part of Casting the spell, you retrieve the focus (if necessary), manipulate it, and can stow it again if you so choose.<![CDATA[<br/>]]> Foci tend to be expensive, and you need to acquire them in advance to Cast the Spell.</entry>
      </line>
      <line name="Disrupted and Lost Spells">Some abilities and spells can disrupt a spell, causing it to have no effect and be lost. When you lose a spell, you've already expended the spell slot, spent the spell's costs and actions, and used the Cast a Spell activity. If a spell is disrupted during a Sustain a Spell action, the spell immediately ends. See the full rules for more information.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Order Spells</title>

      <line>Order spells are a type of focus spell. It costs 1 Focus Point to cast a focus spell, and you have a focus pool of 1 Focus Point for each focus spell you have, to a maximum of 3 Focus Points. You refill your focus pool during your daily preparations, and you can regain 1 Focus Point by spending 10 minutes using the Refocus activity to commune with local nature spirits or otherwise tend to the wilderness in a way befitting your order.</line>
      <line>Focus spells don't require spell slots to cast, and you can't cast them using spell slots. They are automatically heightened half your level rounded up. You gain the order spell for your druidic order.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Refocus</title>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait>
      <requirement>You have a focus pool, and you have spent at least 1 Focus Point</requirement>

      <line>You spend 10 minutes performing deeds to restore your magical connection. This restores 1 Focus Point to your focus pool. The deeds you need to perform are specified in the class or ability that gives you your focus spells. These deeds can usually overlap with other tasks that relate to the source of your focus spells. For instance, a cleric with focus spells from a good deity can usually Refocus while tending the wounds of their allies, and a wizard of the illusionist school might be able to Refocus while attempting to Identify Magic of the illusion school.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Reach Spell</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Druid</trait> <trait>Metamagic</trait>

      <line>You can extend the range of your spells. If the next action you use is to Cast a Spell that has a range, increase that spell's range by 30 feet. As is standard for increasing spell ranges, if the spell normally has a range of touch, you extend its range to 30 feet.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tempest Surge</title>
      <type>Focus</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon /> <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Druid</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>You surround a foe in a swirling storm of violent winds, roiling clouds, and crackling lightning. The storm deals 1d12 electricity damage. The Target must attempt a basic Reflex save. On a failure, the target also is clumsy 2 for 1 round and takes 1 persistent electricity damage.</line>
      <heighten value="+1">The initial damage increases by 1d12, and the persistent electricity damage on a failure increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Wild Shape</title>
      <type>Focus</type> <level>1</level>
      <uncommon /> <trait>Druid</trait> <trait>Polymorph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <duration>1 minute (or longer)</duration>

      <line>You infuse yourself with primal essence and transform yourself into another form. You can polymorph into any form listed in <![CDATA[<i>pest form</i>]]>, which lasts for 10 minutes. All other <![CDATA[<i>wild shape</i>]]> forms last 1 minute.</line>
      <line>You can add more forms to your <![CDATA[<i>wild shape</i>]]> list with druid feats; your feat might grant you some or all of the forms from a given polymorph spell. When you transform into a form from a spell, you gain all the effects of the form you choose from a version of the spell heightened to <![CDATA[<i>wild shape</i>]]>'s level.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Wild shape</i>]]> allows you to use your own shapeshifting training more easily than most polymorph spells. When you choose to use your own attack modifier while polymorphed instead of the form's default attack modifier, you gain a +2 status bonus to your attack rolls.</line>

      <heighten value="2nd">You can also <![CDATA[<i>wild shape</i>]]> into the forms listed in <![CDATA[<i>animal form</i>]]>.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Pest Form</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Polymorph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>You transform into the battle form of a Tiny animal, such as a cat, insect, lizard, or rat. You can decide the specific type of animal (such as a rat or praying mantis), but this has no effect on the form's Size or statistics. While in this form, you gain the animal trait, and you can't make Strikes. You can Dismiss the spell.</line>
      <line>You gain the following statistics and abilities:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>AC = 15 + your level. You ignore your armor's check penalty and Speed reduction.</entry>
         <entry>Speed of 20 feet.</entry>
         <entry>Weakness 5 to physical damage, meaning if you take physical damage in this form, you take 5 additional damage.</entry>
         <entry>Low-light vision and imprecise scent 30 feet.</entry>
         <entry>Acrobatics and Stealth modifiers of +10, unless your own modifier is higher; Atheletics modifier of -4.</entry>
      </line>

      <heighten value="4th">You can turn into a flying creature, such as a bird, which grants you a fly Speed of 20 feet in addition to the above statistics.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Animal Form</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Polymorph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You call upon primal energy to transform yourself into a Medium animal battle form. When you cast this spell, choose ape, bear, bull, canine, cat, deer, frog, shark, or snake. You can decide the specific type of animal (such as lion or snow leopard for cat), but this has no effect on the form's Size or statistics. While in this form, you gain the Animal trait. You can Dismiss the spell.</line>
      <line>You gain the following statistics and abilities regardless of which battle form you choose:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>AC = 16 + your level. Ignore your armor check penalty and Speed reduction.</entry>
         <entry>5 temporary hit points.</entry>
         <entry>Low-light vision and imprecise scent 30 feet.</entry>
         <entry>One or more unarmed melee attacks specific to the battle form you choose, which are the only attacks you can Strike with. You're trained with them. Your attack modifier is +9, and your damage bonus is +1. These attacks are Strength-based (for the purpose of the enfeebled condition, for example). If your unarmed attack bonus is higher, you can use it instead.</entry>
         <entry>Athletics modifier of +9, unless your own modifier is higher.</entry>
      </line>
      <line>You also gain specific abilities based on the type of animal you choose:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Ape">Speed 25 feet, climb Speed 20 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> fist, <b>Damage </b>]]> 2d6 bludgeoning.</entry>
         <entry name="Bear">Speed 30 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> jaws, <b>Damage </b>2d8 piercing; <br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> claw (agile), <b>Damage </b>]]> 1d8 slashing.</entry>
         <entry name="Bull">Speed 30 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> horn, <b>Damage </b>]]>2d8 piercing.</entry>
         <entry name="Canine">Speed 40 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> jaws, <b>Damage </b>]]>2d8 piercing.</entry>
         <entry name="Cat">Speed 40 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> jaws, <b>Damage </b>2d6 pierching; <br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> claw (agile), <b>Damage </b>]]>1d10 slashing.</entry>
         <entry name="Deer">Speed 50 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> antler, <b>Damage </b>]]> 2d6 piercing.</entry>
         <entry name="Frog">Speed 25 feet, swim Speed 25 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> jaws, <b>Damage </b>2d6 bludgeoning; <br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> tongue (reach 15 feet), <b>Damage </b>]]>2d4 bludgeoning.</entry>
         <entry name="Shark">swim Speed 35 feet, breathe underwater but not in air; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> jaws, <b>Damage </b>]]>2d8 piercing.</entry>
         <entry name="Snake">Speed 20 feet, climb Speed 20 feet, swim Speed 20 feet; <![CDATA[<br/>
         <b>Melee </b><span style="font-family: 'pfactions'; font-size: 150%; width:2em; text-align: center;">1</span> fangs, <b>Damage </b>]]>2d4 piercing plus 1d6 poison.</entry>
      </line>

      <heighten value="3rd">You instead gain 10 temporary HP, AC = 17 + your level, attack modifier +14, damage bonus +5, and Athletics +14.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">You can choose to make your battle form Large and your attacks have 10-foot reach (20-foot reach for the frog's tongue Strike); You must have enough space to expand into or the spell is lost. You instead gain 15 temporary HP, AC = 18 + your level, attack modifier +16, damage bonus +9, and Athletics +16.</heighten>
      <heighten value="5th">You can choose to make your battle form Huge and your attacks have 15-foot reach (30-foot reach for the frog's tongue Strike); You must have enough space to expand into or the spell is lost. You instead gain 20 temporary HP, AC = 18 + your level, attack modifier +18, damage bonus +7 and double the number of damage dice, and Athletics +20.</heighten>
   </rule>
</catalog>
