<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Potion</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1+</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Potion</trait> <trait>Vitality</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>(manipulate)</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A <i>healing potion</i> is a vial of ruby-red liquid that imparts a tingling sensation as the drinker's wounds heal rapidly. When you drink a <i>healing potion</i>, you regain the listed number of Hit Points.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Minor</type> <level>1</level>
         <price>4 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 1d8 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Lesser</type> <level>3</level>
         <price>12 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 2d8+5 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Moderate</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>50 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 3d8+10 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Studded Leather Armor</title>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <ac>+2</ac> <dexcap>+3</dexcap> <checkpenalty>-1</checkpenalty> <spdpenalty>-</spdpenalty>
      <strreq>+1</strreq> <bulk>1</bulk>
      <armorcat>Light</armorcat> <armorgroup>Leather</armorgroup>

      <line>This leather armor is reinforced with metal studs and sometimes small metal plates, providing most of the flexibility of leather armor with more robust protection.</line>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">+1 potency</rune> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>160 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto the armor</usage>

         <line>Magic wards deflect attacks. Increase the armor's item bonus to AC by 1. The armor can be etched with a property rune.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Steel Shield</title>
      <price>2 gp</price>
      <ac>+2</ac>
      <bulk>1</bulk> <hardness>5</hardness>
      <shieldhp>20</shieldhp> <shieldbt>10</shieldbt>

      <line>Though they come in a variety of shapes and sizes, the protection offered by wooden shields comes from the stoutness of their materials. While wooden shields are less expensive than steel shields, they break more easily.</line>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">minor reinforcing</rune> <level>4</level>
         <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>75 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto the shield</usage>

         <line><i>Reinforcing runes</i> make a shield significantly more durable, allowing it to effectively block more powerful attacks.</line>
         <line>A <i>minor reinforcing rune</i> increases the shield's Hardness by 3, Hit Points by 44, and its BT by 22 (maximum 8 Hardness, 64 HP, 32 BT).</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Clawed Bracers</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>7</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn bracers</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <price>325 gp</price>

      <line>Animal claws are woven into the thick leather of these bracers.</line>

      <block>
         <name activate="">Extend Claws</name> <action>1</action> <type>(manipulate, morph)</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per hour</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>The bracers fuse temporarily with your forearms, with the claws extending to your fingertips. You gain a climb Speed of 20 feet and a claw unarmed attack with the Agile and Finesse traits that deals 1d6 damage and is in the Brawling group. This lasts for 10 minutes or until you Dismiss it.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Magic Wand of Heal (rank 1)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Vitality</trait> <trait>Wand</trait>
      <price>60 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This baton is about a foot long and contains a 1st-rank <i>heal</i> that can be cast once per day. The golden end caps on this white wooden wand are adorned with ruby cabochons.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name>
         <type>Cast a Spell</type>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must have <i>heal</i> on your spell list</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>You Cast the Spell from the wand</part>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Overcharge</name>If the spell has been cast from the wand for the day, you can cast it one more time by overcharging the wand at the risk of destroying it. After you Cast the Spell, make a DC 10 flat check. On a success, the wand is broken and can be repaired. On a failure, the wand is destroyed.</part>
         <part>Activating a wand that has been overcharged for the day automatically destroys it, and no spell is cast.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Staff of Elemental Power</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>6</level>
      <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Staff</trait>
      <price>230 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>This staff is tapered at the base and carved into a gem-studded twist at the top. While wielding the staff, you gain a +2 circumstance bonus checks to identify elemental creatures.</line>
      <line list="Contained Spells">
         <entry name="Cantrip"><i>frostbite</i></entry>
         <entry name="1st"><i>breathe fire</i>, <i>pummeling rubble</i>, <i>thunderstike</i></entry>
         <entry name="2nd"><i>floating flame</i>, <i>resist energy</i></entry>
      </line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <type>Cast a Spell</type>
         <part><name>Effect</name>You expend a number of charges from the staff to cast a spell from its list.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ring of Discretion</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Visual</trait>
      <price>15 gp</price>
      <usage>worn</usage>

      <line>A <i>ring of discretion</i> magically conceals any armor and sheathed weapons you're wearing by either turning them invisible or creating the illusion of ordinary clothes. The ring doesn't change your appearance beyond concealing weapons and armor.</line>
      <line>As soon as you wield a weapon affected by the ring, the weapon becomes obvious to onlookers and is no longer affected until you sheathe the weapon for at least 1 minute. A creature can use the Seek action to examine you and disbelieve this illusion (DC 15), and it can attempt to do so without using an action each time it hits you with an attack.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cloak of Illusions</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>7+</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn cloak</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This cloak flows, covering and concealing the wearer's body. The cloak allows you to cast <i>figment</i> as an occult innate cantrip. Although naturally a dull gray, while invested the cloak picks up colors and patterns from its surroundings, granting an item bonus to Stealth checks.</line>
      <block>
         <name activate="">Draw Hood</name><action>2</action><type>(manipulate)</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>You draw the hood up and gain the effects the <i>invisibility</i> spell, with the spell's normal duration or until you pull the hood back down, whichever comes first.</part>
      </block>

      <variant>
         <type>Regular</type> <level>7</level>
         <price>360 gp</price>

         <line>+1 item bonus to Stealth.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Figment</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Subtle</trait>
      <tradition>arcane</tradition> <tradition>occult</tradition>
      <range>30 feet</range>
      <duration>sustained</duration>

      <line>You create a simple illusory sound or vision. A sound adds the <u>auditory</u> trait to the spell and the sound can't include intelligible words or elaborate music. A vision adds the <u>visual</u> trait and can be no larger than a 5-foot cube, and is clearly crude and undetailed if viewed from within 15 feet.</line>
      <line>When you Cast or Sustain the Spell, you can attempt to Create a Diversion with the illusion, gaining a +2 circumstance bonus to your Deception check. If the attempt fails against a creature, that creature disbelieves the figment.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Invisibility</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Subtle</trait>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>Illusions bend light around the target, rendering it Invisible. This makes it Undetected to all creatures, though the creatures can attempt to find the target, making it Hidden to them instead. If the target uses a hostile action, the spell ends after that hostile action is completed.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Adventurer's Pack</title>
      <price>1 gp, 5 sp</price>
      <bulk>1 in the backpack</bulk>

      <line>This is the starter kit for an adventurer, containing the essential items for exploration and survival.</line>
      <line>The pack contains the following items: backpack (containing the other goods), bedroll, 10 pieces of chalk, flint and steel, 50 feet of rope, 2 weeks' rations, soap, 5 torches, and a waterskin.</line>

      <variant>
         <container>Backpack</container>
         <bulk>-</bulk>

         <line>A backpack holds up to 4 Bulk of items, and the first 2 Bulk of these items don't count against your Bulk limits. If you're carrying or stowing the pack rather than wearing it, its Bulk is light instead of negligible and the Bulk reduction does not apply.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healer's Tools</title>
      <price>5 gp</price>
      <hands>2</hands> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>This kit of bandages, herbs, and suturing tools is necessary for Medicine checks to Administer First Aid, Treat Disease, Treat Poison, or Treat Wounds. If you wear your healer's tools, you can draw and replace them as part of the action that uses them.</line>
      <line toolkit=""/>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Repair Kit</title>
      <price>2 gp</price>
      <hands>2</hands> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>A repair kit allows you to perform simple repairs while traveling. It contains a portable anvil, tongs, woodworking tools, a whetstone, and oils for conditioning leather and wood. You can use a repair kit to Repair items using the Crafting skill. If you wear your repair kit, you can draw and replace them as part of the action to use them.</line>
      <line>You can use a set of tools with 1 hand if you're wearing them, or 2 if you're holding them. You can wear up to 2 Bulk of Tools.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
