<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Coerce</title>
      <type>Intimidation</type>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Linguistic</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>

      <line>With threats veiled or overt, you attempt to bully a creature into doing what you want. You must spend at least 1 minute of conversation with a creature you can see and that can either see or sense you. At the end of the conversation, attempt an Intimidation check against the target's Will DC, modified by circumstances the GM determines.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target gives you the information you seek or agrees to follow your directives so long as they aren't likely to harm the target in any way. The target continues to comply for an amount of time determined by the GM but not exceeding 1 day, at which point the target becomes unfriendly (if they weren't already unfriendly or hostile). However, the target is too scared of you to retaliate — at least in the short term.</critsuccess>
         <success>As critical success, but once the target becomes unfriendly, they might decide to act against you — for example, by reporting you to the authorities or assisting your enemies.</success>
         <fail>The target doesn't do what you say, and if they were not already unfriendly or hostile, they become unfriendly.</fail>
         <critfail>The target refuses to comply, becomes hostile if they weren't already, and can't be Coerced by you for at least 1 week.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Decipher Writing</title>
      <type>Varies</type>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Secret</trait>

      <line>You attempt to decipher complicated writing or literature on an obscure topic. This usually takes 1 minute per page of text, but might take longer (typically an hour per page for decrypting ciphers or the like). The text must be in a language you can read, though the GM might allow you to attempt to decipher text written in an unfamiliar language using Society instead.</line>
      <line>The DC is determined by the GM based on the state or complexity of the document. The GM might have you roll one check for a short text or a check for each section of a larger text.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You understand the true meaning of the text.</critsuccess>
         <success>You understand the true meaning of the text. If it was a coded document, you know the general meaning but might not have a word-for-word translation.</success>
         <fail>You can't understand the text and take a -2 circumstance penalty to further checks to decipher it.</fail>
         <critfail>You believe you understand the text on that page, but you have in fact misconstrued its message.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>You must be trained in the relevant skill to Decipher Writing:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Arcana - arcane theory</entry>
         <entry>Crafting - engineering plans, alchemical notations</entry>
         <entry>Lore - texts related to the subcategory</entry>
         <entry>Occultism - occult topics, including complex metaphysical systems, syncretic principles, weird philosophies, and incoherent ramblings</entry>
         <entry>Religion - writing of religious nature, including allegories, homilies, and proverbs</entry>
         <entry>Society - coded messages, text writtin in an incomplete or archaic form, or in some cases, text in a language you don't know</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gather Information</title>
      <type>Diplomacy</type>
      <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Secret</trait>

      <line>You canvass local markets, taverns, and gathering places in an attempt to lear about a specific individual or topic. The GM determines the DC of the check and the amount of time it takes (typically 2 hours, but sometimes more), along with any benefit you might be able to gain by spending coin on bribes, drinks, or gifts.</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>You collect information about the individual or topic. The GM determines the specifics.</success>
         <critfail>You collect incorrect information about the individual or topic.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Identify Magic</title>
      <type>Varies</type>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Secret</trait>

      <line>Once you discover that an item, location, or an ongoing effect is magical, you can spend 10 minutes to try identify the particular of its magic. If your attempt is interrupted, you must start over. The GM sets the DC for your check, typically based on the item, location or effect's level. Cursed or esoteric subjects usually have higher DCs or might even be impossible to identify using this activity alone. Heightening a spell doesn't increase the DC to identify it.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You learn all the attributes of the magic, including its name (for an effect), what it does, any means of activating it (for an item or location), and whether it is cursed.</critsuccess>
         <success>For an item or location, you get a sense of what it does and learn any means of activating it. For an ongoing effect (such as a spell with a duration), you learn the effects name and what it does. You can't try again in hopes of getting a critical success.</success>
         <fail>You fail to identify the magic and can't try again for 1 day.</fail>
         <critfail>You misindentify the magic as something else of the GM's choice.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Magical Traditions and Skills </b>]]></line>
      <line>Each magical tradition has a corresponding skill. You must have the trained proficiency rank in a skill to use it to Identify Magic. Something without a specific tradition, such as an item with the magical trait, can be identified using any of these skills.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Arcane tradition - Arcana skill</entry>
         <entry>Divine tradition - Religion skill</entry>
         <entry>Occult tradition - Occultism skill</entry>
         <entry>Primal tradition - Nature skill</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Impersonate</title>
      <type>Deception</type>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Secret</trait>

      <line>You create a disguise to pass yourself off as someone or something you are not. Assembling a convincing disguise takes 10 minutes and requires a disguise kit, but a simpler, quicker disguise might do the job if you're not trying to imitate a specific individual, at the GM's discretion.</line>
      <line>In most cases, creatures have a chance to detect your deception only if they use the Seek action to attempt Perception checks against your Deception DC. If you attempt to directly interact with someone while disguised, the GM rolls a secret Deception check for you against that creature's Perception DC instead. If you're disguised as a specific individual, the GM might give creatures you interact with a circumstance bonus based on how well they know the person you're imitating, or the GM might roll a secret Deception check even if you aren't directly interacting with others.</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>You trick the creature into thinking you're the person you're disguised as. You might have to attempt a new check if your behavior changes.</success>
         <fail>The creature can tell you're not who you claim to be.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature can tell you're not who you claim to be, and it recognizes you if it would know you without a disguise.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Learn a Spell</title>
      <type>Varies</type>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait>
      <requirement>You have a spellcasting class feature, and the spell you want to learn is on your magical tradition's spell list.</requirement>

      <line>You can gain access to a new spell of your tradition from someone who knows that spell or from magical writing like a spellbook or scroll. If you can cast spells of multiple traditions, you can Learn a Spell of any of those traditions, but you must use the corresponding skill to do so. For example, if you were a cleric with the bard multiclass archetype, you couldn't use Religion to add an occult spell to your bardic spell repertoire.</line>
      <line>To learn a spell, you must do the following:</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>Spend 1 hour per level of the spell, during which you must remain in conversation with a person who knows the spell or have the magical writing in your possession.</entry>
         <entry>Have materials with a price depending on the spell's level.</entry>
         <entry>Attempt a skill check for the skill corresponding to your tradition, with uncommon and rare spells generally having higher DCs.</entry>
      </line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You expend half the materials and learn the spell.</critsuccess>
         <success>You expend the materials and learn the spell.</success>
         <fail>You fail to learn the spell but can try again after you gain a level. The materials aren't expended.</fail>
         <critfail>As failure, plus you expend half the materials.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>If you have a spellbook, Learning a Spell lets you add the spell to your spellbook; if you prepare spells from a list, it's added to your list; if you have a spell repertoire, you can select it when you add or swap spells.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Material Price and Typical DC by Spell Level</b>]]></line>
      <line list="">
         <entry>1st-level or cantrip: 2 gp, DC 15</entry>
         <entry>2nd-level: 6 gp, DC 18</entry>
         <entry>3rd-level: 16 gp, DC 20</entry>
         <entry>4th-level: 36 gp, DC 23</entry>
         <entry>5th-level: 70 gp, DC 26</entry>
         <entry>6th-level: 140 gp, DC 28</entry>
         <entry>7th-level: 300 gp, DC 31</entry>
         <entry>8th-level: 650 gp, DC 34</entry>
         <entry>9th-level: 1,500 gp, DC 36</entry>
         <entry>10th-level: 7,000 gp, DC 41</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Make an Impression</title>
      <type>Diplomacy</type>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Linguistic</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>

      <line>With at least 1 minute of conversation, during which you engage in charismatic overtures, flatter, and other acts of goodwill, you seek to make a good impression on someone to make them temporarily agreeable. At the end of the conversation, attempt a Diplomacy check against the Will DC of one target, modified by any circumstance the GM sees fit. Good impressions (or bad impressions, on a critical failure) last for only the current social interaction unless the GM decides otherwise.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target's attitude toward you improves by two steps (such as from indifferent to helpful).</critsuccess>
         <success>The target's attitude toward you improves by one step (such as from indifferent to friendly).</success>
         <critfail>The target's attitude toward you decreases by one step (such as from indifferent to unfriendly).</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Refocus</title>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait>
      <requirement>You have a focus pool, and you have spent at least 1 Focus Point since you last regained any Focus Points.</requirement>

      <line>You spend 10 minutes performing deeds to restore your magical connection. This restores 1 Focus Point to your focus pool. The deeds you need to perform are specified in the class or ability that gives you your focus spells. These deeds can usually overlap with other tasks that relate to the source of your focus spells. For instance, a cleric with focus spells from a good deity can usually Refocus while tending the wounds of their allies, and a wizard of the illusionist school might be able to Refocus while attempting to Identify Magic of the illusion school.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Repair</title>
      <type>Crafting</type>
      <trait>Exploration</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <requirement>You have a repair kit.</requirement>

      <line>You spend 10 minutes attempting to fix a damaged item, placing the item on a stable surface and using the repair kit with both hands. The GM sets the DC, but it's usually about the same DC to Repair a given item as it is to Craft it in the first place. You can't Repair a destroyed item.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You restore 10 Hit Points to the item, plus an additional 10 Hit Points per proficiency rank you have in Crafting (a total of 20 HP if you're trained, 30 HP if you're an expert, 40 HP if you're a master, or 50 HP if you're legendary).</critsuccess>
         <success>You restore 5 Hit Points to the item, plus an additional 5 per proficiency rank you have in Crafting (for a total of 10 HP if you're trained, 15 HP if you're an expert, 20 HP if you're a master, or 25 HP if you're legendary).</success>
         <critfail>You deal 2d6 damage to the item. Apply the item's Hardness to this damage.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Search</title>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait>

      <line>You Seek meticulously for hidden doors, concealed hazards, and so on. You can usually make an educated guess as to which locations are best to check and move at half speed, but if you want to be thorough and guarantee you checked everything, you need to travel at a Speed of no more than 300 feet per minute, or 150 feet per minute to ensure you check everything before you walk into it. You can always move more slowly while Searching to cover the area more throughly, and the Expeditious Search feat increases these maximum Speeds. If you come across a secret door, item, or hazard while Searching, the GM will attempt a free secret check to Seek to see if you notice the hidden object or hazard. In locations with many objects to search, you have to stop and spend significantly longer to search thoroughly.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
