<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>1st-level General Feats</category>
      <title>Adopted Ancestry</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You're fully immersed in another ancestry's culture and traditions, whether born into them, earned through rite of passage, or bonded through a deep friendship or romance. Choose a common ancestry. You can select ancestry feats from the ancestry you chose, in addition to your character's own ancestry, as long as the ancestry feats don't require any physiological feature that you lack, as determined by the GM.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Armor Proficiency</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You become trained in light armor. If you already were trained in light armor, you gain training in medium armor. If you were trained in both, you become trained in heavy armor.</line>
      <special>You can select this feat more than once. Each time, you become trained in the next type of armor above.</special>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Breath Control</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You have incredible breath control, which grants you advantages when air is hazardous or sparse. You can hold you breath for 25 times as long as usual before suffocating. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to saving throws against inhaled threats, such as inhaled poisons, and if you roll a success on such a saving throw, you get a critical success instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Canny Acumen</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>Your avoidance or observation is beyond the ken of most in your profession. Choose Fortitude saves, Reflex saves, Will saves, or Perception. You become an expert in your choice.</line>
      <line>At 17th level, you become a master in your choice.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Diehard</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>It takes more to kill you than most. You die from the dying condition at dying 5, rather than dying 4.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fast Recovery</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>Your body quickly bounces from afflictions. You regain twice as many Hit Points from resting.</line>
      <line>Each time you succeed at a Fortitude save against an ongoing disease or poison, you reduce its stage by 2, or by 1 against a virulent disease or poison. Each critical success you achieve against an ongoing disease or poison reduces its stage by 3, or by 2 against a virulent disease or poison.</line>
      <line>In addition, you reduce the severity of your drained condition by 2 when you rest for a night instead of by 1.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Feather Step</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <prereq>Dexterity 14</prereq>

      <line>You step carefully and quickly. You can Step into difficult terrain.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fleet</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You move more quickly on foot. Your Speed increases by 5 feet.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Incredible Initiative</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You react more quickly than others can. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to initiative rolls.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ride</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>When you Command an Animal you're mounted on to take a move action (such as Stride), you automatically succeed instead of needing to attempt a check.</line>
      <line>Any animal you're mounted on acts on your turn, like a minion. If you Mount an animal in the middle of an encounter, it skips its next turn and then acts on your next turn.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shield Block</title>
      <action>R</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <trigger>While you have your shield raised, you would take damage from a physical attack</trigger>

      <line>You snap your shield in place to ward off a blow. Your shield prevents you from taking an amount of damage up to the shield's Hardness. You and the shield each take any remaining damage, possibly breaking or destroying the shield.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Toughness</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You can withstand more punishment than most before succumbing. Increase your maximum Hit Points by your level.</line>
      <line>The DC of recovery checks is equal to 9 + your dying condition value.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weapon Proficiency</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You become trained in all simple weapons. If you were already trained in all simple weapons, you become trained in all martial weapons. If you were already trained in all martial weapons, you become trained in one advanced weapon of your choice.</line>
      <special>You can select this feat more than once. Each time you do, you become trained in additional weapons as appropriate, following the above progression.</special>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <category>3rd-level General Feats</category>
      <title>Ancestral Paragon</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>Whether through instinct, study, or magic, you feel a deeper connection to your ancestry. You gain a 1st-level ancestry feat.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Improvised Repair</title> <action>3</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You are skilled at making quick fixes to damaged equipment, but your fixes aren't meant to last forever. You make a quick repair to a broken non-magical item in your possession. Until the item takes damage again, you can still use it as a shoddy item (-2 item penalty to attakcs, checks, or DCs using the item) of its type. This repair restores no Hit Points, so the item is easy to destroy.</line>
      <line>Once the item is Repaired normally such that it is no longer broken, it is also no longer shoddy.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Keen Follower</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>Your keen observation of your allies has made you better at following their lead. When using the Follow the Expert activity in exploration mode, you gain a +3 circustance bonus if the ally you are following is an expert and a +4 circumstance bonus if your ally is master.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Pick up the Pace</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <prereq>Constitution 14</prereq>

      <line>You lead by example and can help others push themselves beyond their normal limits. When Hustling in a group during exploration mode, your group can Hustle for up to 20 additional minutes, to a maximum of the emount of time the character with the highest Constitution modifier could Hustle alone.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Prescient Planner</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <cost>the Price of the chosen item</cost>
      <requirement>You haven't used this ability since the last time you were able to purchase goods.</requirement>

      <line>You regularly create convoluted plans and contingencies, using your resources to enact them. You take 1 minute to remove your backpack, then carefully remove an item you hadn't previously declared that you purchased — you intuited you would come to need the item and purchased it at the latest opportunity.</line>
      <line>The item must be a piece of adventuring gear and can't be a weapon, armor, alchemical item, magic item, or other treasure. It must be common with a level no highe than half your level, and its Bulk must be low enough that carrying it wouldn't have made you encumbered.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Skitter</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <prereq>Dexterity 16; Fleet feat</prereq>

      <line>You can scoot swiftly across the ground. You can Crawl up to half your Speed.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Thorough Search</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <prereq>expert in Perception</prereq>

      <line>You take your time to ensure you find everything. When Searching, you can take twice as long to search. If you do, you gain a +2 circu.</line>
      <line>Normally this means you Search at up to one quarter of your Speed to a maximum of 150 feet per minute to check everything, or 75 feet per minute to check everything before you walk into it.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Untrained Improvisation</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You're learned how to handle situations when you're out of your depths. Your proficiency bonus to untrained skill checks is equal to half your level instead of +0. If you're 7th level or higher, the bonus increases to your full level instead. This doesn't allow you to use the skill's trained actions.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
