<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Potion</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1+</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Potion</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>healing potion</i>]]> is a vial of ruby-red liquid that imparts a tingling sensation as the drinker's wounds heal rapidly. When you drink a <![CDATA[<i>healing potion</i>]]>, you regain the listed number of Hit Points.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Minor</type> <level>1</level>
         <price>4 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 1d8 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Lesser</type> <level>3</level>
         <price>12 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 2d8+5 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <type>Moderate</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>50 gp</price>

         <line>The potion restores 3d8+10 Hit Points.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hat of Disguise</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn headwear</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>
      <price>30 gp</price>

      <line>This ordinary-looking hat allows you to cloak yourself in illusions.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <type>1 minute (Interact)</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>The hat casts a 1st-level <![CDATA[<i>illusory disguise</i>]]> spell on you. While setting up the disguise, you can magically alter the hat to appear as a comb, ribbon, helm, or other piece of headwear.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Illusory Disguise</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Visual</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>

      <line>You create an illusion that cause you to appear as another creature of the same body shape, and with roughly similar height (within 6 inches) and weight (within 50 pounds), as yourself. The disguise is typically good enough to hide your identity, but not to impersonate a specific individual. The spell doesn't change your voice, scent, or mannerisms. You can change the appearance of your clothing and worn items, such as making your armor look like a dress. Held items are unaffected, and any worn item you remove returns to its true appearance.</line>
      <line>Casting <![CDATA[<i>illusory disguise</i>]]> counts as setting up a disguise for the Impersonate use of Deception; it ignores any circumstance penalties you might take for disguising yourself as a dissimilar creature, it gives you a +4 status bonus to Deception checks to prevent others from seeing through your disguise, and you add your level even if you're untrained. You can Dismiss this spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ring of Energy Resistance</title>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <type>Item</type> <level>6+</level>
      <usage>worn</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>

      <line>This ring grants you resistance against one type of energy damage: acid, cold, electricity, or sonic. Each ring is crafted to protect against a particular type of energy damage.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>acid resistance</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>245 gp</price>

         <line>This ring is adorned with an emerald. It grants resistance 5 acid.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Navigator's Star</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Tattoo</trait>
      <price>18 gp</price>
      <usage>tattooed on the body</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>

      <line>A star inked on the back of the hand, usually between the thumb and forefinger, keeps you on the right path.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <action>2</action> <type>Envision, Interact</type>
         <part><name>Effect</name>As you hold up your hand and align the star in view, you learn which direction you're facing.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hide Armor</title>
      <price>2 gp</price>
      <ac>03</ac> <dexcap>+2</dexcap> <checkpenalty>-2</checkpenalty> <spdpenalty>-5 ft.</spdpenalty>
      <strreq>14</strreq> <bulk>2</bulk>
      <armorcat>Medium</armorcat> <armorgroup>Leather</armorgroup>

      <line>A mix of furs, sturdy hide, and sometimes molded boiled leather, this armor provides protection due to its layers of leather, though its bulkiness slows the wearer down and decreases mobility.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dagger</title>
      <trait>Agile</trait> <trait>Finesse</trait> <trait>Thrown 10 ft.</trait> <trait>Versatile S</trait>
      <price>2 sp</price> <damage>1d4 P</damage>
      <hands>1</hands> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Simple</weapcat> <weapgroup>Knife</weapgroup>

      <line>This small, bladed weapon is held in one hand and used to stab a creature in close combat. It can also be thrown.</line>

      <traittext><name>Agile</name>The multiple attack penalty you take with this weapon on the second attack is -4 instead of -5, and -8 instead of -10 on the third and subsequent attacks in the turn.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Finesse</name>You can use your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier on attack rolls using this weapon. You still use your Strength modifier when calculating damage.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Thrown 10 ft.</name>You can throw this weapon as a ranged attack, and it is a ranged weapon when thrown. A thrown weapon adds your Strength modifier to damage, just like a melee weapon does.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Versatile S</name>A versatile weapon can be used to deal a different type of damage than that listed in the Damage entry. You choose the damage type each time you make an attack.</traittext>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gate Attenuator</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>
      <price>60 gp</price>

      <line><![CDATA[<i>gate attenuators</i>]]> are typically worn near the body's core and are shaped like portals or passageways, making literal the elemental gates kineticists posses within their bodies. The appearance can vary from a simple disk with a hole in the middle to a design matching a cirty gate of a particular settlement.</line>
      <line>If you're a kineticist, the attenuator grants you a +1 item bonus to your impulse attack modifier (but not your impulse DC).</line>
      <line>When you invest a <![CDATA[<i>gate attenuator</i>]]> (usually as part of your daily preparations), attune it to an element of your choice. Designs on the attenuator's surface transform to match that element, and the attenuator gains the element's trait until it's no longer invested or is attuned to a different element.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <action>2</action> <type>Envision</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>The <![CDATA[<i>gate attenuator</i>]]> casts a 1st-level spell, with an spell attack modifier of +7 and spell DC of 17. If you're a kineticist and the spell's element matches one of your kinetic elements, you can use your impulse attack modifier instead of the spell's attack modifier or your impulse DC instead of the spell DC. The spell corresponds to the element the item is attuned to, and it gains that element's trait if it doesn't already have it</part>
         <part linebreak=""><name>air</name><![CDATA[<i>gust of wind</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>earth</name><![CDATA[<i>pummeling rubble</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>fire</name><![CDATA[<i>dehydrate</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>metal</name><![CDATA[<i>thunderstrike</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>water</name><![CDATA[<i>snowball</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>wood</name><![CDATA[<i>flourishing flora</i>]]></part>
      </block>
   </rule>
</catalog>
