<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <rule>
      <title>Gate Attenuator</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>
      <price>60 gp</price>

      <line><![CDATA[<i>gate attenuators</i>]]> are typically worn near the body's core and are shaped like portals or passageways, making literal the elemental gates kineticists posses within their bodies. The appearance can vary from a simple disk with a hole in the middle to a design matching a cirty gate of a particular settlement.</line>
      <line>If you're a kineticist, the attenuator grants you a +1 item bonus to your impulse attack modifier (but not your impulse DC).</line>
      <line>When you invest a <![CDATA[<i>gate attenuator</i>]]> (usually as part of your daily preparations), attune it to an element of your choice. Designs on the attenuator's surface transform to match that element, and the attenuator gains the element's trait until it's no longer invested or is attuned to a different element.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <action>2</action> <type>Envision</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>The <![CDATA[<i>gate attenuator</i>]]> casts a 1st-level spell, with an spell attack modifier of +7 and spell DC of 17. If you're a kineticist and the spell's element matches one of your kinetic elements, you can use your impulse attack modifier instead of the spell's attack modifier or your impulse DC instead of the spell DC. The spell corresponds to the element the item is attuned to, and it gains that element's trait if it doesn't already have it</part>
         <part linebreak=""><name>air</name><![CDATA[<i>gust of wind</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>earth</name><![CDATA[<i>pummeling rubble</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>fire</name><![CDATA[<i>dehydrate</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>metal</name><![CDATA[<i>thunderstrike</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>water</name><![CDATA[<i>snowball</i>]]></part>
         <part><name>wood</name><![CDATA[<i>flourishing flora</i>]]></part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dehydrate</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>5-foot burst</area>
      <save>Fortitude (see text)</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You stir the inner fire of all things within the area, driving out moisture. All creatures in the area take 1d6 persistent fire damage with a basic Fortitude save; creatures with the water or plant traits get a result one degree of success worse than they rolled. The spell ends for a creature when its persistent damage ends.</line>
      <line>A creature affected by <![CDATA[<i>dehydrate</i>]]> attempts an additional Fortitude save at the end of each of its turns, before rolling to recover from the persistent damage. It can forgo this additional save if it consumed water or similar hydrating liquid within the last round (typically, drinking requires a single action).</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>The creature takes no additional effect.</success>
         <fail>The creature is enfeebled 1 until the end of its next turn.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is enfeebled 2 until the end of its next turn.</critfail>
      </line>
      <!-- <heighten value="+2">The range increases by 10 feet, the burst increases by 5 feet, and the persistent fire damage increases by 3d6.</heighten> -->
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Flourishing Flora</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Wood</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>5-foot burst</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>Plants rapidly grow up from the ground. All creatures in the target area take 2d4 damage. The type of damage depends on the type of plant you choose to grow. On a critical failure, targets experience additional effects, also depending on what you choose to grow. The type of plant and its effects are chosen when you Cast the Spell.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Cacti">Piercing damage, and 1 persistent bleed damage on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Flowers">Poison damage, and dazzled for 2 rounds on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Fruits">Bludgeoning damage, and clumsy 1 for 2 rounds on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Roots">Bludgeoning damage, and the affected creatures fall prone on a critical failure.</entry>
      </line>
      <!-- <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4, and the persistent bleed damage from cacti increases by 1.</heighten> -->
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gust of Wind</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>60-foot line.</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save> <duration>until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>A violent wind issues forth from your palm, blowing from the point where you are when you cast the spell to the line's opposite end. The wind extinguishes small non-magical fires, disperses fog and mist, blows objects of light Bulk or less around, and pushes larger objects. Large or smaller creatures in the area must attempt a Fortitude save. Large or smaller creatures that later move into the gust must attempt the save when entering.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature can't move against the wind.</success>
         <fail>The creature is knocked prone. If it was flying, it suffers the effects of critical failure instead.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is pushed 30 feet in the wind's direction, knocked prone, and takes 2d6 bludgeoning damage.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Pummeling Rubble</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>A spray of heavy rocks flies through the air in front of you. The rubble deals 2d4 bludgeoning damage to each creature in the area. Each creature must attempt a Reflex save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage and is pushed 5 feet away from you.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you.</critfail>
      </line>
      <!-- <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten> -->
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Snowball</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You throw a magically propelled and chilled ball of dense snow. The target takes 2d4 cold damage and potentially other effects, depending on the result of your ranged spell attack roll.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and a -10-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage and a -5-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</success>
         <fail>No effect.</fail>
      </line>
      <!-- <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten> -->
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Thunderstrike</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Sonic</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>You call down a tendril of lightning that cracks with thunder, dealing 1d12 electricity damage and 1d4 sonic damage to the target with a basic Reflex save. A target wearing metal armor or made of metal takes a -1 circumstance penalty to its save and, if damaged by the spell, is clumsy 1 for 1 round.</line>
      <!-- <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d12 electricity and 1d4 sonic.</heighten> -->
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tiefling Heritage</title>
      <uncommon/>

      <line>You descend from fiends or bear the mark of the fiendish realms, manifesting as some unusual feature that belies your heritage, such as horns or a tail. You gain the tiefling trait, in addition to the traits from your ancestry. You also gain low-light vision, or you gain darkvision if your ancestry already has low-light vision. You can choose from the tiefling feats and feats from your ancestry whenever you gain an ancestry feat.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Low-Light Vision</title>

      <line>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the concealed condition due to dim light.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hellspawn</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Lineage</trait> <trait>Tiefling</trait>

      <line>Your lineage descends from devils, the conniving schemers of Hell's malevolent hierarchy. You're as skilled at noticing lies and twisted words as you are at constructing them.</line>
      <line>You are trained in Deception and Legal Lore. If you were already trained in Deception (from your background or class, for example), you instead become trained in a skill of your choice. You also gain the Lie to Me skill feat.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Lie to Me</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Deception</prereq>

      <line>You can use Deception to weave traps to trip up anyone trying to deceive you. If you can engage in conversation with someone trying to Lie to you, use your Deception DC if it's higher than your Perception DC to determine whether they succeed. This doesn't apply if you don't have a back-and-forth dialogue, such as when someone attempts to Lie during a long speech.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cat Fall</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Acrobatics</prereq>

      <line>Your catlike aerial acrobatics allow you to cushion your falls. Treat falls as 10 feet shorter.</line>
      <line>If you're an expert in Acrobatics, treat falls as 25 feet shorter. If you're a master in Acrobatics, treat them as 50 feet shorter. If you're legendary in Acrobatics, you always land on your feet and down take damage, regardless of the distance of the fall.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Rolling Landing</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>Cat Fall; trained in Acrobatics</prereq>

      <line>You land with quick rolls that help you keep your momentum. If you fall and don't take damage (usually due to treating the fall as s shorter distance), you can use your reaction to immediately enter a short roll when you land and Step.</line>
      <line>If you are an expert in Acrobatics, you can use your reaction to Step, or to Stride up to half your Speed. If you're a master in Acrobatics, you can use your reaction to Step, or to Stride your full speed. If you're legendary in Acrobatics, you don't trigger reactions triggered by movement when you Stride this way.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Steady Balance</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Acrobatics</prereq>

      <line>You can keep your balance easily, even in adverse conditions. Whenever you roll a success using the Balance action, you get a critical success instead. You're not flat-footed while attempting to Balance on a narrow surface and uneven ground.</line>
      <line>Thanks to your incredible balance, you can attempt an Acrobatics check instead of a Reflex save to Grab and Edge.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Grab an Edge</title> <action>R</action>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <trigger>You fall from or past an edge or handhold</trigger>
      <requirement>Your hands are not tied behind your back or otherwise restrained</requirement>

      <line>When you fall off or past an edge or other handhold, you can try to grab it, potentially stopping your fall. You must succeed at a Reflex save, usually at the Climb DC. If you grab the edge or handhold, you can then Climb up using Athletics.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You grab the edge or handhold, whether or not you have a hand free, typically by using a suitable held item to catch yourself (catching a battle axe on a ledge, for example). You still take damage from the distance fallen so far, but you treat the fall as though it were 30 feet shorter.</critsuccess>
         <success>If you have at least one hand free, you grab the edge or handhold, stopping your fall. You still take damage from the distance fallen so far, but you treat the fall as though it were 20 feet shorter. If you have no hands free, you continue to fall as if you had failed the check.</success>
         <critfail>You continue to fall, and if you've fallen 20 feet or more before you use this reaction, take 10 bludgeoning damage from the impact for every 20 feet fallen.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Incredible Initiative</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You react more quickly than others can. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to initiative rolls.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Navigator's Star</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Tattoo</trait>
      <price>18 gp</price>
      <usage>tattooed on the body</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>

      <line>A star inked on the back of the hand, usually between the thumb and forefinger, keeps you on the right path.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <action>2</action> <type>Envision, Interact</type>
         <part><name>Effect</name>As you hold up your hand and align the star in view, you learn which direction you're facing.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hat of Disguise</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn headwear</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>
      <price>30 gp</price>

      <line>This ordinary-looking hat allows you to cloak yourself in illusions.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <type>1 minute (Interact)</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>The hat casts a 1st-level <![CDATA[<i>illusory disguise</i>]]> spell on you. While setting up the disguise, you can magically alter the hat to appear as a comb, ribbon, helm, or other piece of headwear.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Illusory Disguise</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Visual</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>

      <line>You create an illusion that cause you to appear as another creature of the same body shape, and with roughly similar height (within 6 inches) and weight (within 50 pounds), as yourself. The disguise is typically good enough to hide your identity, but not to impersonate a specific individual. The spell doesn't change your voice, scent, or mannerisms. You can change the appearance of your clothing and worn items, such as making your armor look like a dress. Held items are unaffected, and any worn item you remove returns to its true appearance.</line>
      <line>Casting <![CDATA[<i>illusory disguise</i>]]> counts as setting up a disguise for the Impersonate use of Deception; it ignores any circumstance penalties you might take for disguising yourself as a dissimilar creature, it gives you a +4 status bonus to Deception checks to prevent others from seeing through your disguise, and you add your level even if you're untrained. You can Dismiss this spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Kinetic Gate</title>

      <line>As a kineticist, you've awakened or opened a kinetic gate, a supernatural conduit within your body that can channel elemental forces straight from the elemental planes.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Dual Gate</b>]]></line>
      <line>Your kinetic gate is a harmonious conduit between two planes, allowing you to combine their elements to give you a versatile set of abilities.</line>
      <line>You chose Air and Fire for your kinetic elements, and gained one 1st-level impulse feat for each element.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Kinetic Aura</title>

      <line>Through your kinetic gate, elements flow from an elemental plane to orbit your person. The form and appearance of this kinetic aura are unique to you. Examples include a chaotic wind orbiting the body, fragments of floating gravel, colorful wicks of flame, stars of raw metal always changing shape, floating snowflakes, or splinters dancing in the air. If you can channel more than one element, pieces of all your kinetic elements appear in the aura.</line>
      <line>You have the Channel Elements action, which lets you activate your kinetic aura</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Impulse</title>
      <type>Trait</type>

      <line>The primary magical actions kineticists use are called impulses. You can use an impulse only if your kinetic aura is active and channeling that element, and only if you have a hand free to shape the elemental flow. The impulse trait means the action has the concentrate trait unless another ability changes it.</line>
      <line>If an impulse allows you to choose an element, you can choose any element you're channeling, and the impulse gains that element's trait.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Overflow</title>
      <type>Trait</type>

      <line>Powerful impulses temporarily overdraw the energy of your kinetic gate. When you use an impulse that has the overflow trait, your kinetic aura deactivates until you revitalize it (typically with the Channel Element action). Extinguishing your element this severy is taxing, and consequentially, you can use only one overflow impulse per round, even if you reactivate your kinetic gate.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Channel Elements</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <trait>Aura</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <requirement>Your kinetic gate isn't active</requirement>

      <line>You tap into your kinetic gate to make elements flow around your. Your kinetic aura activates, and as part of this action, you can use a 1-action Elemental Blast or a 1-action stance impulse.</line>
      <line>Your kinetic aura is a 10-foot emanation where pieces of your kinetic element (or all your kinetic elements, if you can channel more than one) flow around you. The kinetic aura can't damage anything or affect or affect the environment around you unless another ability allows it. Channel Elements has the traits of all your kinetic elements.</line>
      <line>Your kinetic aura automatically deactivates if your knocked out, you use an impulse with the overflow trait, or you Dismiss the aura. Though you can't use new impulses while your kinetic aura is deactivated, ones you already used remain, and you can still Sustain any that can be sustained. Stance impulses are linked to your kinetic aura and when the aura deactivates.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Impulses</title>

      <line>An impulse is a special type of magical action available to kineticists, allowing them to wield or shape their element into diverse and powerful forms. To wield an element, you must have your kinetic aura active and have a free hand, as described in the impulse trait. You automatically gain the Elemental Blast and Base Kinesis impulses, and your kinetic gate selection gives you additional impulse feats. You can select more impulse feats with kineticist class feats, and at higher levels, you'll automatically get more with the Gate's Threshold class feature. You can select an impulse feat only if it matches one of your kinetic elements.</line>
      <line>Impulses are magical, and though they aren't spells, some things that affect spells also affect impulses. Abilities that restrict you from casting spells (such as being polymorphed into a battle form) or protect against spells (such as a spell that protects against other spells or a creature's bonus to saves against spells) also apply to impulses.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Impulse Levels </b>]]> Any impulse you use is the same level you are. For instance, if you're 5th level, your Elemental Blast would be 5th level (and its counteract rank would be 3rd rank), even though you gained the action at 1st level.</line>
      <line>Similar to spells, many impulses get more powerful as you increase in level. In these cases, the impulse ends with one or more "Level" entries. This either lists the levels at which the impulse gets an upgrade or has an entry with a plus sign that describes a benefit that increases on a regular basis. For instance, a 1st-level impulse with a "Level (+4)" entry would get stronger at 5th, 9th, 13th, and 17th levels.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Impulse Attacks and DCs </b>]]> An impulse that requires a saving throw uses your kineticist class DC. Some of your impulses require you to attempt an <![CDATA[<i>impulse attack roll</i>]]> to see how effective they are. Your impulse attack roll uses the same proficiency and attribute modifier as your kineticist class DC. Like a spell attack modifier, your impulse attack modifier uses the following formule: d20 roll + attribute modifier + proficiency bonus + other bonuses + penalties. This means your impulse attack roll is typically 10 lower than your class DC. The drained condition can reduce your impulse attack rolls and class DC. You can acquire a <![CDATA[<i>gate attenuator</i>]]> to gain a bonus to your impulse attack modifier.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Base Kinesis</title>
      <type>Level</type> <level>1</level>
      <action>2</action>
      <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range>

      <line>It's trivial for you to create some of your element or alter a portion of it that already exists. Choose one of your kinetic elements to affect. The Bulk of the target must be negligible or light. The GM determines what Bulk the element is. You can't affect an element that's magical, secured in place (line a stone mortared in a wall), or attended by a creature unwilling to let you.</line>
      <line>Choose one  of the following options, though the GM might allow you to make similar small alterations. Base Kinesis can't deal damage or cause conditions unless otherwise noted.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Generate">You bring an ordinary, non-magical piece of the chosen element from its elemental plane. The element can be used for any of its normal uses. For example, air can be breathed by an air-breathing creature, and fire casts light and can ignite flammable substances.</entry>
         <entry name="Move">Move an existing piece of the element up to 20 feet in any direction. If you bring it into your space, you can catch it in an open hand. You can Sustain the impulse to keep moving the element.</entry>
         <entry name="Suppress">You destroy an existing piece of element, such as snuffing out a flame or evaporating water from a cup. This affects only natural forms of the element, not durable, crafted goods like a stone statue, metal lock, or a wooden door.</entry>
      </line>

      <levels value="+4">The range increases by 15 feet, and the maximum Bulk increases by 1 (allowing Bulk 1 at 5th level).</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Elemental Blast</title>
      <type>Level</type> <level>1</level>
      <action or="2">1</action>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>

      <line>With a wave of your hand, you collect elemental matter from your aura and swing or hurl it. Choose one of your kinetic elements and a damage type listed for that element, then make a melee or ranged impulse attack against the AC of one creature. Add your Strength modifier to the damage roll for a melee Elemental Blast. If you make a 2-action Elemental Blast, you gain a status bonus to the damage roll equal to your Constitution modifier.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
      <line>The element determines the damage die, damage type, and range (for a ranged blast). A damage type other than a physical damage type adds its trait to the blast.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Air">1d6 electricity or slashing, 60 feet</entry>
         <entry name="Fire">1d6 fire, 60 feet</entry>
      </line>

      <levels value="+4">The damage increases by one die.</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Aerial Boomerang</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>

      <line>A blade of shearing wind races away from you in a 60-foot line. Each creature in the area takes 2d4 slashing damage with a basic Reflex save against your class DC. In the final square of the line, the boomerang whirls in place until the end of your next turn. Any creature that ends its turn in that square has to save against the boomerang.</line>
      <line>On your next turn, you can use a single action, which has the concentrate trait, to return the boomerang to you. It returns in a line from its squareto your current location, with the same effect as the initial line, then the impulse ends. You must have line of effect to the boomerang and be within 60 feet of it.</line>
      <levels value="+2">The damage increases by 1d4.</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Extract Elements</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Level</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>A creature that has a trait matching one of your kinetic elements or is made of one of your kinetic elements</targets>

      <line>You extract elemental matter from a creature's body to weaken it and take its power for your own. The target takes 2d4 damage (with no damage type) and becomes susceptible to your impulses, depending on its Fortitude save against your class DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage, and you add some of its elemental matter to your kinetic aura. Your impulses bypass any immunity the creature has to their elemental tait or traits, and the target takes a -1 circumstance penalty to its saves and AC against your impulses. If the target normally has a resistance that would apply to damage from one of your impulses, ignore that resistance; if it normally would be immune to that damage type, it instead has resistance equal to its level to damage from the impulse. You can't target a creature with your Extract Element if elemental matter you extracted from it is already in your kinetic aura. These effects last for 5 minutes or until your kinetic aura ends, whichever comes first.</success>
         <fail>As success, but the creature takes full damage.</fail>
         <critfail>As failure, but the creature takes double damage.</critfail>
      </line>
      <levels value="+2">The damage increases by 1d4.</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Flying Flame</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>

      <line>A Tiny shape of flame appears, taking a form of your choice -such as a bird, arrow, or a simple sphere. It Flies from you up to 30 feet in a path you choose. Each creature it passes through takes 1d6 fire damage with a basic Reflex save against your class DC. A creature takes this damage only once, even if the flame passes through it multiple times.</line>
      <levels value="+2">The damage increases by 1d6.</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Burning Jet</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>

      <line>A condensed burst of flame shoots behind you, propelling you forward with its sheer force. Stride up to 40 feet in a straight line. Movement from this impulse ignores difficult terrain and doesn't trigger reactions.</line>
      <levels value="6th">The maximum distance of the Stride is 60 feet. You can choose to Leap up to 40 feet in any direction instead of Striding. If you're in the air at the end of this Leap, you fall normally.</levels>
      <levels value="10th">As 6th level, but you hover briefly after leaping into the air. If you Leap, you don't fall until the end of your next turn. If you use Burning Jet again on a subsequent turn, you remain airborne.</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Lightning Dash</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Move</trait> <trait>Overflow</trait> <trait>Polymorph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>

      <line>For an instant, you transform yourself into a being of pure lightning and fly forward, shocking anyone in your way. You propel yourself in a 30-foot line. You can move through creatures during this movement, and this movement doesn't trigger reactions that are triggered by movement.</line>
      <line>Each creature you move through takes 2d12 electricity damage with a basic Reflex save against your class DC. You return to your normal form in the final square of the line. If you're in the air, you fall unless you have a fly Speed.</line>
      <levels value="+3">The length of the line increases by 5 feet, and the damage increases by 1d12.</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Whisper on the Wind</title> <action>1</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Impulse</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Linguistic</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>

      <line>You speak in a whisper, a soft wind carrying your words far away. This has the effect of the <![CDATA[<i>message</i>]]> spell with a range of 500 feet, and it can target only a creature surrounded by air. If you start your message with the target's name, you and the target don't need to be able to see each other, nor do you need line of effect.</line>
      <levels value="4th">The range is 1 mile.</levels>
      <levels value="14th">The range is planetary plus the Plane of Air.</levels>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Message</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Linguistic</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
      <cast action="1">verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>see below</duration>

      <line>You mouth words quietly, but instead of coming out of your mouth, they're transferred directly to the ears of the target. While others can't hear your words any better than if you normally mouthed them, the target can hear your words as if they were standing next to you. The target can give a brief response as a reaction, or as a free action on their next turn if they wish, but they must be able to see you and be within range to do so. If they respond, their response is delivered directly in your ear, just like the original message.</line>
      <!-- <heighten value="3rd">The spell's range increases to 500 feet.</heighten> -->
   </rule>
</catalog>
