<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Tiefling Heritage</title>
      <uncommon/>

      <line>You descend from fiends or bear the mark of the fiendish realms, manifesting as some unusual feature that belies your heritage, such as horns or a tail. You gain the <u>tiefling</u> trait, in addition to the traits from your ancestry. You also gain low-light vision, or you gain darkvision if your ancestry already has low-light vision. You can choose from the tiefling feats and feats from your ancestry whenever you gain an ancestry feat.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Low-Light Vision</title>

      <line>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the concealed condition due to dim light.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hellspawn</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Lineage</trait> <trait>Tiefling</trait>

      <line>Your lineage descends from devils, the conniving schemers of Hell's malevolent hierarchy. You're as skilled at noticing lies and twisted words as you are at constructing them.</line>
      <line>You are trained in Deception and Legal Lore. If you were already trained in Deception (from your background or class, for example), you instead become trained in a skill of your choice. You also gain the Lie to Me skill feat.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Lie to Me</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Deception</prereq>

      <line>You can use Deception to weave traps to trip up anyone trying to deceive you. If you can engage in conversation with someone trying to Lie to you, use your Deception DC if it's higher than your Perception DC to determine whether they succeed. This doesn't apply if you don't have a back-and-forth dialogue, such as when someone attempts to Lie during a long speech.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fiendish Resistance</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Tiefling</trait>

      <line>Your connection to your fiendish forebears has granted you one of their resistances as well. Choose one of the following energy types: acid, cold, electricity, fire, or sonic. You gain resistance 5 to that damage type.</line>
      <line>Though you can choose any of these, the damage type typically matches a fiend associated with your bloodline. For instance, a hellspawn might choose resistance to fire, or a pitborn with a vrock ancestor might choose resistance to electricity.</line>
      <line name="Choice">You chose fire.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cat Fall</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Acrobatics</prereq>

      <line>Your catlike aerial acrobatics allow you to cushion your falls. Treat falls as 10 feet shorter.</line>
      <line>If you're an expert in Acrobatics, treat falls as 25 feet shorter. If you're a master in Acrobatics, treat them as 50 feet shorter. If you're legendary in Acrobatics, you always land on your feet and down take damage, regardless of the distance of the fall.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Rolling Landing</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>Cat Fall; trained in Acrobatics</prereq>

      <line>You land with quick rolls that help you keep your momentum. If you fall and don't take damage (usually due to treating the fall as s shorter distance), you can use your reaction to immediately enter a short roll when you land and Step.</line>
      <line>If you are an expert in Acrobatics, you can use your reaction to Step, or to Stride up to half your Speed. If you're a master in Acrobatics, you can use your reaction to Step, or to Stride your full speed. If you're legendary in Acrobatics, you don't trigger reactions triggered by movement when you Stride this way.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Steady Balance</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Acrobatics</prereq>

      <line>You can keep your balance easily, even in adverse conditions. Whenever you roll a success using the Balance action, you get a critical success instead. You're not flat-footed while attempting to Balance on a narrow surface and uneven ground.</line>
      <line>Thanks to your incredible balance, you can attempt an Acrobatics check instead of a Reflex save to Grab and Edge.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Grab an Edge</title> <action>R</action>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <trigger>You fall from or past an edge or handhold</trigger>
      <requirement>Your hands are not tied behind your back or otherwise restrained</requirement>

      <line>When you fall off or past an edge or other handhold, you can try to grab it, potentially stopping your fall. You must succeed at a Reflex save, usually at the Climb DC. If you grab the edge or handhold, you can then Climb up using Athletics.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You grab the edge or handhold, whether or not you have a hand free, typically by using a suitable held item to catch yourself (catching a battle axe on a ledge, for example). You still take damage from the distance fallen so far, but you treat the fall as though it were 30 feet shorter.</critsuccess>
         <success>If you have at least one hand free, you grab the edge or handhold, stopping your fall. You still take damage from the distance fallen so far, but you treat the fall as though it were 20 feet shorter. If you have no hands free, you continue to fall as if you had failed the check.</success>
         <critfail>You continue to fall, and if you've fallen 20 feet or more before you use this reaction, take 10 bludgeoning damage from the impact for every 20 feet fallen.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Incredible Initiative</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You react more quickly than others can. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to initiative rolls.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Feather Step</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>
      <prerequisite>Dexterity +2</prerequisite>

      <line>You step carefully and quickly. You can Step into difficult terrain.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Kinetic Gate</title>

      <line>As a kineticist, you've awakened or opened a kinetic gate, a supernatural conduit within your body that can channel elemental forces straight from the elemental planes.</line>
      <line name="Dual Gate">Your kinetic gate is a harmonious conduit between two planes, allowing you to combine their elements to give you a versatile set of abilities.</line>
      <line>You chose Air and Fire for your kinetic elements, and gained one 1st-level impulse feat for each element.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Kinetic Aura</title>

      <line>Through your kinetic gate, elements flow from an elemental plane to orbit your person. The form and appearance of this kinetic aura are unique to you. Examples include a chaotic wind orbiting the body, fragments of floating gravel, colorful wicks of flame, stars of raw metal always changing shape, floating snowflakes, or splinters dancing in the air. If you can channel more than one element, pieces of all your kinetic elements appear in the aura.</line>
      <line>You have the Channel Elements action, which lets you activate your kinetic aura</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Impulse</trait>

      <line>The primary magical actions kineticists use are called impulses. You can use an impulse only if your kinetic aura is active and channeling that element, and only if you have a hand free to shape the elemental flow. The <u>impulse</u> trait means the action has the <u>concentrate</u> trait unless another ability changes it.</line>
      <line>If an <u>impulse</u> allows you to choose an element, you can choose any element you're channeling, and the impulse gains that element's trait.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <trait>Overflow</trait>

      <line>Powerful impulses temporarily overdraw the energy of your kinetic gate. When you use an <u>impulse</u> that has the <u>overflow</u> trait, your kinetic aura deactivates until you revitalize it (typically with the Channel Element action). Extinguishing your element this severely is taxing, and consequentially, you can use only one <u>overflow impulse</u> per round, even if you reactivate your kinetic gate.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Channel Elements</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Aura</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Kineticist</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <requirement>Your kinetic gate isn't active</requirement>

      <line>You tap into your kinetic gate to make elements flow around your. Your kinetic aura activates, and as part of this action, you can use a 1-action Elemental Blast or a 1-action <u>stance impulse</u>.</line>
      <line>Your kinetic aura is a 10-foot emanation where pieces of your kinetic element (or all your kinetic elements, if you can channel more than one) flow around you. The kinetic aura can't damage anything or affect or affect the environment around you unless another ability allows it. Channel Elements has the traits of all your kinetic elements.</line>
      <line>Your kinetic aura automatically deactivates if you're knocked out, you use an impulse with the overflow trait, or you Dismiss the aura. Though you can't use new impulses while your kinetic aura is deactivated, ones you already used remain, and you can still Sustain any that can be sustained. Stance impulses are linked to your kinetic aura and when the aura deactivates.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Impulses</title>

      <line>An impulse is a special type of magical action available to kineticists, allowing them to wield or shape their element into diverse and powerful forms. To wield an element, you must have your kinetic aura active and have a free hand, as described in the impulse trait. You automatically gain the Elemental Blast and Base Kinesis impulses, and your kinetic gate selection gives you additional impulse feats. You can select more impulse feats with kineticist class feats, and at higher levels, you'll automatically get more with the Gate's Threshold class feature. You can select an impulse feat only if it matches one of your kinetic elements.</line>
      <line>Impulses are magical, and though they aren't spells, some things that affect spells also affect impulses. Abilities that restrict you from casting spells (such as being polymorphed into a battle form) or protect against spells (such as a spell that protects against other spells or a creature's bonus to saves against spells) also apply to impulses.</line>
      <line name="Impulse Levels"> Any impulse you use is the same level you are. For instance, if you're 5th level, your Elemental Blast would be 5th level (and its counteract rank would be 3rd rank), even though you gained the action at 1st level.</line>
      <line>Similar to spells, many impulses get more powerful as you increase in level. In these cases, the impulse ends with one or more "Level" entries. This either lists the levels at which the impulse gets an upgrade or has an entry with a plus sign that describes a benefit that increases on a regular basis. For instance, a 1st-level impulse with a "Level (+4)" entry would get stronger at 5th, 9th, 13th, and 17th levels.</line>
      <line name="Impulse Attacks and DCs"> An impulse that requires a saving throw uses your kineticist class DC. Some of your impulses require you to attempt an <i>impulse attack roll</i> to see how effective they are. Your impulse attack roll uses the same proficiency and attribute modifier as your kineticist class DC. Like a spell attack modifier, your impulse attack modifier uses the following formule: d20 roll + attribute modifier + proficiency bonus + other bonuses + penalties. This means your impulse attack roll is typically 10 lower than your class DC. The drained condition can reduce your impulse attack rolls and class DC. You can acquire a <i>gate attenuator</i> to gain a bonus to your impulse attack modifier.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gate's Threshold</title>

      <line>You reach a new milestone in your odyssey to become in tune with your kinetic gate and must decide how to expand the gate's power. At 5th levle and every 4 levels thereafter, you can choose to either expand the portal or fork the path.</line>
      <line name="5th level">You chose to expand the fire portal. You gained the Blazing Wave fire impulse, and the Fire Impulse Junction.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Impulse Junction</title>

      <line>An impulse junction is a benefit that occurs when you use an impulse of the chosen element that takes 2 actions or more. This happens before the other effects of the impulse, unless otherwise noted. You can gain only one impulse junction per round.</line>

      <variant>
         <element>Fire</element>
         <line>Increase the damage die size of fire damage dealt by the impulse by one step, such as from d6 to d8.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Kinetic Durability</title>
      <line>The sustenance of your inner gate counters harm that would come to your body. When you roll a success on a Fortitude save, you get a critical success instead.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
