<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Low-Light Vision</title>

      <line>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the concealed condition due to dim light.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sensate Gnome</title>

      <line>You see all colors as brighter, hear all sounds as richer, and especially smell all scents with incredible detail. You gain a special sense: imprecise scent with a range of 30 feet. This means you can use your sense of smell to determine the exact location of a creature. The GM will usually double the range if you're downwind from the creature or halve the range if you're upwind.</line>
      <line>In addition, you gain a +2 circumstance bonus to Perception checks whenever you're trying to locate an undetected creature that is within the range of your scent.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gnome Weapon Familiarity</title>
      <type>Feat</type>
      <level>1</level>
      <trait>Gnome</trait>

      <line>You favor unusual weapons tied to your people, such as blades with curved and peculiar shapes. You are trained with the glaive and and kukri.</line>
      <line>In addition, you gain access to kukris and all uncommon gnome weapons. For the purpose of determining your proficiency, martial gnome weapons are simple weapons and advanced gnome weapons are martial weapons.</line>
   </rule>

  <rule>
    <title>Stubborn</title>
    <line>You don't like being told what to do, and you don't give up. Your proficiency rank for Will saves increases to expert.</line>
    <line>When you fail, but don't critically fail, a Will save against an effect that would give you the controlled condition, you can attempt a second save against the effect at the start of your next turn. On a successful second save, the controlled condition ends, though any other effects remain. As normal, failing this second save doesn't allow you to attempt a third save on the subsequent turn.</line>
  </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Quick Repair</title>
      <type>Feat</type>
      <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Crafting</prereq>

      <line>You take 1 minute to Repair an item. If you're a master in Crafting, it takes 3 actions. If you're legendary, it takes 1 action.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Intimidating Glare</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Intimidation</prereq>

      <line>You can Demoralize with a mere glare. When you do, Demoralize loses the auditory trait and gains the visual trait, and you don't take a penalty if the creature doesn't understand your language.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Demoralize</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <type>Intimidation</type>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>

      <line>With a sudden shout, a well-timed taunt, or a cutting putdown, you can shake an enemy's resolve.</line>
      <line>Choose a creature within 30 feet of you who you're aware of. Attempt an Intimidation check against that target's Will DC. If the target does not understand the language you are speaking, or you're not speaking a language, you take a -4 circumstance penalty to the check. Regardless of your result, the target is temporarily immune to your attempts to Demoralize it for 10 minutes.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target becomes frightened 2.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target becomes frightened 1.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Singular Expertise</title>

      <line>You have particular expertise with guns and crossbows that grants you greater proficiency with them and the ability to deal more damage. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to damage rolls with firearms and crossbows.</line>
      <line>This intense focus on firearms and crossbows prevents you from reaching the same heights with other weapons. Your proficiency with unarmed attacks and with weapons other than firearms and crossbows can't be higher than trained, even if you gain an ability that would increase your proficiency in one or more other weapons to match your highest weapon proficiency (such as the weapon expertise feats many ancestries have). If you have gunslinger weapon mastery, the limit is expert, and if you have gunslinging legend, the limit is master.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Improved Initiative</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait>

      <line>You react more quickly than others can. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to initiative rolls.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spring the Trap</title>
      <action>F</action>
      <trait>Gunslinger</trait>
      <trigger>You roll initiative.</trigger>

      <line>You can Interact to draw a combination weapon and set it to melee or ranged mode. On your first turn, your movement and ranged attacks don't trigger reactions that are normally triggered by movement or ranged attacks (such as Attack of Opportunity).</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Touch and Go</title>
      <action>1</action>
      <trait>Gunslinger</trait>
      <requirement>You are wielding a combination weapon</requirement>

      <line>Your body's shadows mask your hands' steel. You can Step toward and enemy,  and you can Interact to change your weapon between melee or ranged modes, and you then Interact to reload.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Risky Reload</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>2</level>
      <action>1</action>
      <trait>Flourish</trait> <trait>Gunslinger</trait>
      <requirements>You're wielding a firearm.</requirements>

      <line>You're practiced a technique for rapidly reloading your firearm, but attempting to use this technique is a dangerous gamble with your firearm's functionality. Interact to relead a firearm, them make a Strike with that firearm. If the Strike fails, the firearm misfires.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Misfires</title>

      <line>Firearms that are improperly maintained or subjected to unsual strain can misfire. If you attempt to fire a firearm that was fired the previous day or earlier and hasn't been cleaned since then, roll a DC 5 flat check before making your attack roll. If you fail this misfire check, the weapon misfires and jams, turning the attack into an automatic critical failure.</line>
      <line>You must use an Interact action to clear the jam before you can reload the weapon and fire again.</line>
      <line>When you spend an hour cleaning a weapon, you don't need to roll for a misfire until the next day unless an effect says otherwise. You can clear multiple firearms during this hour, up to a reasonable limit as determined by the GM (typically no more than five).</line>
      <line>Some abilities cause a weapon to misfire as part of their effects. If such a misfire happens as a result of an attack (due to an action that causes a misfire on a failed attack, for example), it retroactively makes the attack a critical failure.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Munitions Crafter</title>
      <type>Feat</type>
      <level>1</level>
      <trait>Gunslinger</trait>

      <line>Bullets and bombs can be scarce in some parts, so you've learned to make your own. You become trained in Crafting and gain the alchemist's Infused Reagents class feature. You also gain the Alchemical Crafting feat and four additional formular for 1st-level alchemical items.</line>
      <line>You gain infused reagents (a pool of reagents usable to make alchemical items) and advanced alchemy (allowing you to make alchemical items during your daily preparations without the normal cost or time expenditure). You can use the infused reagents only to create bombs or alchemical ammunition. Your advanced alchemy level for creating these is 1 and doesn't increase on its own.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Infused Reagents</b>]]></line>
      <line>You infuse reagents with your own alchemical essence, allowing you to create alchemical items at no cost. Each day during your daily preparations, you gain a number of batches of infused reagents equal to your level. You can use these reagents for advanced alchemy, described below. Together, these infused reagents have light bulk.</line>
      <line>As soon as you make your next daily preparations, your infused reagents from the previous day's preparations are instantly destroyed, and nonpermanent effects of your previous day's infused items immediately end. While infused reagents are physical objects, they can't be duplicated, preserved, or created in any way other than your daily preparations. Any such artificial reagents lack the infusion and are useless for advanced alchemy.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Advanced Alchemy</b>]]></line>
      <line>During your daily preparations, after producing new infused reagents, you can spend batches of those infused reagents to create infused alchemical items. You don't need to attempt a Crafting check to do this, and you ignore both the number of days typically required to create the items and any alchemical component requirements. Your advanced alchemy level is 1. For each batch of infused reagents you spend, choose an alchemical item of your advanced alchemy level or lower that's in your formula book, and make a batch of two of that item. These items have the infused trait and remain potent for 24 hours or until your next daily preparations, whichever comes first.</line>
      <line>If you use a batch of infused reagents to create basic level-0 ammunition such as black powder cartridges or black powder doses, you produce 10 rounds of ammunition.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Alchemical Crafting</title>
      <type>Feat</type>
      <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Crafting</prereq>

      <line>You can use the Craft activity to create alchemical items. When you select this feat, you immediately add the formulas for four common 1st-level alchemical items to your formula book.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Black Powder<![CDATA[<br/>]]>(dose or round)</title>
      <type>Item</type>
      <level>0</level>
      <uncommon /> <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait>
      <price>1 cp</price>
      <ammunition>round</ammunition>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>Black powder is a volatile and explosive alchemical substance commonly used in the production of firearm munitions. Black powder becomes inert and useless when wet and must be kept in a sealed, water-tight container.</line>
      <line>The smallest unit of black powder that still has a simple use, a dose can be a simple package paper parcel around black powder or it can be packaged with a metal bullet or pellet to be used as ammunition. When ignited with a fuse or exposed to direct flame, a dose of black powder explodes. This isn't powerful enough to deal damage but makes a loud sound and could trigger further explosions. A fuse for a dose can be created with a few twists of paper and causes the dose to explore the round after it's lit.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Alchemist's Fire, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type>
      <level>1</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Bomb</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Splash</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <range>20 ft.</range>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Strike</type>
      </activate>

      <line>Alchemist's fire is a combination of volatile liquids that ignite when exposed to air.</line>
      <line>A lesser alchemist's fire deals 1d8 fire damage, 1 persistent fire damage, and 1 fire splash damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Splash</title>
      <type>Trait</type>
      <line>When you use a thrown weapon with the splash trait, you don't add your Strength modifier to the damage roll. If an attack with a splash weapon fails, succeeds, or critically succeeds, all creatures within 5 feet of the target (including the target) take the listed splash damage. On a failure (but not a critical failure), the target of the attack roll still takes the splash damage. Add splash damage together with the initial damage against the target before applying a target's weaknesses or resistances. You don't multiply splash damage on a critical hit.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Thunderstone, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Bomb</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Sonic</trait> <trait>Splash</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <range>20 ft.</range>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Strike</type>
      </activate>

      <line>When this stone hits a creature or a hard surface, it explodes with a deafening bang.</line>
      <line>A lesser thunderstone deals 1d4 sonic damage, 1 sonic splash damage, and each creature within 10 feet of the space in which the stone exploded must succeed at a DC 17 Fortitude saving throw or be deafened until the end of its next turn.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Goo Grenade, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Bomb</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Splash</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <range>20 ft.</range>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Strike</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A goo grenade is a flask filled with a fast-growing, short-lived alchemical ooze.</line>
      <line>When you hit a creature with a goo grenade, that creature takes 1d4 acid damage, 1 persistent acid damage, and a –5-foot circumstance penalty to its Speed from the clinging goo, and the grenade deals 1 acid splash damage.</line>
      <line>The target can end any penalties, conditions, and persistent damage caused by the goo grenade by Escaping (DC 15) or spending a total of 3 Interact actions to pry themselves free of the ooze. These Interact actions don't have to be consecutive, and other creatures can provide the actions as well.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tanglefoot Bag, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Bomb</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <range>20 ft.</range>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Strike</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A tanglefoot bag is filled with sticky substances.</line>
      <line>When you hit a creature wtih a tanglefoot bag, that creature takes a –10-foot penalty to its Speed for 1 minute.</line>
      <line>On a critical hit, a creature in contact with a solid surface becomes stuck to the surface and immobilized for 1 round, and a creature flying via wings has its wings tangled, causing it to fall safely to the ground and become unable to Fly again for 1 round. Tanglefoot bags are not effective when used on a creature that is in water.</line>
      <line>The target can end any effects by Escaping (DC 17) or spending a total of 3 Interact actions to carefully remove the sticky substances. These interact actions don't have to be consecutive, and other creatures can provide the actions as well.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ammunition</title>
      <type>Rule</type>

      <line>Each ammunition's stat block includes an Ammunition entry that lists which type of ammunition it can be crafted as (such as arrow or round), or "any" if it's not limited to any particular type. All stat blocks for ammunition omit the usage and Bulk entries; use the standard rules for the type of ammunition to determine reloading times and Bulk.</line>
      <line>When using special ammunition, use your ranged weapon's fundamental runes to determine the attack modifier and damage dice. Don't add the effects of your weapon's property runes unless the ammunition states otherwise –the ammunition creates its own effects. Special ammunition deals damage on a hit normally in addition to any listed effects unless its description states otherwise.</line>
      <line>Regardless of whether an attack with special ammunition hits or misses, launching the ammunition consumes its magic. Unless stated otherwise, the ammunition is made of normal materials, not precious materials.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Activated Ammunition</b>]]></line>
      <line>If special ammunition doesn't have an Activate entry, it's activated automatically when it's launched. Types of special ammunition that have an Activate entry must be activated with additional actions before being used. Once ou activate the ammunition, you must shoot it before the end of your turn. Otherwise, it deactivates (but isn't consumed) and you must Activate it again before you can use it. If you shoot the ammunition without activating it first, it functions as non-magical ammunition and is still consumed.</line>
      <line>The action required to activate the ammunition doesn't alter how many actions it takes to reload. For example, you could activate a <![CDATA[<i>beacon shot</i>]]> arrow by touching it with 1 action, then draw and shoot the arrow as part of a Strike as normal. For a <![CDATA[<i>beacon shot</i>]]> bolt or round, you could Activate it, load it into a weapon, then shoot it, or load the ammunition into the weapon, then Activate it, and then shoot it.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Acid Ammunition, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Acid</trait> <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Splash</trait>
      <ammunition>any</ammunition>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>When activated, the reservoir of alchemical reagents in lesser acid ammunition atomizes on impact, dealing 1 persistent acid damage and 1 acid splash damage in addition to the damage the attack normally deals.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fire Ammunition, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
       <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Splash</trait>
      <ammunition>any</ammunition>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>When activated, the reservoir of alchemical reagents in lesser fire ammunition atomizes on impact, dealing 1 persistent fire damage and 1 fire splash damage in addition to the damage the attack normally deals.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Poison Ammunition, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Splash</trait>
      <ammunition>any</ammunition>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>When activated, the reservoir of alchemical reagents in lesser poison ammunition atomizes on impact, dealing 1 persistent poison damage and 1 poison splash damage in addition to the damage the attack normally deals.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
