<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Bracers of Missile Deflection</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn bracers</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <price>52 gp</price>

      <line>These bracers are made from plates of durable mithral and gleam like the summer sun.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name>
         <action>R</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Trigger</name>A ranged weapon attack hits you but doesn't critically hit</part>
         <part><name>Requirements</name>You are aware of the attack and not flat-footed</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>The bracers send the missle off-course. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus to AC against the triggering attack. If this attack would cause the attack to be a failure, the attack misses you.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Bag of Holding (Type I)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Extradimensional</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>
      <price>75 gp</price>

      <line>Though it appears to be a cloth sack decorated with panels of richly colored silk or stylish embroidery, a <![CDATA[<i>bag of holding</i>]]> opens into an extradimensional space larger than its outside dimensions. The Bulk held inside the bag doesn't change the Bulk of the <![CDATA[<i>bag of holding</i>]]> itself. The bag's extradimensional space can hold up to 25 Bulk.</line>
      <line>You can Interact with the <![CDATA[<i>bag of holding</i>]]> to stow items in it or remove them just like a mundane sack. Though the bag can hold a great amount of material, an object still needs to be able to fit through the opening of the sack to be stored inside.</line>
      <line>If the bag is overloaded or broken, it ruptures and is ruined, causing the items inside to be lost forever. If it's turned inside out, the items inside spill out unharmed, but the bag must be put right before it can be used again. A living creature placed inside the bag has enough air for 10 minutes before it begins to suffocate, and it can attempt to Escape against a DC of 13. An item inside the bag provides no benefits unless it's retrieved first. An item in the bag can't be detected by magic that detects on things on the same plane.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Vapor (Lesser)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait>
      <price>20 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>3</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line><![CDATA[<i>Healing vapor</i>]]> is a substance that accelerates natural recovery processes by dispersing a mist infused with a variety of reagents typically used for healing and recovery. When deployed from a sealed container, the vapor fills a 5-foot burst, lasts for 10 minutes, and can affect up to four creatures at one time. Any creatures beyond the first four gain no benefit, though if a creature leaves before the duration is over, a new creature that enters can benefit from the mist.</line>
      <line>A creature benefiting from the vapors regains a number of Hit Points based on the vapor's type. While affected, a creature also gains an item bonus to saving throws against diseases and poisons. If the areas of more than one <![CDATA[<i>healing vapor</i>]]> overlap, only the strongest applies to creatures inside overlapping areas. Strong wind disperses the mist, rendering it ineffective while the wind blows.</line>
      <line>Each creature benefiting from a <![CDATA[<i>lesser healing vapor</i>]]> regains 1 Hit Points every 2 minutes, and gets a +1 item bonus.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Striking Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>68 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to a weapon, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Etching a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 19, you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Striking Rune</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>65 gp</price>
      <usage>Etched onto a weapon</usage>
      <craft>You are an Expert in Crafting</craft>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune stores destructive magic in the weapon, increasing the weapon damage dice it deals to two instead of one. For istance, a <![CDATA[<i>+1 striking dagger</i>]]> would deal 2d4 damage instead of 1d4 damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Crafter's Eyepiece</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <usage>worn eyepiece</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>
      <price>60 gp</price>

      <line>This rugged metal eyepiece etched with sqare patterns is designed to be worn over a single eye. Twisting the lens reveals a faint three-dimensional outline of an item you plan to build or repair, with helpful labels on the component parts. You gain a +1 item bonus to Crafting checks.</line>
      <line>When you Repair an item, increase the Hit Points restored to 10 + 10 per proficiency rank on a success or 15 + 15 per proficiency rank on a critical success.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Blast Boots (Moderate)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait>
      <price>11 gp</price>
      <usage>worn attached to footwear or feet</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>These sets of rockets come in pairs and strap onto existing footwear (or a creature's feet). Inserting them and aligning them properly takes 1 minute.</line>
      <line>When you Activate the <![CDATA[<i>blast boots</i>]]>, you can High Jump or Long Jump without the need to Stride first. If you High Jump, you can increase the vertical distance by up to 30 feet. If you Long Jump, you can increase the horizontal distance by up to 45 feet.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spiderfoot Brew (Lesser)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Elixir</trait> <trait>Morph</trait>
      <price>12 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>This sticky fluid is made from the silk glands of giant spiders. When you drinka <![CDATA[<i>spiderfoot brew</i>]]>, tine hairs grow on your hands and feet, granting you a climb Speed and an item bonus to Athletics checks made to Climb for the duration.</line>
      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>lesser spiderfoot brew</i>]]> grants a climb Speed of 15 feet, a +1 item bonus, and the duration is 1 minute.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Mistform Elixir (Lesser)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Elixir</trait> <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Visual</trait>
      <price>18 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A faint mist emanates from your skin, making you concealed (a creature must succeed a a flat DC 5 check to target you with an attack, spell, or other effect) for the listed duration. As usual, being concealed when your position is still obvious, you can't use this concealment to Hide or Sneak.</line>
      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>lesser mistform elixir</i>]]> has a duration of 3 rounds.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sneezing Powder</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Inhaled</trait>
      <price>2 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>2</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>You can toss <![CDATA[<i>sneezing powder</i>]]> at an adjacent creature as an Interact action. The target must attempt a DC 15 Fortitude save to avoid sneezing. On a failed save, the creature sneezes uncontrollably, becoming slowed 1 for 1 round. On a critical failure, the creature is instead slowed 1 for 3 rounds.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
