@ -0,0 +1,207 @@
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Lambent Perfume</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>6</level>
      <trait>Censer</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>250 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>This ceramic incense burner is shaped like a three-headed ibis in the form of Atreia the Lambent King, spreading his wings and preparing to take flight; it hangs on a thin, golden chain.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate - Light Incense</name> <type>(aura, manipulate)</type> <action>2</action>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Cost</name>incense worth at least 1 sp</part>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>Sparkling golden mist escapes the ibis's open beaks, spreading in a 20-foot emanation. This perfume mist is calming and restorative. A creature that ends its turn within the censer's smoke while sickened or under an affliction can attempt a new saving throw to overcome it. After attempting a new saving throw against an affliction, a creature is temporarily immune to <![CDATA[<i>lambent perfume</i>]]> for the purposes of overcoming that affliction for 24 hours.<![CDATA[<br/>]]>A creature with multiple afflictions, or that is both sickened and has an affliction, chooses one to attempt to overcome each time it ends its turn in the aura.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Censer</title>
      <type>Trait</type>

      <line>An item with the censer trait must be filled with incense to Activate it, which ignites the incense and causes the censer to exude a cloud of smoke. The smoke creates an aura in an emanation from the censer's square. The smoke lasts for 1 minute but is immediately dispersed by a strong wind (ending the activation) or if you Dismiss the activation to snuff out the incense.</line>
      <line>Unless specifically noted otherwise, the smoke from a censer isn't thick enough to make creatures concealed, and you can choose to be immune to the smoke of any censer you Activate. You must be holding a censer to Activate it, but if you Release the censer, the incense continues to burn from the censer's location.</line>
      <line>A magical censer requires incense, as noted in its activation, which can be purchased in most settlements. You can use an alchemical or magical incense item for this purpose, but the magic of the censer overwhelms the incense and negates any other magical or alchemical properties it has. You can typically use the censer without activating it to burn incense as though it were a mundane censer.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Salve of Antiparalysis</title>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Oil</trait>
      <type>Item</type> <level>6+</level>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>
      <activate><action>1</action><type>(manipulate)</type></activate>

      <line>Applying this filmy salve to a creature helps it overcome magical paralysis. The salve attempts to counteract the paralysis with a counteract rank and modifier depending on its type.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>moderate</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>40 gp</price>

         <line>The salve has a counteract rank of 3rd, and a counteract modifier of +22.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Runestone</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
         <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>3 gp</price>
         <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

         <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to an armor, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
         <block>
            <name>Transferring a rune</name>
            <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
            <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
            <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 22; you transfer the rune on a success</part>
         </block>

         <variant>
            <rune italic="">quenching</rune> <level>6</level>
            <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
            <price>250 gp</price>
            <usage>etched onto an armor</usage>

            <line>This rune counters burning and corrosive agents. Armor with this rune reduces the DC of the flat check to end persistent acid or fire damage affecting you from 15 to 12 (from 10 to 7 with particularly effective assistance).</line>
         </variant>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Energy Breath Potion</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>7+</level>
         <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Potion</trait>
         <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         <activate><action>1</action><type>(manipulate)</type></activate>

         <line>Distilled from the energy of dangerous spells, an <![CDATA[<i>energy breath potion</i>]]> grants you the Energy Breath action for the duration. The potency of the breath depends on the potion's type, based on how long the distilled ingredients were aged.</line>
         <line>The potion itself and the Energy Breathe action have the trait matching the damage type.</line>
         <block>
            <name>Energy Breath</name> <type>(Magical)</type> <action>1</action>
            <part><name>Effect</name>You breathe out damaging energy in an area determined by the damage type. Creatures in the area take damage depending on the type of the potion, with a basic save whose type and DC depends on the type of the potion. After you use this action, you can't use it for 1d4 rounds.</part>
         </block>

         <variant>
            <type>lesser electricity</type> <level>7</level>
            <trait>Electricity</trait>
            <price>70 gp</price>

            <line>Electricity breath is a 30-foot line with a basic Reflex save.</line>
            <line>A lessser potion deals 4d6 damage, with a DC 23.</line>
         </variant>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Boots of Bounding</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>7+</level>
         <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
         <usage>worn shoes</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
         <price>340 gp</price>

         <line>The springy soles of these sturdy leather boots cushion your feet and make each step lighter. These boots give you a +5-foot item bonus to your Speed and a +2 item bonus to Athletics checks to High Jump and Long Jump.</line>
         <line>In addition, when you use the Leap action, you can move 5 feet further if jumping horizontally or 3 feet higher if jumping vertically.</line>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Clawed Bracers</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>7</level>
         <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
         <usage>worn bracers</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
         <price>325 gp</price>

         <line>Animal claws are woven into the thick leather of these bracers.</line>

         <block>
            <name>Activate - Extend Claws</name> <action>1</action> <type>(manipulate, morph)</type>
            <part><name>Frequency</name>once per hour</part>
            <part><name>Effect</name>The bracers fuse temporarily with your forearms, with the claws extending to your fingertips. You gain a climb Speed of 20 feet and a claw unarmed attack with the Agile and Finesse traits that deals 1d6 damage and is in the Brawling group. This lasts for 10 minutes or until you Dismiss it.</part>
         </block>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Stalagmite Seed</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>7</level>
         <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>60 gp</price>
         <bulk>-</bulk>
         <activate><action>1</action><type>manipulate</type></activate>

         <line>A <![CDATA[<i>stalagmite seed</i>]]> can be thrown with a range increment of 15 feet, used as a sling stone, or packed into firearm ammunition. When you throw or fire an activated seed, you aim it at a 5-foot square rather than a specific target. Stalagmites of assorted sizes erupt in the square the seed lands in, dealing 6d6 piercing damage to any creature in that space with a DC 23 basic Reflex save. The stalagmites remain for 1 minute, creating difficult terrain in that space, before they crumble to dust.</line>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Peace in Dreams Tea</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>6</level>
         <uncommon/> <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Potion</trait> <trait>Tea</trait>
         <price>50 gp</price>
         <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         <activate><action>1</action><type>(manipulate)</type><alt type="Tea Ceremony" /></activate>

         <line>This creamy tea is made from warm soy milk steeped with whole, dried chrysanthemum flowers and honey, and brewed from when the sun first touches the horizon to when it has fully set.</line>
         <line>Consuming this tea causes mild drowsiness, aids in sleep, and protects from harmful mental effects. You gain a +1 item bonus to all saving throws against mental effects for the duration.</line>
         <line>Once you drink a dose of magic tea, you're temporarily immune to that particular type of magic tea for 24 hours.</line>

         <block>
            <name>Tea Ceremony</name>
            <part linebreak="">The duration increases to 8 hours, and as long as you're asleep, the item bonus increases to +2.</part>
         </block>

         <traittext><name>Magic Tea, Tea Ceremony</name>You can activate magic tea with a 10-minute activity that requires sterling artisan's tools specific for tea ceremonies, though the tools can be shared by up to four people taking the activity together. This activity allows you to prepare and then either consume the tea or present it to someone during the ceremony. Activating magic tea in this way enhances its effects, as detailed in each tea's Tea Ceremony entry.</traittext>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Octopus Potion</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>6</level>
         <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Morph</trait> <trait>Potion</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
         <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
         <duration>1 minute</duration>
         <activate><action>1</action><type>(manipulate)</type></activate>

         <line>Eight flailing octopus arms covered in suckers pop out from the sides of your body for the duration when you imbibe this potion. The arms share your multiple attack penalty and attempt to Grapple a random enemy within 15 feet of you. On a success, roll 1d4 to determine an additional effect of the arms, which remains as long as the target remains grabbed or restrained by the arms.</line>
         <line list="Added Effect">
            <entry name="1 -">The arms cover the eyes; the target is also blinded.</entry>
            <entry name="2 -">The arms cover the mouth; the target can't speak.</entry>
            <entry name="3 -">The arms wrap around the limbs; the flat check the target makes to use a manipulate action is DC 7 instead of 5.</entry>
            <entry name="4 -">The arms crush the enemy; the target takes bludgeoning damage equal to the potion's level immediate and at the end of each of its turns.</entry>
         </line>
         <line>On subsequent turns you can use a single action, which has the attack trait, to have the arms either Grapple a creature currently grabbed or restrained by the arms (with no additional effect) or release any creature they currently held by the arms and Grapple a random enemy within 15 feet of you with the added effect on a success.</line>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Ginger Chew</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Lozenge</trait>
         <price>28 gp</price>
         <duration>1 hour</duration>
         <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>

         <line>This chewy ginger candy aids digestion and soothes unsettled stomachs. For the duration, it grants you a +1 item bonus to Fortitude saves against being sickened.</line>
         <block>
            <name>Chew Down</name><action>1</action>
            <part><name>Effect</name>Reduce your sickened value by 1, if any. The chew becomes inert.</part>
         </block>
      </rule>

      <rule>
         <title>Clown Monarch</title>
         <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Injury</trait> <trait>Poison</trait>
         <price>21 gp</price>
         <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
         <activate><action>2</action><type>Interact</type></activate>

         <line>A victim of clown monarch is amusing to behold as they repeatedly suffer slapstrick pratfalls. This poison disrupts the victim's sense of balance.</line>

         <block>
            <name>Saving Throw</name><type>DC 22 Fortitude</type>
            <part><name>Max Duration</name>6 rounds</part>
            <part><name>Stage 1</name>falls prone, and must succeed at a DC 5 flat check when attempting to Stand Up or the action is disrupted (1 round)</part>
            <part><name>Stage 2</name>as stage 1, but the DC is 10 (1 round)</part>
            <part><name>Stage 3</name>as stage 1, but the DC is 15 (1 rouns)</part>
         </block>
      </rule>
</catalog>
