<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Elixir of Life, Minor</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Elixir</trait> <trait>Healing</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>
      <price>3 gp</price>

      <line>Elixirs of life accelerate a living creature's natural healing process and immune system. Upon drinking this elixir, you regain 1d6 Hit Points, and gain a +1 item bonus to saving throws against diseases and poisons for the duration.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Potency Crystal</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Talisman</trait>
      <price>4 gp</price>
      <usage>affixed to a weapon</usage>
      <activate>
         <action>F</action>
         <type>envision</type>
         <trigger>You make an attack with the affixed weapon, but you haven't rolled yet</trigger>
      </activate>

      <line>This fluoride crystal glows with a strange phosphorence. When you activate the crystal, the weapon becomes a <![CDATA[<i>+1 striking weapon</i>]]> for the rest of the turn, gaining a +1 item bonus to attack rolls and increasing the damage on a hit to two weapon damage dice.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Flask of Fellowship</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>25 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This is a metal drinking flask, 4 inches in diameter and 10 inches tall. Its screw top is covered by four simple metal cups that nest together.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name>
         <type>Make an Impression</type>
         <part><name>Effect</name>If you share drinks from a flask of fellowship as part of your Make an Impression action, the drink that pours from the flask happens to be exactly what the target of your efforts would most like to have a dram or two of—wine, spirits, hot ginger tea, or ice cold water with lemon, for example. You gain a +1 item bonus on your Diplomacy check.</part>
         <part>The GM can disallow the flask's use if it doesn't make sense in the moment for you to pull out a flask and start pouring, if drinks are inappropriate for the occasion, or if your target is absolutely not interested in sharing a drink with you. Drinks from the <![CDATA[<i>flask of fellowship</i>]]> are entirely social; they won't intoxicate anyone, nor alleviate serious thirst.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>+1 Weapon Potency Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>38 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a <![CDATA[<i>+1 weapon potency</i>]]> rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to a weapon, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Etching a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 16, you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cloak of Feline Rest</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>20 gp</price>
      <usage>worn cloak</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This black velvet cloak is featureless and very soft to the touch. Upon wearing it for the first time, you're momentarily overwhelmed with a sense of comfort and coziness. While wearing this cloak you can comfortably rest in any space, so long as it's not wet or particularly hazardous. While sleeping in this cloak you only take a –2 status penalty to auditory Perception checks, rather than a –4 status penalty.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Oil of Potency</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Oil</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <price>7 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>When you apply this thick, viscous oil to a weapon or suit of armor, that item immediately becomes magically potent. If the item is a weapon, it temporarily becomes a <![CDATA[<i>+1 striking</i> weapon, or, if it's armor, it temporarily becomes <i>+1 resilient</i>]]> armor. This lasts for 1 minute.</line>
      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>+1 striking</i>]]> weapon gains a +1 item bonus to attack rolls, and deals two weapon damage dice of damage on a hit. A <![CDATA[<i>+1 resilient</i>]]> armor has an item bonus to AC one higher, and grants a +1 item bonus to saving throws.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Crying Angel Pendant</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Divine</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Talisman</trait>
      <price>7 gp</price>
      <usage>affixed to armor</usage>
      <activate>
         <action>F</action>
         <type>envision</type>
         <trigger>You critically fail to Administer First Aid</trigger>
         <requirement>You are trained in Medicine</requirement>
      </activate>

      <line>When you activate this alabaster pendant, your critical failure becomes a normal failure instead.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>+1 Weapon Potency Rune</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>35 gp</price>
      <usage>Etched onto a weapon</usage>
      <craft>You are an Expert in Crafting</craft>

      <line>Magical enhancements make this weapon strike true. Attack rolls with this weapon gain a +1 item bonus, and the weapon can be etched with one property rune.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scroll of Fear</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Mental</trait> <trait>Scroll</trait>
      <price>4 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Will</save> <duration>varies</duration>
      <activate>
         <action>2</action>
         <type>Cast a Spell (somatic, verbal)</type>
         <requirement linebreak="">You must have <![CDATA[<i>fear</i>]]> on your spell list</requirement>
      </activate>

      <line>This furled piece of parchment has been imbued with magical energy that allows you to plant fear in the mind of the target; it must attempt a Will save against your spell DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target is frightened 1.</success>
         <fail>The target is frightened 2.</fail>
         <critfail>The target is frightened 3 and fleeing for 1 round.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ring of Discretion</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Visual</trait>
      <price>15 gp</price>
      <usage>worn</usage>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>ring of discretion</i>]]> magically conceals any armor and sheathed weapons you're wearing by either turning them invisible or creating the illusion of ordinary clothes. The ring doesn't change your appearance beyond concealing weapons and armor.</line>
      <line>As soon as you wield a weapon affected by the ring, the weapon becomes obvious to onlookers and is no longer affected until you sheathe the weapon for at least 1 minute. A creature can use the Seek action to examine you and disbelieve this illusion (DC 15), and it can attempt to do so without using an action each time it hits you with an attack.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
