<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Eternal Eruption</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>5+</level>
      <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This blueberry-sized bead appears to be a sphere of glass with a flickering light at its core. An <i>eternal eruption</i> resembles <i>frozen lava</i> and is made with the same type of time magic used to suspend lava at the exact point before a volcanic eruption, but it reforms itself after it's used. Determining the difference between the two requires a close examination to see a fain, repeating pattern of red runes.</line>
      <block>
         <name activate="">Lava Bomb</name> <action>2</action> <type>(concentrate, manipulate)</type>
         <part><name>Effect</name>You fling the <i>eternal eruption</i>, which detonates into a 20-foot burst ball of fire where it lands. Your toss can place the center anywhere within 70 feet, though at the GM's discretion, you might need to make a ranged attack roll if the throw is unusually challenging. After 2d4 hours, the <i>eternal eruption</i> reforms itself in a container on your person, typically the one you most recently stored it in.</part>
      </block>

      <variant>
         <name italic="">eternal eruption of blackpeak</name> <level>7</level>
         <price>360 gp</price>

         <line>7d6 fire damage, with a DC 25 basic Reflex save.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cloak of Illusions</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>7+</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn cloak</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This cloak flows, covering and concealing the wearer's body. The cloak allows you to cast <i>figment</i> as an occult innate cantrip. Although naturally a dull gray, while invested the cloak picks up colors and patterns from its surroundings, granting an item bonus to Stealth checks.</line>
      <block>
         <name activate="">Draw Hood</name><action>2</action><type>(manipulate)</type>
         <part><name>Frequency</name>once per day</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>You draw the hood up and gain the effects the <i>invisibility</i> spell, with the spell's normal duration or until you pull the hood back down, whichever comes first.</part>
      </block>

      <variant>
         <type>Regular</type> <level>7</level>
         <price>360 gp</price>

         <line>+1 item bonus to Stealth.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Figment</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Subtle</trait>
      <tradition>arcane</tradition> <tradition>occult</tradition>
      <range>30 feet</range>
      <duration>sustained</duration>

      <line>You create a simple illusory sound or vision. A sound adds the <u>auditory</u> trait to the spell and the sound can't include intelligible words or elaborate music. A vision adds the <u>visual</u> trait and can be no larger than a 5-foot cube, and is clearly crude and undetailed if viewed from within 15 feet.</line>
      <line>When you Cast or Sustain the Spell, you can attempt to Create a Diversion with the illusion, gaining a +2 circumstance bonus to your Deception check. If the attempt fails against a creature, that creature disbelieves the figment.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Leaper's Elixir</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1+</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Elixir</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>
      <activate><action>1</action><type>(manipulate)</type></activate>

      <line>This tingly solution increases the elasticity and contraction of your leg muscles. For the duration, you can High Jump and Long Jump as a single action instead of 2 actions. If you do, you don't perform the initial Stride (nor do you fail if you don't Stride 10 feet).</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Greater</type> <level>7</level>
         <price>55 gp</price>

         <line>The maximum vertical distance you can jump with a High Jump is the same as you can jump horizontally with a Long Jump.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scroll of Soothing Spring</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>7</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Scroll</trait> <trait>Vitality</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <tradition>divine</tradition> <tradition>primal</tradition>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <range>30 feet</range>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>
      <price>70 gp</price>
      <activate><type>Cast a Spell, 1 minute (concentrate, manipulate)</type></activate>

      <line>This roll of paper contains <i>soothing spring</i>, allowing you to conjure a stone-lined pool in the ground and fill it with hot water that bubbles up from the earth. The water is comfortably hot and smells mildly sulfurous in a non-unpleasant way. You are able to draw out the full energizing potential of the mineral-rich water.</line>
      <line>Any creature that spends the full hour soaking in the hot spring or basking in the mud from the bottom of the pit regains 10d8 Hit Points and feels refreshed, losing the fatigued condition. As normal for effects that remove fatigue, this doesn't remove any underlying source of fatigue, such as lack of sleep, causing the condition to return if the underlying source isn't addressed.</line>
      <line>The pool is 20 feet on each side, and it's 5 feet deep. It can contain 16 Medium or smaller creatures at a time. A Large creature counts as eight Medium creatures and a Huge creature fills the entire pool. This pool has the <u>structure</u> trait and the same restrictions as magic items that create structures.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Backfire Mantle</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3+</level>
      <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>worn cloak</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>This vivid red cloak of sturdy fabric is favored by aggressive battle alchemists and mages, as well as those cautious warriors who need to advance into the fray ahead of the blast-happy back line. The mantle interposes to protect you from your own and allies' magic, granting you a circumstance bonus to Reflex saves against your own spell as well as those of your allies. You also gain resistance to splash damage from your own alchemical items and those of your allies.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Greater</type> <level>8</level>
         <price>430 gp</price>

         <line>The mantle grants a +2 circumstance bonus and resistance 10.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spun Cloud</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2+</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Bottled Breath</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate><action>1</action><type>Inhale (manipulate)</type></activate>

      <line>On the Elemental Plane of Air, small clouds of differing colors can sometimes float separately from other cloud formations. Clever people can spin these clouds into small handfuls, creating a magical bundle of elemental power.</line>
      <line>After unhaling a <u>bottled breath</u>, you must hold your breath. You can hold your breath for a number of rounds equal to 5 + your Constitution modifier (reducing your remaining air by 1 at the end of each of your turns, or by 2 if you attacked or cast a <u>subtle</u> spell, and by 1 each time you are critically hit or critically fail a save). You lose all remaining air if you speak or Cast a Spell.</line>
      <line>Unlike most <u>bottled breath</u>, <i>spun clouds</i> don't have any effect on you while you hold them in your lungs, but you can exhale the cloud as a single action. When exhaled, the cloud flows out and expands into a 20-foot burst within 60 feet of you. The cloud dissipates after 1 minute.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Red</type> <level>8</level>
         <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
         <price>100 gp</price>

         <line>A red cloud terrifies those it surrounds. Any creature in the cloud, or that later enters the cloud, must succeed at a DC 24 Will save or become frightened 2 (or frightened 3 or a critical failure). Regardless of its save, the creature becomes temporarily immune for 24 hours.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>3 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a rune. When the rune is transferred from the <i>runestone</i> to a weapon, the <i>runestone</i> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Transferring a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 24; you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">flaming</rune> <level>8</level>
         <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <price>500 gp</price>
         <usage>etched onto a weapon</usage>

         <line>A weapon with this rune is empowered by flickering flame. The weapon deals an additional 1d6 fire damage on a successful Strike, plus 1d10 persistent fire damage on a critical hit.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Surging Serum</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2+</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Elixir</trait> <trait>Healing</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate><action>1</action><type>(manipulate)</type></activate>

      <line>Involuntary jolts and surges of energy move through the drinker's body as it restores normal muscle control. When you drink this elixir, it attempts to counteract each effect inflicting the clumsy or enfeebled condition on you, using the lised counteract rank and modifier.</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Moderate</type> <level>8</level>
         <price>75 gp</price>

         <line>This elixir counteracts at 4th-rank and has a +14 counteract modifier.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Winterstep Elixir</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2+</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Elixir</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate><action>1</action><type>(manipulate)</type></activate>

      <line>This frigid white elixir widens your feet and lightens your step, enabling you to walk across ice and snow without difficulty. For the duration, you ignore the uneven ground and difficult terrain caused by ice, and the difficult terrain caused by snow (reducing greater difficult terrain caused by ice or snow to ordinary difficult terrain).</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Lesser</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>36 gp</price>
         <duration>10 minutes</duration>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Barricade Stone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>6+</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Structure</trait>
      <usage>held in 1 hand, or loaded into a sling</usage> <bulk>-- when not activated</bulk>
      <activate><action>2</action><type>(concentrate, interact)</type></activate>

      <line>These magic rocks were crafted in ancient times to construct defenses quickly. In its stone form, a <i>barricade stone</i> appears to be a simple pebble with an unnaturally geometric shape. The size and shape of the stone's final form depends on the type of the <i>barricade stone</i>.</line>
      <line>When you activate the <i>barricade stone</i>, you drop it on the ground, throw it up to 20 feet away, or sling it using a sling weapon. Upon landing, the stone instantly and permanently expands. The stone grows to its maximum size. While normally items with the <u>structure</u> trait put creatures in the area inside the structure, this effect creates solid stone, so it can't be placed in an area where there are creatures.</line>
      <line>While it is likely to take some time even with the right tools, an activated <i>barricade stone</i> can be destroyed the same as any normal stone structure (Hardness 14, HP 56).</line>

      <variant>
         <type>Sphere</type> <level>6</level>
         <price>40 gp</price>

         <line>This smooth marble keeps its shape when activated, growing into a spherical boulder 10 feet in diameter. If stationary, the boulder can be pushed 5 feet with a successful DC 24 Athletics check. If the marble was thrown or slung, the boulder retains its momentum, moving 25 feet away from you each round. A creature in the boulder's way takes 4d6 bludgeoning damage (DC 20 basic Reflex save; on a failure, the creature is knocked prone).</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>
</catalog>
