<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>+1 Weapon Potency Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>38 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a <![CDATA[<i>+1 weapon potency</i>]]> rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to a weapon, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Etching a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 16, you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>+1 Weapon Potency Rune</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>35 gp</price>
      <usage>Etched onto a weapon</usage>
      <craft>You are an Expert in Crafting</craft>

      <line>Magical enhancements make this weapon strike true. Attack rolls with this weapon gain a +1 item bonus, and the weapon can be etched with one property rune.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Returning Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>58 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a <![CDATA[<i>returning</i>]]> rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to a weapon, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Etching a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 18, you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Returning Rune</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>55 gp</price>
      <usage>Etched onto a weapon</usage>

      <line>When you make a thrown Strike with this weapon, it flies back to your hand after the Strike is complate. If you hands a re full when the weapon returns, it falls to the ground in your space.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dagger, low-grade silver</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Agile</trait> <trait>Finesse</trait> <trait>Thrown 10ft.</trait> <trait>Versatile S</trait>
      <price>40 gp</price> <damage>1d4 P</damage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <hands>1</hands>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Simple</weapcat> <weapgroup>Knife</weapgroup>

      <line>This small, bladed weapon is held in one hand and used to stab a creature in close combat. It can also be throw.</line>
      <line>This particular one has been plated in silver, making it more effective against some creatures.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Potion, Minor</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Potion</trait>
      <price>4 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>healing potion</i>]]> is a vial of ruby-red liquid that imparts a tingling sensation as the drinker's wounds heal rapidlyu. When you drink a <![CDATA[<i>minor healing potion</i>]]>, you regain 1d8 Hit Points.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Potion, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Potion</trait>
      <price>12 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>healing potion</i>]]> is a vial of ruby-red liquid that imparts a tingling sensation as the drinker's wounds heal rapidlyu. When you drink a <![CDATA[<i>lesser healing potion</i>]]>, you regain 2d8+5 Hit Points.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Life-Boosting Oil</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Necormancy</trait> <trait>Oil</trait>
      <price>12 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>When you apply sticky, stinging <![CDATA[<i>life-boosting oil</i>]]>, you gain fast healing that starts the first time you take damage while the oil lasts. Once the fast healing starts, the oil remains effective for 4 rounds. The oil lasts only 8 hours, whether it provides fast healing or not.</line>
      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>lesser life-boosting oil</i>]]> grants fast healing 3, meaning you regain 3 Hit Points at the start of each of your turns.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Oil of Skating</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Oil</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <price>5 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>This thin, slippery oil shimmers with a golden hue. Coating your shoes or feet with <![CDATA[<i>oil of skating</i>]]> enables you to skate quickly along flat surfaces for 1 hour. You gain a +10-foot status bonus to your Speed, which doubles if you move on a downhill surface.</line>
      <line>You lose this bonus if moving on difficult terrain, greater difficult terrain, or uneven ground. Also, you treat any uphill movement as moving on difficult terrain while your feet are oiled and treat the results of any Acrobatics checks made to Balance as one degree worse.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Potion of Retaliation, Minor Electricity</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Potion</trait>
      <price>4 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>For 1 minute after drinking a <![CDATA[<i>minor potion of electricity retaliation</i>]]>, you glow with a faint electricity aura, and a creature that touches you (such as by making an unarmed attack or using a spell with a range of touch against you) takes 1 electricity damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Silversheen</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait>
      <price>6 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 2 hands</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>You can slather this silvery paste onto one melee weapon, one thrown weapon, or 10 pieces of ammunition. For the next hour, the weapon or ammunition counts as silver instead of its normal precious material (such as cold iron) for any physical damage it deals.</line>
      <line>Silversheen spoils quickly, so once you open a vial, you must use it all at once, rather than saving it.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Wand of Briny Bolt</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Wand</trait>
      <price>60 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This baton is about a foot long and contains a 1st-level <![CDATA[<i>briny bolt</i>]]> spell that can be cast once per day. It has a light blue coloration with watery images etched along its length.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name>
         <type>Cast a Spell</type>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must have <![CDATA[<i>briny bolt</i>]]> on your spell list</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>You Cast the Spell from the wand</part>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Overcharge</name>If the spell has been cast from the wand for the day, you can cast it one more time by overcharging the wand at the risk of destroying it. After you Cast the Spell, make a DC 10 flat check. On a success, the wand is broken and can be repaired. On a failure, the wand is destroyed.</part>
         <part>Activating a wand that has been overcharged for the day automatically destroys it, and no spell is cast.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Briny Bolt</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You hurl a bolt of salt water from your extended hand. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creatures takes 4d6 bludgeoning damage and is blinded for 1 round and dazzled for 1 minute as salt water sprays into its eyes. The creature can use an Interact action to rub its eyes and end the blinded condition, but not the dazzled condition.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creatures takes 2d6 bludgeoning damage and in blinded for 1 round. The creature can spend an Interact action wiping the salt water from its eyes to end the blinded condition.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
