<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Armor Potency Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>163 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a <![CDATA[<i>+1 armor potency</i>]]> rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to an armor, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Etching a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 20, you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Armor Potency</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>160 gp</price>
      <usage>Etched onto a weapon</usage>
      <craft>You are an Expert in Crafting</craft>

      <line>Magic wards deflect attacks. Increase the armor's item bonus to AC by 1. The armor can be etched with one property rune.</line>
   </rule>

  <rule>
      <title>Fearsome Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
      <price>163 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a <![CDATA[<i>fearsome</i>]]> rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to a weapon, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Etching a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 20, you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fearsome</title>
      <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
      <price>160 gp</price>
      <usage>etched onto a weapon</usage>

      <line>When you critically hit with this weapon, the target becomes frightened 1.</line>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <title>Striking Runestone</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>68 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>

      <line>This flat piece of hard stone is specially etched with a <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune. When the rune is transferred from the <![CDATA[<i>runestone</i> to a weapon, the <i>runestone</i>]]> cracks and is destroyed.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Etching a rune</name>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Time</name>1 day</part>
         <part><name>Requirement</name>You must be able to craft magical items</part>
         <part><name>Check</name>Crafting DC 19, you transfer the rune on a success</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Striking Rune</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>65 gp</price>
      <usage>Etched onto a weapon</usage>
      <craft>You are an Expert in Crafting</craft>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune stores destructive magic in the weapon, increasing the weapon damage dice it deals to two instead of one. For istance, a <![CDATA[<i>+1 striking dagger</i>]]> would deal 2d4 damage instead of 1d4 damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sturdy Shield (Minor)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>100 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>
      <base item="Shield">Steel Shield</base>

      <line>With a superior design and excellent craftsmanship, this steel shield has higher Hardness than its non-magical counterparts, making it hard to break and destroy.</line>
      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>minor sturdy shield</i>]]> has Hardness 8, HP 64, and BT 32.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Mistform Elixir (Lesser)</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Elixir</trait> <trait>Illusion</trait> <trait>Visual</trait>
      <price>18 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A faint mist emanates from your skin, making you concealed (a creature must succeed a a flat DC 5 check to target you with an attack, spell, or other effect) for the listed duration. As usual, being concealed when your position is still obvious, you can't use this concealment to Hide or Sneak.</line>
      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>lesser mistform elixir</i>]]> has a duration of 3 rounds.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Potion, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Potion</trait>
      <price>12 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>L</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>1</action>
         <type>Interact</type>
      </activate>

      <line>A <![CDATA[<i>healing potion</i>]]> is a vial of ruby-red liquid that imparts a tingling sensation as the drinker's wounds heal rapidlyu. When you drink a <![CDATA[<i>lesser healing potion</i>]]>, you regain 2d8+5 Hit Points.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fear Gem Talisman</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>4</level>
      <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Mental</trait> <trait>Talisman</trait>
      <price>20 gp</price>
      <usage>affixed to a weapon</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>
      <activate>
         <action>2</action>
         <type>Intimidating Strike</type>
      </activate>

      <line>Dark smoke seems to writhe within this obsidian gem. When you activate the gem, you make an Intimidating Strike, as the fighter feat.</line>
      <line>If you have the intimidating Strike feat, increase the frightened condition value from this Intimidating Strike to frightened 2, or frightened 3 on a critical hit.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Intimidating Strike</title>
      <action>2</action>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Fighter</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>

      <line>Your blow not only wounds creatures but also shatters their confidence. Make a melee Strike. If you hit and deal damage, the target is frightened 1, or frightened 2 on a critical hit.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scroll of Stinking Cloud</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Scroll</trait>
      <price>4 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage>
      <bulk>L</bulk>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>20-foot burst</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>
      <activate>
         <action>2</action>
         <type>Cast a Spell (somatic, verbal)</type>
         <requirement linebreak="">You must have <![CDATA[<i>stinking cloud</i>]]> on your spell list</requirement>
      </activate>

      <line>This furled piece of parchment has been imbued with magical energy that allows you to create a cloud of putrid mists. All creatures in the cloud become concealed, and all creatures outside the cloud are concealed to creatures within it. A creature that ends its turn in the cloud must make a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature is sickened 1.</success>
         <fail>The creature is sickened 1, and slowed 1 while in the cloud.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is frightened 2, and slowed 1 while in the cloud.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>The concealed condition is not a poison effect. You can Dismiss the cloud.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Crackling Bubble Gum, Lesser</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>5</level>
      <trait>Alchemical</trait> <trait>Consumable</trait> <trait>Lozenge</trait>
      <price>30 gp</price>
      <usage>held in 1 hand</usage> <bulk>-</bulk>

      <line>This tangy gum cracks and pops in your mouth as you chew it. While you're chewing <![CDATA[<i>lesser crackling bubble gum</i>]]>, for up to 10 minutes, you have a +1 item bonus to saving throws against auditory and sonic effects.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Pop the Bubble</name>
         <trait>sonic</trait>
         <part><name>Effect</name>You blow a bubble with the gum until it pops, after which it becomes inert. The pop deals 4d4 sonic damage in a 15-foot cone with a DC 19 basic Fortitude save. A creature that fails its save is also bound with sticky gum, taking a -10-foot penalty to its Speed for 1 minute. The creature can remove the gum with a total of 3 Interact actions. These actions don't have to be consecutive, and other creatures can provide the actions as well.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Everyneed Pack</title>
      <type>Item</type> <level>3</level>
      <uncommon/> <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Invested</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
      <price>20 gp</price>
      <usage>worn backpack</usage> <bulk>1</bulk>

      <line>Constructed of green material and decorated with a while Glyph of the Open Road, an <![CDATA[<i>everyneed pack</i>]]> has a dozen or more small pockets lning the inside. The pack is enchanted so that each pocket contains common, mundane gear, each item worth no more than 1 gp, such as chalk, flint and steel, and string. It doesn't contain any armor, shields, weapons, or items made of precious material.</line>
      <line>Keep track of the exact value of the gear you retrieve from the pack. The pack becomes a mundane backpack after items of your choice with a combined value of 8 gp have been removed from it.</line>
      <block>
         <name>Activate</name> <type>1 minute (Interact)</type>
      </block>
   </rule>
</catalog>
