<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Prestidigitation</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>10 feet</range> <targets>1 object (cook, lift, or tidy only)</targets>
      <duration>sustained</duration>

      <line>The simplest magic does your bidding. You can perform simple magical effects for as long as you Sustain the Spell. Each time you Sustain the Spell, you can choose one of four options.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Cook</b>]]> Cool, warm, or flavor 1 pound of nonliving material.</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Lift</b>]]> Slowly lift an unattended object of light Bulk or less 1 foot off the ground.</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Make</b>]]> Create a temporary object of negligible Bulk, made of congealed magical substance. The object looks crude and artificial and is extremely fragile; it can't be used as a tool, weapon, or spell component.</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Tidy</b>]]> Color, clean, or soil an object of light Bulk or less. You can affect an object of 1 Bulk with 10 rounds of concentration, and a larger object a 1 minute per Bulk.</entry>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Prestidigitation</i>]]> can't deal damage or cause adverse conditions. Any actual change to an object (beyond what is noted above) persists only as long as you Sustain the Spell.</line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Otherwordly Magic:</b>]]> You gained this cantrip from your Otherwordly Magic ancestry feat. It is an arcane innate spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Acid Splash</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Acid</trait> <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You splash a glob of acid that splatters on your target and nearby creatures. Make a ranged spell attack against your target's AC. If you hit, you deal 1d6 acid damage plus 1 splash acid damage. On a critical success, the target also takes 1 persistent acid damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Detect Magic</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Detection</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>30-foot emanation</area>

      <line>You send out a pulse that registers the presence of magic. You receive no information beyond the rpesence or absence of magic. You can choose to ignore magic you're fully aware of, such as the magic items and ongoing spells of you and your allies.</line>
      <line>You detect illusion magic only if that magic's effect has a lower level than the level of your <![CDATA[<i>detect magic</i>]]> spell. However, items that have an illusion aura but aren't deceptive in appearance (such as an <![CDATA[<i>invisibility potion</i>]]>) typically are detected normally.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Electric Arc</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 or 2 creatures</targets>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>An arc of lightning leaps from one target to another. You deal electricity damage equal to 1d4 plus your spellcasting ability modifier.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gouging Claw</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Morph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You temporarily morph your limb into a clawed appendage. Make a melee spell attack roll against your target's AC. If you hit, you deal your choice of slashing or piercing damage equal to 1d6 plus your spellcasting ability modifier. On a critical success, you deal double damage plus 1d4 persistent bleed damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gale Blast</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>5-foot emanation</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>Wind flows from your outstretched hands and whirls around you in a 5-foot emanation. Each creature in the area takes bludgeoning damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier, with a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage and is pushed 5 feet away from you.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Produce Flame</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A small ball of flame appears in the palm of your hand, and you lash out with it either in melee or at range. Make a spell attack roll against your target's AC. This is normally a ranged attack, but you can also make a melee attack against a creature in your unarmed reach. The flame deals fire damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcastint ability modifier.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage, and 1d4 persistent fire damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scatter Scree</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>two contiguous 5-foot cubes</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You evoke a jumble of rocks in the area. The scattering rocks deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier to creatures in the area, with a basic Reflex save. The ground in the area becomes difficult terrain for the duration. A creature can Interact to clear a square of this scree.</line>
      <line>If you cast this spell again, any previous scree you have scattered ends.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Stabilize</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 dying creature</targets>

      <line>Positive energy shuts death's door. The target loses the dying condition, though it remains unconscious at 0 Hit Points.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tanglefoot</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A vine covered in sticky sap appears from thin air, flicking from your hand and lashing itself to the target. Attempt a ranged spell attack against the taget.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target gains the immobilized condition and takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty and the immobilized condition.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty.</success>
         <fail>The target is unaffected.</fail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Briny Bolt</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You hurl a bolt of salt water from your extended hand. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creatures takes 4d6 bludgeoning damage and is blinded for 1 round and dazzled for 1 minute as salt water sprays into its eyes. The creature can use an Interact action to rub its eyes and end the blinded condition, but not the dazzled condition.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creatures takes 2d6 bludgeoning damage and in blinded for 1 round. The creature can spend an Interact action wiping the salt water from its eyes to end the blinded condition.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Buffeting Winds</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Nonlethal</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>You release a quick burst of wind that batters your living opponents without causing them lasting harm, while also blowing undead away. The wind deals 2d4 bludgeoning damage, which is nonlethal against living creatures. Against undead, the winds are more vicious, and the spell loses the nonlethal trait against such creatures.</line>
      <line>Each creature in the area must attempt a basic Reflex save. On a failure, undead creatures are also knocked back 5 feet (or 10 feet on a critical failure).</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Heal</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1" to="3" />
      <range>varies</range> <targets>1 willing living creature or 1 undead</targets>

      <line>You channel positive energy to heal the living or damage the undead. If the target is a willing living creature, you restore 1d8 Hit Points. If the target is undead, you deal that amount of positive damage to it, and it gets a basic Fortitude save.</line>
      <line>The number of actions you spend when Casting this Spell determines its targets, range, area, and other parameters.</line>
      <line action="1" traits="somatic">The spell has a range of touch.</line>
      <line action="2" traits="somatic, verbal">The spell has a range of 30 feet. If you're healing a living creature, increase the Hit Points restored by 8.</line>
      <line action="3" traits="material, somatic, verbal">You disperse positive energy in a 30-foot emanation. This targets all living and undead creatures in the emanation.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Helpful Steps</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>You call forth a ladder or staircase to help you reach greater heights. The ladder or staircase appears in a space you designate and either stands freely or connects to a nearby wall if possible. You decide the height of the ladder or staircase when casting the spell, up to a maximum height of 40 feet. The ladder or staircase is locked in place and magically supported, allowing you to ascend even if it's in an open area.</line>
      <line>The conjured ladder is simple in design and made of wood. The staircase is a spiral staircase made of wood. While both are supported and have no risk of falling, they can be damaged and destroyed as normal. The staircase is typically easier to ascend, though it's less discreet than a ladder and could possibly draw more attention. You can Dismiss the spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hydraulic Push</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature or unattended object</targets>

      <line>You call forth a powerful blat of pressurized water that bludgeons the target and knocks it back. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes 6d6 bludgeoning damage and is knocked back 10 feet.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes 3d6 bludgeoning damage and is knocked back 5 feet.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shillelagh</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 club or staff you hold</targets>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>The target grows vines and leaves, brimming with primal energy. The target becomes a <![CDATA[<i>+1 striking</i>]]> weapon while in your hands, gaining a +1 item bonus to attack rolls and increasing the number of weapon damage dice to two. Additionally, as long as you are on your home plane, attacks you make with the target against aberrations, extraplanar creatures, and undead increase the number of weapon damage dice to three.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shocking Grasp</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You shroud your hands in a crackling field of lightning. make a melee spell attack roll against the target's AC. On a hit, the target takes 2d12 electricity damage. If the target is wearing metal armor or is made of metal, you gain a +1 circumstance bonus to the your attack roll with <![CDATA[<i>shocking grasp</i>]]>, and the target also takes 1d4 persistent electricity damage on a hit. On a critical hit, double the initial damage, but not the persistent damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spider Sting</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You magically duplicate a spider's venomous sting. You deal 1d4 piercing damage to the touched creature and afflict it with spider venom. The target must attempt a Fortitude save against your spell DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes 1d4 poison damage.</success>
         <fail>The target is afflicted with spider venom at stage 1.</fail>
         <critfail>The target is afflicted with spider venom at stage 2.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line block="">
         <name>Spider Venom</name>
         <part>(poison)</part>
         <part><name>Level</name>1</part>
         <part><name>Maximum Duration</name>4 rounds</part>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Stage 1</name>1d4 poison damage and enfeebled 1 (1 round)</part>
         <part><name>Stage 2</name>1d4 poison damage and enfeebled 2 (1 round)</part>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Summon Animal</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="3">material, somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range>
      <duration>sustained up to 1 minute</duration>

      <line>You conjure an animal to fight for you. You summon a common creature that has the animal trait and whose level is -1, such as those below. The creature gains the summoned and minion traits. Immediately when you finish Casting the Spell, the summoned creature uses its 2 actions for that turn.</line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
