<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>Druid Cantrips</category>
      <title>Acid Splash</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Acid</trait> <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You splash a glob of acid that splatters on your target and nearby creatures. Make a ranged spell attack against your target's AC. If you hit, you deal 1d6 acid damage plus 1 splash acid damage. On a critical success, the target also takes 1 persistent acid damage.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The initial damage increases to 1d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, and the persistent damage increases to 2.</heighten>
      <heighten value="5th">The initial damage increases to 2d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, the persistent damage increases to 3, and the splash damage increases to 2.</heighten>
      <heighten value="7th">The initial damage increases to 3d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, the persistent damage increases to 4, and the splash damage increases to 3.</heighten>
      <heighten value="9th">The initial damage increases to 3d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, the persistent damage increases to 5, and the splash damage increases to 4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Deep Breath</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait>
      <cast action="1">somatic</cast>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>You take an incredibly deep breath and can hold it for the spell's duration. You don't lose breath when hit, but you do lose all the air you inhaled if you speak (including to Cast a Spell). This spell doesn't create air; if you don't have air to breathe when you cast it, you get no benefit.</line>

      <heighten value="2nd">The duration increases to 1 hour, and you lose only 10 minutes of breath if you speak.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">The duration increases to 8 hours, and you lose only 10 minutes of breath if you speak.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Detect Magic</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Detection</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>30-foot emanation</area>

      <line>You send out a pulse that registers the presence of magic. You receive no information beyond the rpesence or absence of magic. You can choose to ignore magic you're fully aware of, such as the magic items and ongoing spells of you and your allies.</line>
      <line>You detect illusion magic only if that magic's effect has a lower level than the level of your <![CDATA[<i>detect magic</i>]]> spell. However, items that have an illusion aura but aren't deceptive in appearance (such as an <![CDATA[<i>invisibility potion</i>]]>) typically are detected normally.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">You learn the school of magic for the highest-level effect within range that the spell detects. If multiple effects are equally strong, the GM determines which you learn.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">As 3rd level, but you also pinpoint the source of the highest-level magic. Like for an imprecise sense, you don't learn the exact location, but you can narrow down the source to within a 5-foot cube (or the nearest if larger than that).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Disrupt Undead</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 undead creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You lance the target with energy. You deal 1d6 positive damage plus your spellcasting ability modifier. The target must attempt a basic Fortitude save. If the creature critically fails the save, it is also enfeebled 1 for 1 round.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Eat Fire</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Fire</trait>
      <cast action="T">somatic</cast>
      <duration>until the end of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You consume and ingest fire, making it less harmful to you. You gain resistance 5 to fire damage until the end of the current turn.</line>
      <line>During the remaining duration of the spell, you can use the Belch Smoke action. The spell ends if you fall unconscious, inhale, or exhale (this includes speaking).</line>
      <block>
         <name>Belch Smoke</name> <action>1</action>
         <part>You exhale what remains of the smoke, ending the spell and creating a smoke cloud in a 5-foot burst within 20 feet. All creatures within the smoke cloud are concealed, and all other creatures are concealed to them. The smoke lasts for 1 minute or until dispersed by a strong wind.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Electric Arc</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 or 2 creatures</targets>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>An arc of lightning leaps from one target to another. You deal electricity damage equal to 1d4 plus your spellcasting ability modifier.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gale Blast</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>5-foot emanation</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>Wind flows from your outstretched hands and whirls around you in a 5-foot emanation. Each creature in the area takes bludgeoning damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier, with a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage and is pushed 5 feet away from you.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Glass Shield</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait>
      <cast action="1">verbal</cast>
      <save>basic Reflex</save> <duration>until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You summon a layer of glass to keep you from harm. This counts as using the Raise a Shield action, giving you a +1 circumstance bonus to AC until the start of your next turn, but it doesn't require a hand to use.</line>
      <line>While the spell is in effect, you can use the Shield Block reaction with your glass shield. The shield has Hardness 2 and 4 Hit Points. If this shield breaks, you can't cast this spell again for 10 minutes and, if the breaker is within 5 feet, they must succeed at a basic Reflex save or take 1d6 piercing damage from the glass shards.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The shield has a Hardness of 4 and 8 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 2d6.</heighten>
      <heighten value="5th">The shield has a Hardness of 7 and 16 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 3d6.</heighten>
      <heighten value="7th">The shield has a Hardness of 10 and 24 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 4d6.</heighten>
      <heighten value="9th">The shield has a Hardness of 14 and 32 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 5d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gouging Claw</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Morph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You temporarily morph your limb into a clawed appendage. Make a melee spell attack roll against your target's AC. If you hit, you deal your choice of slashing or piercing damage equal to 1d6 plus your spellcasting ability modifier. On a critical success, you deal double damage plus 1d4 persistent bleed damage.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6 and the persistent bleed damage on a critical increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Guidance</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1">verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>Until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You ask for divine guidance, granting the target a +1 status bonus to one attack roll, Perception check, saving throw, or skill check the target attempts before the duration ends. The target chooses which roll to use the bonus on before rolling. If the target uses the bonus, the spell ends. Either way, the target is then temporarily immune for 1 hour.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Light</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Light</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 object of 1 Bulk or less, either unattended or possessed by you or a willing ally</targets>
      <duration>until the net time you make your daily preparation</duration>

      <line>The object glows, casting bright light in a 20-foot radius (and dim light for the next 20 feet) like a torch. If you cast this spell again on a second object, the <![CDATA[<i>light</i>]]> spell on the first object ends.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The objects sheds bright light in a 60-foot radius (and dim light for the next 60 feet).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Needle Darts</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Metal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You shape needles out of a piece of metal in your possession and sen them flying in a tight group toward one target. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC. The needles deal 3d4 piercing damage and might cause bleeding.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and 1 persistent bleed damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
      <line>The needles impart any special properties of the metal that forms them; for instance, cold iron needles deal additional damage to creatures with weakness to cold iron. All needles are made of the same metal, and the metal returns to you after the attack.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">You send additional needles, increasing the regular damage by 1d4 and increasing the persistent bleed damage on a critical hit by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Produce Flame</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A small ball of flame appears in the palm of your hand, and you lash out with it either in melee or at range. Make a spell attack roll against your target's AC. This is normally a ranged attack, but you can also make a melee attack against a creature in your unarmed reach. The flame deals fire damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcastint ability modifier.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage, and 1d4 persistent fire damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">Increase the damage by 1d4 and the persistent damage on a critical hit by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Puff of Poison</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Inhaled</trait> <trait>Poison</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>5 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You exhale a shimmering cloud of toxic breath at an enemy's face. The target takes poison damage equal to your spellcasting modifier and 2 persistent poison damage, depending on its Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes half initial and persistent damage.</success>
         <fail>The target takes full initial and persistent damage.</fail>
         <critfail>The target takes double initial and persistent damage.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The initial poison damage increases by 1d8 and the persistent poison damage increases by 2.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ray of Frost</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You blast an icy ray. make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC. The ray deals cold damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and takes a -10-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes normal damage.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Rousing Splash</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You cause a splash of cold water to descend on an ally's head, granting some temporary vigor. The target gains 1d4 temporary Hit Points, which last for 1 minute. The target is then temporarily immune to the temporary Hit Points from <![CDATA[<i>rousing splash</i>]]> for 10 minutes.</line>
      <line>The target can also attempt an immediate flat check to recover from a single source of persistent acid or fire damage, with the DC reduction from appropriate assistance.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The amount of temporary Hit Points granted increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scatter Scree</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>two contiguous 5-foot cubes</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You evoke a jumble of rocks in the area. The scattering rocks deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier to creatures in the area, with a basic Reflex save. The ground in the area becomes difficult terrain for the duration. A creature can Interact to clear a square of this scree.</line>
      <line>If you cast this spell again, any previous scree you have scattered ends.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Stabilize</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 dying creature</targets>

      <line>Positive energy shuts death's door. The target loses the dying condition, though it remains unconscious at 0 Hit Points.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tanglefoot</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A vine covered in sticky sap appears from thin air, flicking from your hand and lashing itself to the target. Attempt a ranged spell attack against the taget.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target gains the immobilized condition and takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty and the immobilized condition.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty.</success>
         <fail>The target is unaffected.</fail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="2nd">The effects last for 2 rounds.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">The effects last for 1 minute.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <category>1st-level Druid Spells</category>
      <title>Briny Bolt</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You hurl a bolt of salt water from your extended hand. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creatures takes 4d6 bludgeoning damage and is blinded for 1 round and dazzled for 1 minute as salt water sprays into its eyes. The creature can use an Interact action to rub its eyes and end the blinded condition, but not the dazzled condition.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creatures takes 2d6 bludgeoning damage and in blinded for 1 round. The creature can spend an Interact action wiping the salt water from its eyes to end the blinded condition.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Buffeting Winds</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Nonlethal</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>You release a quick burst of wind that batters your living opponents without causing them lasting harm, while also blowing undead away. The wind deals 2d4 bludgeoning damage, which is nonlethal against living creatures. Against undead, the winds are more vicious, and the spell loses the nonlethal trait against such creatures.</line>
      <line>Each creature in the area must attempt a basic Reflex save. On a failure, undead creatures are also knocked back 5 feet (or 10 feet on a critical failure).</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Burning Hands</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save> basic Reflex</save>

      <line>Gouts of flame rush from your hands. You deal 2d6 fire damage to creatures in the area.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Conductive Weapon</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Metal</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 metal weapon that is unattended or attended by a willing creature</targets>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You channel powerful electric current through a metal weapon, zapping anyone the item hits. The target becomes a <![CDATA[<i>+1 shocking</i>]]> weapon. If any target of an attack with the weapon is wearing metal armor is is primarily made of metal, the electricity die from the <![CDATA[<i>shock</i>]]> rune is 1d12.</line>
      <line>A weapon with a <![CDATA[<i>shock</i>]]> rune deals an extra 1d6 electricity damage on a hit. On a critical hit, electricity arcs out to deal an equal amount of damage to up to two creatures of the attacker's choice within 10 feet of the target.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dehydrate</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>5-foot burst</area>
      <save>Fortitude (see text)</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You stir the inner fire of all things within the area, driving out moisture. All creatures in the area take 1d6 persistent fire damage with a basic Fortitude save; creatures with the water or plant traits get a result one degree of success worse than they rolled. The spell ends for a creature when its persistent damage ends.</line>
      <line>A creature affected by <![CDATA[<i>dehydrate</i>]]> attempts an additional Fortitude save at the end of each of its turns, before rolling to recover from the persistent damage. It can forgo this additional save if it consumed water or similar hydrating liquid within the last round (typically, drinking requires a single action).</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>The creature takes no additional effect.</success>
         <fail>The creature is enfeebled 1 until the end of its next turn.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is enfeebled 2 until the end of its next turn.</critfail>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+2">The range increases by 10 feet, the burst increases by 5 feet, and the persistent fire damage increases by 3d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Flourishing Flora</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Wood</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>5-foot burst</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>Plants rapidly grow up from the ground. All creatures in the target area take 2d4 damage. The type of damage depends on the type of plant you choose to grow. On a critical failure, targets experience additional effects, also depending on what you choose to grow. The type of plant and its effects are chosen when you Cast the Spell.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Cacti">Piercing damage, and 1 persistent bleed damage on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Flowers">Poison damage, and dazzled for 2 rounds on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Fruits">Bludgeoning damage, and clumsy 1 for 2 rounds on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Roots">Bludgeoning damage, and the affected creatures fall prone on a critical failure.</entry>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4, and the persistent bleed damage from cacti increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gust of Wind</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>60-foot line</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save> <duration>until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>A violent wind issues forth from your palm, blowing from the point where you are when you cast the spell to the line's opposite end. The wind extinguishes small non-magical fires, disperses fog and mist, blows objects of light Bulk or less around, and pushes larger objects. Large or smaller creatures in the area must attempt a Fortitude save. Large or smaller creatures that later move into the gust must attempt the save when entering.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature can't move against the wind.</success>
         <fail>The creature is knocked prone. If it was flying, it suffers the effects of critical failure instead.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is pushed 30 feet in the wind's direction, knocked prone, and takes 2d6 bludgeoning damage.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Heal</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1" to="3">varies</cast>
      <range>varies</range> <targets>1 willing living creature or 1 undead</targets>

      <line>You channel positive energy to heal the living or damage the undead. If the target is a willing living creature, you restore 1d8 Hit Points. If the target is undead, you deal that amount of positive damage to it, and it gets a basic Fortitude save.</line>
      <line>The number of actions you spend when Casting this Spell determines its targets, range, area, and other parameters.</line>
      <line action="1" traits="somatic">The spell has a range of touch.</line>
      <line action="2" traits="somatic, verbal">The spell has a range of 30 feet. If you're healing a living creature, increase the Hit Points restored by 8.</line>
      <line action="3" traits="material, somatic, verbal">You disperse positive energy in a 30-foot emanation. This targets all living and undead creatures in the emanation.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The amount of damage or healing increases by 1d8, and the extra healing for the 2-action version increases by 8.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Helpful Steps</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>You call forth a ladder or staircase to help you reach greater heights. The ladder or staircase appears in a space you designate and either stands freely or connects to a nearby wall if possible. You decide the height of the ladder or staircase when casting the spell, up to a maximum height of 40 feet. The ladder or staircase is locked in place and magically supported, allowing you to ascend even if it's in an open area.</line>
      <line>The conjured ladder is simple in design and made of wood. The staircase is a spiral staircase made of wood. While both are supported and have no risk of falling, they can be damaged and destroyed as normal. The staircase is typically easier to ascend, though it's less discreet than a ladder and could possibly draw more attention. You can Dismiss the spell.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The maximum height increases by 40 feet.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hydraulic Push</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature or unattended object</targets>

      <line>You call forth a powerful blat of pressurized water that bludgeons the target and knocks it back. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes 6d6 bludgeoning damage and is knocked back 10 feet.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes 3d6 bludgeoning damage and is knocked back 5 feet.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Jump</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Move</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="1">somatic</cast>

      <line>Your legs surge with strength, ready to leap high or far. You jump 30 feet in any direction without touching the ground. You must land on a space of solid ground, or else you fall after using your next action.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The range becomes touch, the target changes to one touched creature, and the duration becomes 1 minute, allowing the target to jump as described whenever it takes the Leap action.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Longstrider</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>

      <line>You lengthen your stride beyond what should be possible. You gain a +10-foot status bonus to your speed.</line>

      <heighten value="2nd">The duration increases to 8 hours.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Mud Pit</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="3">material, somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <area>squares on the ground in a 15-foot burst</area>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>Thick, clinging mud covers the ground, 1 foot deep. The mud is difficult terrain.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Pummeling Rubble</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>A spray of heavy rocks flies through the air in front of you. The rubble deals 2d4 bludgeoning damage to each creature in the area. Each creature must attempt a Reflex save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage and is pushed 5 feet away from you.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you.</critfail>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shillelagh</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 club or staff you hold</targets>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>The target grows vines and leaves, brimming with primal energy. The target becomes a <![CDATA[<i>+1 striking</i>]]> weapon while in your hands, gaining a +1 item bonus to attack rolls and increasing the number of weapon damage dice to two. Additionally, as long as you are on your home plane, attacks you make with the target against aberrations, extraplanar creatures, and undead increase the number of weapon damage dice to three.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shocking Grasp</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You shroud your hands in a crackling field of lightning. make a melee spell attack roll against the target's AC. On a hit, the target takes 2d12 electricity damage. If the target is wearing metal armor or is made of metal, you gain a +1 circumstance bonus to the your attack roll with <![CDATA[<i>shocking grasp</i>]]>, and the target also takes 1d4 persistent electricity damage on a hit. On a critical hit, double the initial damage, but not the persistent damage.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d12, and the persistent electricity damage increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shockwave</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>You create a wave of energy that ripples through the earth. Terrestrial creatures in the affected area must attempt a Reflex save to avoid stumbling as the shockwave shakes the ground.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature is flat-footed until the start of its next turn.</success>
         <fail>The creature falls prone.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature falls prone plus takes 1d6 damage.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The area increases by 5 feet (to a 20-foot cone at 2nd spell level, and so on).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Snowball</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You throw a magically propelled and chilled ball of dense snow. The target takes 2d4 cold damage and potentially other effects, depending on the result of your ranged spell attack roll.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and a -10-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage and a -5-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</success>
         <fail>No effect.</fail>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spider Sting</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You magically duplicate a spider's venomous sting. You deal 1d4 piercing damage to the touched creature and afflict it with spider venom. The target must attempt a Fortitude save against your spell DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes 1d4 poison damage.</success>
         <fail>The target is afflicted with spider venom at stage 1.</fail>
         <critfail>The target is afflicted with spider venom at stage 2.</critfail>
      </line>
      <block>
         <name>Spider Venom</name>
         <part>(poison)</part>
         <part><name>Level</name>1</part>
         <part><name>Maximum Duration</name>4 rounds</part>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Stage 1</name>1d4 poison damage and enfeebled 1 (1 round)</part>
         <part><name>Stage 2</name>1d4 poison damage and enfeebled 2 (1 round)</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Thunderstrike</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Sonic</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>You call down a tendril of lightning that cracks with thunder, dealing 1d12 electricity damage and 1d4 sonic damage to the target with a basic Reflex save. A target wearing metal armor or made of metal takes a -1 circumstance penalty to its save and, if damaged by the spell, is clumsy 1 for 1 round.</line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d12 electricity and 1d4 sonic.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <category>2nd-level Druid Spells</category>
      <title>Barkskin</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>The target's skin becomes covered in bark. The target gains resistance 2 to bludgeoning and piercing damage and weakness 3 to fire. After the target takes fire damage, it can Dismiss the spell as a free action triggered by taking the damage; doing so doesn't reduce the fire damage the target was dealt.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">The resistance increases by 2, and the weakness increases by 3.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Brine Dragon Bile</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Acid</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="R">verbal</cast>
      <trigger>A creature within range takes damage from a slashing or piercing attack, or one that inflicts persistent bleed damage</trigger>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>the creature that took damage</targets>

      <line>You spit a glob of caustic saltwater that stings the wounds of the creature. Make a ranged spell attack against the triggering creature's AC. On a hit, salt scours its open wound, dealing 2d6 persistent acid damage, or 2d10 persistent acid damage on a critical hit.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">The persistent damage increases by two dice.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Create Food</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast>1 hour (somatic, verbal)</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range>

      <line>You create enough food to feed six Medium creatures for a day. This food is bland and unappealing, but it is nourishing. After 1 day, if no one has eaten the food, it decause and becomes inedible. Most Small creatures eat one-quarter as much as a Medium creature (one-sixteenth as much for most Tiny creatures), and most Large creatures eat 10 times as much (100 times as much for Huge creatures and so on).</line>

      <heighten value="4th">You can feed 12 Medium creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">You can feed 50 Medium creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="8th">You can feed 200 Medium creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Enlarge</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Polymorph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>
      <duration>5 minutes</duration>

      <line>Bolstered by magical power, the target grows to size Large. Its equipment grows with it but returns to natural size if removed. The creature is clumsy 1. Its reach increases by 5 feet (or by 10 feet if it started out Tiny), and it gains a +2 status bonus to melee damage. This spell has no effect on a Large or larger creature.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The creature instead grows to size Huge. The status bonus to melee damage is +4 and the creature's reach increases by 10 feet (or 15 feet if the creature started out Tiny). The spell has no effect on a Huge or larger creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">Choose either the 2nd-level or 4th-level version of this spell and apply its effects to up to 10 willing creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Flaming Sphere</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>1 5-foot square</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>
      <duration>sustained up to 1 minute</duration>

      <line>You create a sphere of flame in a square within range. The sphere deals 3d6 fire damage to each creature in the square where it first appears, with a basic Reflex save.</line>
      <line>When you Sustain this spell, you can move the sphere up to 10 feet. It then deals damage to each creature whose space it shared at any point during the move. This uses the same damage and save, and you roll the damage once each time you Sustain.</line>
      <line>A given creature can take damage from the flaming sphere only once per round.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fungal Infestation</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>Toxic spores swarm over creatures in the area, causing them to erupt in grotesque fungal growths. These noxious growths deal 2d6 persistent poison damage, and each creature must attempt a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes half the persistent damage.</success>
         <fail>The target takes the full persistent poison damage. While it is taking this persistent poison damage, it has weakness 1 to fire and weakness 1 to slashing.</fail>
         <critfail>The target takes double the persistent damage. While it is taking this persistent poison damage, it has weakness 2 to fire and weakness 2 to slashing.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The persistent damage increases by 2d6, and the weakness increases by 1, or by 2 on a critical failure.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gentle Breeze</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <area>40-foot burst</area>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>A light, soothing breeze flows through the area, making it easier to rest and recover. Medicine checks attempted to benefit living creatures in the area get a +2 status bonus. Any living creature in the area also gets a +2 status bonus to saving throws against afflictions and, if it remains within the area for the full duration, regains 10 Hit Points.</line>
      <line>In addition, the cool breeze reduces the temperature effects of heat by one step for any creature in the area.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">The healing increses by 10 Hit Points.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Glitterdust</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>10-foot burst</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>Creatures in the area are outlined by glittering dust. Each creature must attempt a Reflex save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target's invisibility is negated for 2 rounds.</success>
         <fail>The target is dazzled for 1 minute and its invisibility is negated for 1 minute.</fail>
         <critfail>The target is blinded for 1 round and dazzled for 10 minutes. Its invisibility is negated for 10 minutes.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>If a creature has its invisibility negated by this spell, it is concealed instead of invisible. This applies both if the creature was already invisible and if it benefits from new invisibility effects before the end of the invisibility negation from this spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <!-- <rule>
      <title>Obscuring Mist</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="3">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>20-foot burst</area>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You call forth a cloud of mist. All creatures within the mist become concealed (a creature must succeed a a flat DC 5 check to target the concealed creature with an attack, spell, or other effect), and all creatures outside the mist become concealed to creatures within it.</line>
      <line>You can Dismiss the cloud.</line>
   </rule> -->

   <rule>
      <title>Resist Energy</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>A shield of shimmering elemental energy protects a creature against one type of energy damage. Choose acid, cold, electricity, fire, or sonic damage. The target and its gear gain resistance 5 against the damage type you chose.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The resistance increases to 10, and you can target up to two creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="7th">The resistance increases to 15, and you can target up to five creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Restoration</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast>1 minute (somatic, verbal)</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>Restorative magic counters the effects of toxins or conditions that prevent a creature from functioning at its best. When you cast <![CDATA[<i>restoration</i>]]>, choose to either reduce a condition or lessen the effect of a toxin. A creature can benefit from one one <![CDATA[<i>restoration</i>]]> spell each day, and it can't benefit from <![CDATA[<i>restoration</i>]]> more than once to reduce the stage of the same exposure to a given toxin.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Lessen a Toxin">Reduce the stage of one toxin the target suffers from by one stage. This can't reduce the stage below stage 1 or cure the affliction.</entry>
         <entry name="Reduce a Condition">Reduce the value of the target's clumsy, enfeebled, or stupefied condition by 2. You can instead reduce two of the listed conditions by 1 each.</entry>
      </line>

      <heighten value="4th">Add drained to the list of conditions you can reduce. When you lessen a toxin, reduce the stage by two. You also gain a third option that allows you to reduce the target's doomed value by 1. You can't use this to reduce a permanent doomed condition.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">As the 4th-level <![CDATA[<i>restoration</i>]]>, but you can reduce a permanent doomed condition if you add a material component to Casting the Spell, providing 100 gp worth of diamond dust as a cost.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Splinter Volley</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Wood</trait>
      <cast action="2" or="3">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 or 2 creatures</targets>

      <line>You launch a volley of splinters at your foes. Make a ranged spell attack roll against a single creature's AC. On a hit, the splinters deal 4d6 piercing damage. On a critical hit, the splinters deal double damage and 1 persistent bleed damage.</line>
      <line>You can spend a third action while casting this spell to fire splinters at two different targets instead of one. These attacks each increase your multiple attack penalty, but you don't increase your multiple attack penalty until after you make both spell attack rolls for <![CDATA[<i>splinter volley</i>]]>.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">Increase the damage dealt to each target by 4d6, and the persistent bleed damage on a critical hit by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Water Walk</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>The target can walk on the surface of the water and other liquids without falling through. It can go underwater if it wishes, but in that case it must Swim normally. This spell doesn't grant the ability to breathe underwater.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The spell's range increases to 30 feet, the duration increases to 1 hour, and you can target up to 10 creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Web</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="3">material, somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>10-foot burst</area>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You create a sticky web in the area that impedes creatures' movement each time they try to move through it. Squares filled with the web are difficult terrain. Each square can be cleared of the web by a single attack or effect that deals at least 5 slashing damage or 1 fire damage. A square has AC 5, and it automatically fails its saving throws.</line>
      <line>Each time a creature in the web begins to use a move action or enters the web during a move action, it must attempt an Athletics check or Reflex save against your spell DC to avoid taking a circumstance penalty to its Speeds or becoming immobilized. A creature that gets out of the web ceases to take the circumstance penalty to its Speed from the web.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected, and it doesn't need to attempt further Athletics checks or saving throws against the web this turn. If it used an Athletics check, it clears the web from every square it leaves after leaving the square.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature is unaffected during its action. If it used an Athletics check, it clears the web from every square it leaves after leaving the square.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speeds until the start of its next turn.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is immobilized until the start of its next turn, after which it takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speeds for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape to remove its immobilized condition.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="4th">The spell's area increases to a 20-foot burst, and its range increases to 60 feet.</heighten>
   </rule>
</catalog>
