<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Darkvision</title>

      <line>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Unbreakable Goblin</title>

      <line>You're able to bounce back from injuries easily due to an exceptionally thick skull, cartilaginous bones, or some other mixed blessing. You gain 10 Hit Points from your ancestry instead of 6. When you fall, reduce the falling damage you take as though you had fallen half the distance.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>City Scavenger</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Goblin</trait>

      <line>You know that the greatest treasures often look like refuse, and you scoff at those who throw away good scraps. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to checks to Subists, and you can use Society or Survival when you Subsist in a settlement.</line>
      <line>When you Subsist in a city, you also gather valuable junk that silly longshanks threw away. You can Earn Income using Society or Survival in the same time as you Subsist, without spending any additional days of downtime. You also gain a +1 circumstance bonus to this check.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Pickpocket</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Thievery</prereq>

      <line>You can Steal or Palm an Object that's closely guarded, such as in a pocket, without taking the -5 penalty. You can't steal objects that would be extremely noticeable or time consuming to remove (like worn shoes or armor or actively wielded objects). If you're a Master in Thievery, you can attempt to Steal from a creature in combat or otherwise on guard. When doing so, Stealing is a 2-action activity instead 1 action, and you take a -5 penalty.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Palm an Object</title>
      <type>Thievery</type>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait>

      <line>Palming a small, unattended object without being noticed requires you to roll a single Thievery check against the Perception DCs of all creatures who are currently observing you. You take the object whether or not you successfully conceal that you did so. You can typically only Palm Objects of negligible Bulk, though the GM might determine otherwise depending on the situation.</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>The creature does not notice you Palming the Object.</success>
         <fail>The creature notices you Palming the Object, and the GM determines the creature's response.</fail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Steal</title>
      <type>Thievery</type>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait>

      <line>You try to take a small object from another creature without being noticed. Typically, you can Steal only an object of negligible Bulk, and you automatically fail if the creature who has the object is in combat or on guard.</line>
      <line>Attempt a Thievery check to determine if you successfully Steal the object. The DC to Steal is usually the Perception DC of the creature wearing the object. This assumes the object is worn but not closely guarded (like a loosely carried pouch filled with coins, or an object within such a pouch). If the object is in a pocket or similarly protected, you take a -5 penalty to your Thievery check. The GM might increase the DC of your check if the nature of the object makes it harder to steal (such as a very small item in a large pack, or a sheet of parchment mixed in with other documents).</line>
      <line>You might also need to compare your Thievery check result against the Perception DCs of observers other than the person wearing the object. The GM may decrease the Perception DCs of these observers if they're distracted.</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>You Steal the item without the bearer noticing, or an observer doesn't see you take or attempt to take the item.</success>
         <fail>The item's bearer notices your attempt before you can take the object, or an observer sees you take or attempt to take the item. The GM determines the response of any creature that notices your theft.</fail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Experienced Smuggler</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Stealth</prereq>

      <line>You often smuggle things past the authorities. When the GM rolls your Stealth check to see if a passive observer notices that you have Concealed an Object, the GM uses the number rolled or 10 (whichever is higher) as the result of your die roll, adding it to your Stealth modifier to determine your Stealth check result. If you're a Master in Stealth, the GM uses the number rolled or 15, and if you're Legendary in Stealth, you automatically succeed at Concealing the Object.</line>
      <line>This provides no benefits when a creature attempts a Perception check while actively searching you for hidden items. Due to your smuggling skill, you're more likely to find more lucrative smuggling jobs when using Underworld Lore to Earn Income.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Conceal an Object</title>
      <type>Stealth</type>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Secret</trait>

      <line>You hide a small object on your person (such as weapon of light Bulk). When you try to sneak a concealed object past someone who might notice it, the GM rolls your Stealth check and compares it to this passive observer's Perception DC. Once the GM rolls your check for a concealed object, that same result is used no matter how many passive observers you try to sneak it past. If a creature is specifically searching you for an item, it can attempt a Perception check against your Stealth DC instead (finding it on a success).</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>The object remains undetected.</success>
         <fail>The observer finds the object.</fail>
      </line>
      <line>You can also Conceal an Object somewhere other than your person, such as among undergrowth or in a secret compartment within a piece of furniture. In this case, characters Seeking in an area compare their Perception check result to your Stealth DC to determine whether they find the object.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Thief Racket</title>

      <line>Nothing beats the thrill of taking something that belongs to someone else, especially if you can do so completely unnoticed. You might be a pickpocket working the streets, a cat burglar sneaking through windows and escaping via rooftops, or a safecracker breaking into carefully guarded vaults. You might even work as a consultant, testing clients' defenses by trying to steal something precious.</line>
      <line>When a fight breaks out, you prefer swift, lightweight weapons, and you strike where it hurts. When you attack with a finesse melee weapon, you can add your Dexterity modifier to damage rolls instead of your Strength modifier.</line>
      <line>You are trained in Thievery.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sneak Attack</title>

      <line>When your enemy can't properly defend itself, you take advantage to deal extra damage. If you Strike a creature that has the flat-footed condition with an agile or finesse melee weapon, an agile or finesse unarmed attack, a ranged weapon attack, or a ranged unarmed attack, you deal an extra 1d6 precision damage. For a ranged attack with a thrown weapon, that weapon must also be agile or finesse.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Surprise Attack</title>

      <line>You spring into combat faster than foes can react. On the first round of combat, if you rolled Deception or Stealth for initiative, creatures that haven't acted are flat-footed to you.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Avoid Notice</title>
      <trait>Exploration</trait>

      <line>You attempt a Stealth check to Avoid Notice while traveling at half speed. If you have the Swift Sneak skill feat, you can move at full Speed rather than half, but you still can't use another exploration activity while you do so. If you have the Legendary Sneak skill feat, you can move at full Speed and use a second exploration activity.</line>
      <line>If you're Avoiding Notice at the start of an encounter, you usually roll a Stealth check instead of a Perception check both to determine your initiative and to see if the enemies notice you (based on their Perception DCs, as normal for Sneak, regardless of their initiative check results).</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Trap Finder</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Rogue</trait>

      <line>You have an intuitive sense that alerts you to the dangers and presence of traps. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to Perception checks to find traps, to AC against attacks made by traps, and to saves against traps. Even if you aren't Searching, you get a check to find traps that normally require you to be Searching. You still need to meet any other requirements to find the trap.</line>
      <line>You can disable traps that require a proficiency rank of master in Thievery. If you have master proficiency in Thievery, you can disable traps that require a proficiency rank of Legendary instead, and your circumstance bonuses against traps increase to +2.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Search</title>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Exploration</trait>

      <line>You Seek meticulously for hidden doors, concealed hazards, and so on. You can usually make an educated guess as to which locations are best to check and move at half speed, but if you want to be thorough and guarantee you checked everything, you need to travel at a Speed of no more than 300 feet per minute, or 150 feet per minute to ensure you check everything before you walk into it. You can always move more slowly while Searching to cover the area more throughly, and the Expeditious Search feat increases these maximum Speeds. If you come across a secret door, item, or hazard while Searching, the GM will attempt a free secret check to Seek to see if you notice the hidden object or hazard. In locations with many objects to search, you have to stop and spend significantly longer to search thoroughly.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Disable a Device</title>
      <action>2</action>
      <type>Thievery</type>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <requirement>Some devices require you to use thieves' tools when disabling them.</requirement>

      <line>This action allows you to disarm a trap or another complex device. Often, a device requires numerous successes before becoming disabled, depending on its construction and complexity. Thieves' tools are helpful and sometimes even required to Disable a Device, as determined by the GM, and sometimes a device requires a higher proficiency rank in Thievery to disable.</line>
      <line>Your Thievery check result determines how much progress you make.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You disable the device, or you achiever two successes towards disabling a complex device. You leave no trace of your tampering, and you can rearm the device later, if that type of device can be rearmed.</critsuccess>
         <success>You disable the device, or you achieve one success towards disabling a complex device.</success>
         <critfail>You trigger the device, if appropriate.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Earn Income</title>
      <type>Varies</type>
      <trait>Downtime</trait>

      <line>You use one of your skills to make money during downtime. The GM assigns a task level representing the most lucrative job available. You can search for lower-level tasks, with the GM determining whether you find any. Sometimes you can attempt to find better work than the initial offerings, though this takes time and requires using the Diplomacy skill to Gather Information, doing some research, or socializing.</line>
      <line>When you take on a job, the GM secretly sets the DC of your skill check. After your first day of work, you roll to determine your earnings. You gain an amount of income based on your result, the task's level, and your proficiency rank.</line>
      <line>You can continue working at the task on subsequent days without needing to roll again. For each day you spend after the first, you earn the same amount as the first day, up until the task's completion. The GM determines how long you can work at the task. Most tasks last a week or two, though some can take months or even years.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You do outstanding work. Gain the amount of currency listed for the task level +1 and your proficiency rank.</critsuccess>
         <success>You do compenent work. Gain the amount of currency listed for the task level and your proficiency rank.</success>
         <fail>You do shoddy work and get paid the bare minimum for your time. Gain the amount of currency listed in the failure column for the task level. The GM will likely reduce how long you can continue at the task.</fail>
         <critfail>You earn nothing for your work and are fired immediately. YOu can't continue at the task. Your reputation suffers, potentially making it difficult for you to find rewarding jobs in that community in the future.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Income earned per day</b>]]></line>
      <line list="">
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 0 task (DC 14):</b> <i>Failure</i> 1 cp; <i>Trained</i> 5 cp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 1 task (DC 15):</b> <i>Failure</i> 2 cp; <i>Trained</i> 2 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 2 task (DC 16):</b> <i>Failure</i> 4 cp; <i>Trained</i> 3 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 3 task (DC 18):</b> <i>Failure</i> 8 cp; <i>Trained</i> 5 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 4 task (DC 19):</b> <i>Failure</i> 1 sp; <i>Trained</i> 7 sp; <br /><i>Expert</i> 8 sp]]></entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Level 5 task (DC 20):</b> <i>Failure</i> 2 sp; <i>Trained</i> 9 sp; <br /><i>Expert</i> 1 gp]]></entry>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Subsist</title>
      <type>Varies</type>
      <trait>Downtime</trait>

      <line>You try to provide food and shelter for yourself, and possibly others as well, with a standard of living. The GM determines the DC based on the nature of the place where you're trying to Subsist. You might need a minimum proficiency rank to Subsist in particularly strange environments. Unlike most downtime activities, you can Subsist after 8 hours or less of exploration, but if you do, you take a -5 penalty.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>You either provide a subsistence living for yourself and one additional creature, or you improve your own food and shelter, granting yourself a comfortable living.</critsuccess>
         <success>You find enough food and shelter with basic protection from the elements to provide you a subsistence living.</success>
         <fail>You're exposed to the elements and don't get enough food, becoming fatigued until you attain sufficient food and shelter.</fail>
         <critfail>You attract trouble, eat something you shouldn't, or otherwise worsen your situation. You take a -2 circumstance penalty to checks to Subsist for 1 week. You don't find food at all; if you don't have any stored up, you're in danger of starving or dying of thirst if you continue failing.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<b>Sample Subsist Task Difficulties</b>]]></line>
      <line list="">
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Untrained (DC 10):</b>]]> lush forest with calm weather or large city with plentiful resources</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Trained (DC 15):</b>]]> typical hillside or village</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Expert (DC 20):</b>]]> typical mountains or insular hamlet</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Master (DC 30):</b>]]> typical desert or city under siege</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Legendary (DC 40):</b>]]> barren wasteland or city of undead</entry>
      </line>
   </rule>
</catalog>
