@ -0,0 +1,89 @@
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <rule>
      <title>Greataxe</title>
      <trait>Sweep</trait>
      <price>2 gp</price> <damage>1d12 S</damage>
      <hands>2</hands> <bulk>2</bulk>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Martial</weapcat> <weapgroup>Axe</weapgroup>

      <line>This large axe is too heavy to wield with one hand. Many greataxes incorporate two blades, and they are often "bearded", having a hook at the bottom to increase the strength of their chopping power.</line>

      <traittext><name>Sweep</name>This weapon makes wide sweeping or spinning attacks, maknig it easier to attack multiple enemies. When you attack with this weapon, you gain a +1 circumstance bonus to your attack roll if you already attempted to attack a different target this turn using this weapon.</traittext>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">+1 Potency</rune> <level>2</level>
         <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>35 gp</price>

         <line>Magical enhancements make this weapon strike true. Attack rolls with this weapon gain a +1 item bonus, and the weapon can be etched with one property rune.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">Striking</rune> <level>4</level>
         <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>65 gp</price>

         <line>A <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune stores destructive magic in the weapon, increasing the weapon damage dice it deals to two instead of one.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">Fearsome</rune> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>160 gp</price>

         <line>When you critically hit with this weapon, the target becomes frightened 1.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weapon Specialization, Axe</title>
      <line>Choose one creature adjacent to the initial target and within reach. If its AC is lower than your attack roll result for the critical hit, you deal damage to that creature equal to the result of the weapon damage die you rolled (including extra dice for the <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune, if any). This amount isn't doubled, and no bonus or other additional dice apply to this damage.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scythe</title>
      <trait>Deadly d10</trait> <trait>Trip</trait>
      <price>2 gp</price> <damage>1d10 S</damage>
      <hands>2</hands> <bulk>2</bulk>
      <weaptype>Melee</weaptype> <weapcat>Martial</weapcat> <weapgroup>Polearm</weapgroup>

      <line>Derived from a farming tool used to mow down long grains and cereals, this weapon has a long wooden shaft with protruding handles, capped with a curved blade set at a right angle.</line>

      <traittext><name>Deadly d10</name>On a critical hit, the weapon adds a weapon damage die of the listed size, rolled after doubling the weapon's damage. This increases to two dice if the weapon has a <![CDATA[<i>greater striking</i> rune and three dice if the weapon has a <i>major striking rune</i>]]>. An ability that changes the size of the weapon's normal damage dice doesn't change the size of its deadly die.</traittext>
      <traittext><name>Trip</name>You can use this weapon to Trip with the Athletics skill even if you don't have a free hand. This uses the weapon's reach (if different from your own) and adds the weapon's item bonus to attack rolls as an item bonus to the Athletics check. If you critically fail a check to Trip using the weapon, you can drop the weapon to take the effects of a failure instead of a critical failure.</traittext>

      <variant>
         <rune italic="">+1 Potency</rune> <level>2</level>
         <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>35 gp</price>

         <line>Magical enhancements make this weapon strike true. Attack rolls with this weapon gain a +1 item bonus, and the weapon can be etched with one property rune.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">Striking</rune> <level>4</level>
         <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Magical</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>65 gp</price>

         <line>A <![CDATA[<i>striking</i>]]> rune stores destructive magic in the weapon, increasing the weapon damage dice it deals to two instead of one.</line>
      </variant>
      <variant>
         <rune italic="">Fearsome</rune> <level>5</level>
         <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Magical</trait> <trait>Mental</trait>
         <usage>etched onto the weapon</usage>
         <price>160 gp</price>

         <line>When you critically hit with this weapon, the target becomes frightened 1.</line>
      </variant>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weapon Specialization, Polearm</title>
      <line>The target is moved 5 feet in a direction of your choice. This is forced movement.</line>
   </rule>

</catalog>
