<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Eladrin</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Fey</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Graceful warriors and wizards at home in the eldritch twilight of the Feywild</shortfluff>
	
	<height>5'5" - 6'1"</height>
	<weight>130 - 180</weight>
	
	<ability>Intelligence</ability>
  <ability>Dexterity</ability>
  <ability>Charisma</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Low-light Vision</vision>
	
	<language>Common</language> <language>Elven</language>
	
	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
		<description>+2 Arcana, +2 History</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Eladrin Education</name>
		<description>You gain training in one skill of your choice.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Eladrin Weapon Proficiency</name>
		<description>You gain proficiency with the longsword.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Eladrin Will</name>
		<description>You gain a +5 racial bonus to saving throws against Charm effects.</description>
		<description>If you chose Dexterity for your ability bonus, you also gain a +1 racial bonus to Will defense.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Fey Origin</name>
		<description>Your ancestors were native to the Feywild, so your origin is fey instead of a natural.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Trance</name>
		<description>Rather than sleep, eladrin enter a meditative state known as trance. You need to spend 4 hours in this state to gain the same benefits other races gain from taking a 6-hour extended rest.</description>
		<description>While in a trance, you are fully aware of your surroundings and notice approaching enemies and other events normally.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Eladrin Racial Power</name>
		<description>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>fey step</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>
	
	<fluff>Creatures of magic with strong ties to nature, eladrin live in cities in the twilight realm of the Feywild. Their cities lie cose enough to the world that they sometimes cross over, appearing briefly in mountain valleys or deep forest glades before fading back into the Feywild.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play an eladrin if you want to: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be otherworldly and mysterious.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be graceful and intelligent.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to teleport around the battlefield, cloaked in the magic of the Feywild.</fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Fey Step</title>
			<class>Eladrin</class> <category>Utility</category>
			<fluff>With a step, you vanish from one place and appear in another</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
				<action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You teleport up to 5 squares.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Eladrin are of human height. They are slim, and even the strongest simply look athletic rather than muscle-bound. They have the same range of complexions as humans, though they are more often fair than dark. Their straight, fine hair is often white, silver, or pale gold, and they wear it long and loose. Their ears are long and pointed, and their eyes are pearly and opalescent orbs of vibrant blue, violet, or green, lacking pupils. Eladrin can't grow facial hair and have little body hair.</benefit>
		<benefit>Eladrin children grow much as homan children do, but their aging process slows to a crawl when they reach maturity. They enjoy youth and health for most of their lives and don't begin to feel the effects of age until the middle of their third century. Most live for over 300 years, and even at the end they suffer few of the infirmities of old age.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Playing an Eladrin</name>
		<benefit>Eladrin society straddles the boundary between the Feywild and and the natural world. Eladrin build their elegant cities and towers in places of striking natural splendor, especially where the vail between the worlds is thin: isolated mountain vales, green islands along wild and storm-wracked coasts, and the deepest recesses of ancient forests. Some eladrin realms exist mostly in the Feywild, only rarely touching the world, while others appear in the world at sunset each day, only to fade back into the Feywild at dawn.</benefit>
		<benefit>Long-lived and strongly tied to the Feywild, eladrin have a detached view of the world. Eladrin often have difficulty believing that events in the world have much importance to them, and they consider courses of action that can last for centuries.</benefit>
		<benefit>Their general detachment from the world can make eladrin seem distant and intimidating to other races. Their fey nature also makes them simultaneously alluring and a little frightening. However, eladrin take friendships and alliances to heart and can react with swift fury when their friends are endangered. Combined with their intellect, bravery, and magical power, this loyalty makes them powerful and respected allies.</benefit>
		<benefit>Eladrin live by an aesthetic philosophy common to the Feywild and personified by Corellon, the god of beauty and patron of the fey. Eladrin seek to exemplify grace, skill, and learning in every part of life, from dance and song to swordplay and magic. Their cities are places of stunning beauty that shape and guide their natural surroundings into elegant forms.</benefit>
		<benefit>Eladrin are close cousins to the elves and are occasionally called high elves or gray elves. Eladrin favor the Feywild and arcane magic more than elves do, but the two races hold each other in high regard. They share a burning hatred for the third branch of their race -the drow.</benefit>
		<benefit>The Feywild's most powerful eladrin, called noble eladrin, become so infused with their realm's inherent magic that they transform into entirely new creatures. These noble eladrin take on characteristics of the seasons and other natural phenomena.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Eladrin Charasteristics:</b>]]> Aesthetic, deliberative, detached, free, graceful, magical, otherworldly, patient, perceptive</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Aramil, Arannis, Berrian, Dayereth, Erevan, Galinndan, Hadarai, Immeral, Mindartis, Paelias, Quarion, Riardon, Soveliss</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Althaea, Anastrianna, Andraste, Bethrynna, Caelynna, Jelenneth, Leshanna, Meriele, Naivara, Quelenna, Sariel, Shanairra, Theirasta, Valenae</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Sample Eladrin Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Brandis, Human Fighter</name>
			<benefit>Brandis is a mercenary who has sold his sword arm to every baronet, duke, and princeling from the mountains to the coast. His armor is practical, lacking any decoration, and his sword is intended only for battle, not as a mark of prestige. He prays daily to the Raven Queen -not out of devotion but because he knows that death is inevitable and he hopes to postpone it as long as possible.</benefit>
			<benefit>He began adventuring after a mission ended in disaster. His soldier companions were all dead, and he was captured by hobgoblins and held for ransom that no one cared enough to pay. He joined the band of adventurers that slew the hobgoblins. He has since found adventuring both more lucrative and more satisfying than his previous life.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Mari, Human Ranger</name>
			<benefit>Mari's eyes are always on the horizon. She is driven by a passion for exploration and a love of new places. She dreams of ultimately establishing a new settlement in a place where people can live in peace and freedom. She prays to Avandra for protection in her wandering and to Erathis for help in achieving her dreams.</benefit>
			<benefit>She is aware of her life's contradiction: She is a creature of the wilderness, but her dream is to tame and cultivate it. A part of her wonders whether she would be able to settle in the village she dreams of founding.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
		
		<subfeature>
			<name>Thom, Human Wizard</name>
			<benefit>Thom's one desire is for power. He adventures in search of arcane lore and ancient artifacts that will increase his mastery of magic.</benefit>
			<benefit>He prays to Ioun because he sees knowledge as the key to power, but he is also drawn to Vecna, wondering what power the god of secrets might offer him in exchange for his devotion.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>An eladrin can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>
		
		<power>
			<title>Sense Magic</title>
			<class>Eladrin</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>You attune your senses to the magical world, and in a flash, nearby magic becomes as obvious as birdsong on the wind</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You sense the presence of magic within 10 squares of you as if you succeeded on an Arcane check to do so.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>You can then make an Arcana check as a free reaction to identify any revealed magical phenomena, conjurations, or zones.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Eladrin Escape</title>
			<class>Eladrin</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>Your enemy has but one chance to corner you, for wasting the chance gives you the opportunity to flee</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An enemy misses you with a melee attack</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You teleport up to 5 squares.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Recursive Thought</title>
			<class>Eladrin</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>When you clear your mind, your affliction bounces back to your unsuspecting foe</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Special</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You succeed on a save against a dazing or stunning effect</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The source of the triggering effect</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The target is subjected to the effected you saved against. The effect lasts until the end of your next turn if you made a saving throw on your turn, or until the start of the acting creature's next turn if you made a save on another creature's turn.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
		
		<power>
			<title>Spiral Dance Assault</title>
			<class>Eladrin</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>You strike and dance away, only to reappear at your enemy's side</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>At-Will</frequency>
				<keyword>Arcane, Teleportation</keyword>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You hit an enemy with a melee attack on your turn</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You teleport up to 5 squares to a space adjacent to the triggering enemy.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You can use this power only once per turn.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
</race>
