<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../rule-card.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>2nd-rank Druid Spells</category>
      <title>Ash Cloud</title> <action>3</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>20-foot burst</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You summon a tumultuous cloud of ash and smoke. The cloud is difficult terrain for flying creatures, and creatures in the cloud can't detect anything using their sense of smell. Creatures that start their turn within the cloud take 2d4 fire damage as their lungs fill with the hot, acrid smoke, with a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess/>
         <success>The target takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The target takes full damage, and is dazzled for 1 round.</fail>
         <critfail>The target takes double damage and is blinded for 1 round.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Blazing Bolt</title> <action to="3">1</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 or more creatures</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You fire a ray of heat and flame. Make a ranged spell attack roll against a single creature. On a hit, the target takes 2d6 fire damage, and on a critical hit, the target takes double damage.</line>
      <line>For each additional action you use when Casting the Spell, you can fire an additional ray at a different targget, to a maximum of three rays targeting three different targets for 3 actions.</line>
      <line>These attacks each increase your multiple attack penalty, but you don't increase your multiple attack penalty until after you make all the attack rolls for <i>blazing bolt</i>. If you spend 2 or more actions Casting the Spell, the damage increases to 4d6 fire damage on a hit.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage to each target increases by 1d6 for the 1-action version, or by 2d6 for the 2- and 3-action versions.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Brine Dragon Bile</title> <action>R</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Acid</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <trigger>A creature within range takes damage from a slashing or piercing attack, or one that inflicts persistent bleed damage</trigger>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>the creature that took damage</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You spit a glob of caustic saltwater that stings the wounds of the creature. Make a ranged spell attack against the triggering creature's AC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>Salt scours the target's open wound, dealing 2d10 persistent acid damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>Salt stings the target's open wound, dealing 2d6 persistent acid damage.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The persistent damage increases by two dice.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Cleanse Affliction</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>

      <line>Gentle restorative magic pushes back against the effects of toxins and more complex maladies. Choose an affliction on the target, such as a <u>curse</u>, <u>disease</u>, or <u>poison</u>. If it has advanced past stage one, reduce the stage by one. This reduction can be applied only once to a given case of an affliction, with the case ending when it's completely cured.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">Attempt to counteract the affliction if it is a <u>disease</u> or <u>poison</u>. Even though the reduction can't occur again, you can keep attempting to counteract the affliction.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">Attempt to counteract the affliction if it is a <u>curse</u>, <u>disease</u>, or <u>poison</u>. Even though the reduction can't occur again, you can keep attemping to counteract the affliction.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Clear Mind</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Mental</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>

      <line>You drive mental contimaniation from the target's mind. Attempt to counteract an effect of your choice imposing one of these conditions on the target: fleeing, frightened, and stupefied.</line>
      <line>If you failed to counteract the effect but you would have if its counteract rank were 2 lower, instead suppress the effect until the beginning of your next turn. The effect's duration doesn't elapse while it is suppressed.</line>
      <line>This spell can't counteract or suppress conditions that are part of <u>curses</u>, <u>diseases</u>, or a natural state of the target.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">Add confused, controlled, and slowed to the list of conditions.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">Add doomed to the list of conditions.</heighten>
      <heighten value="8th">Add stunned to the list of conditions.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Create Food</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast>1 hour</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range>

      <line>You create enough food to feed six Medium creatures for a day. This food is bland and unappealing, but it is nourishing. After 1 day, if no one has eaten the food, it decays and becomes inedible.</line>
      <line>Most Small creatures eat one-quarter as much as a Medium creature (one-sixteenth as much for most Tiny creatures), and most Large creatures eat 10 times as much (100 times as much for Huge creatures, and so on).</line>

      <heighten value="4th">You can feed 12 Medium creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">You can feed 50 Medium creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="8th">You can feed 200 Medium creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Darkvision</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>

      <line>You grant yourself supernatural sight in areas of darkness. You gain darkvision.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The spell's range is touch and it targets 1 willing creature.</heighten>
      <heighten value="5th">The spell's range is touch and it targets 1 willing creature. The duration is until your next daily preparations.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dispel Magic</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 spell effect or unattended magic item</targets>

      <line>You unravel the magic behind a spell or effect. Attempt a counteract check against the target. If you successfully counteract a magic item, it becomes a mundane item of its type for 10 minutes. This doesn't change the item's non-magical properties.</line>
      <line>If the target is an artifact or similar item, you automatically fail.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Enlarge</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Polymorph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>
      <duration>5 minutes</duration>

      <line>Bolstered by magical power, the target grows to size Large. Its equipment grows with it but returns to natural size if removed. The creature is clumsy 1. Its reach increases by 5 feet (or by 10 feet if it started out Tiny), and it gains a +2 status bonus to melee damage. This spell has no effect on a Large or larger creature.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The creature instead grows to size Huge. The status bonus to melee damage is +4 and the creature's reach increases by 10 feet (or 15 feet if the creature started out Tiny). The spell has no effect on a Huge or larger creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">Choose either the 2nd-rank or 4th-rank version of this spell and apply its effects to up to 10 willing creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Entangling Flora</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Wood</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>All squares in a 20-foot burst</area>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>Plants and fungi burst out of quickly grow, entangling creatures. All surfaces in the area are difficult terrain. Each round that a creature starts its turn in the area, it must attempt a Reflex save. On a failure, it takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speed until it leaves the area, and on a critical failure, it's also immobilized for 1 round. Creatures can attempt to Escape to remove these effects.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Exploding Earth</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You throw a hard-packed ball of earth and stone at a creature, and the projectile explodes upon impact. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC. On a hit, the projectile deals 3d6 bludeoning damage. On a critical hit, the projectile deals double damage, and the target must succeed at a Fortitude saving throw or fall prone.</line>
      <line>On a miss, hit, or critical hit, the projectile deals 1d6 splash damage to all creatures within 5 feet of the target (including the target). Splash damage is not doupled on a critical hit, and you add it together with the initial damage against the target before applying the target's resistance or weakness.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">The initial damage increases by 3d6, and the splash damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Floating Flame</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>1 5-foot square</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>
      <duration>sustained up to 1 minute</duration>

      <line>You create a that burns without fuel and moves to your commands. The flame deals 3d6 fire damage to each creature in the square where it first appears, with a basic Reflex save.</line>
      <line>When you Sustain this spell, you can levitate the sphere up to 10 feet. It then deals damage to each creature whose space it shared at any point during the move. This uses the same damage and save, and you roll the damage once each time you Sustain.</line>
      <line>A given creature can take damage from the <i>floating flame</i> only once per round.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fungal Infestation</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Fungus</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>Toxic spores swarm over creatures in the area, causing them to erupt in grotesque fungal growths. These noxious growths deal 2d6 persistent poison damage, and each creature must attempt a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess/>
         <success>The target takes half the persistent damage.</success>
         <fail>The target takes the full persistent damage. While it is taking this persistent poison damage, it has weakness 1 to fire and weakness 1 to slashing.</fail>
         <critfail>The target takes double the persistent damage. While it is taking this persistent poison damage, it has weakness 2 to fire and weakness 2 to slashing.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The persistent damage increases by 2d6, and the weakness increases by 1, or by 2 on a critical failure.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gentle Breeze</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Vitality</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range> <area>40-foot burst</area>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>A light, soothing breeze flows through the area, making it easier to rest and recover. Medicine checks attempted to benefit living creatures in the area get a +2 status bonus. Any living creature in the area also gets a +2 status bonus to saving throws against afflictions and, if it remains within the area for the full duration, regains 10 Hit Points.</line>
      <line>In addition, the cool breeze reduces the temperature effects of heat by one step for any creature in the area.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">The healing increses by 10 Hit Points.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Mist</title> <action>3</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>20-foot burst</area>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You call forth a cloud of mist. All creatures within the mist become concealed (a creature must succeed a a flat DC 5 check to target the concealed creature with an attack, spell, or other effect), and all creatures outside the mist become concealed to creatures within it.</line>
      <line>You can Dismiss the cloud.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Oaken Skin</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Wood</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>The target's skin becomes tough, with a consistency like bark or wood. The target gains resistance 2 to bludgeoning and piercing damage, and weakness 3 to fire. After the target takes fire damage, it can Dismiss the spell as a free action triggered by taking the damage; doing so doesn't reduce the fire damage the target was dealt.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">The resistance increases by 2, and the weakness increases by 3.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Resist Energy</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>A shield of elemental energy protects a creature against one type of energy damage. Choose acid, cold, electricity, fire, or sonic damage. The target and its gear gain resistance 5 against the damage type you chose.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The resistance increases to 10, and you can target up to two creatures.</heighten>
      <heighten value="7th">The resistance increases to 15, and you can target up to five creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Revealing Light</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Light</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>10-foot burst</area>
      <save>Reflex</save> <duration>varies</duration>

      <line>A wave of magical light washes over the area. You choose the appearance of the light, such as colorful, heatless flames, or sparkling motes. A creature affected by <i>revealing light</i> is dazzled. If the creature was invisible, it becomes concealed instead. If the creature was already concealed for any reason, it is no longer concealed. Each creature must attempt a Reflex save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess/>
         <success>The light affects the creature for 2 rounds.</success>
         <fail>The light affects the creature for 1 minute.</fail>
         <critfail>The light affects the creature for 10 minutes.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sound Body</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Vitality</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>

      <line>You send a surge of healing energy to restore the targetss body. Attempt to counteract an effect of your choice imposing one of these conditions on the target: blinded, dazzled, deafened, enfeebled, or sickened.</line>
      <line>If you didn't counteract the effect, but you would have if its counteract rank were 2 lower, instead suppress the effect until the beginning of your next turn. The effect's duration doesn't elapse while it's suppressed.</line>
      <line>This spell can't counteract or suppress <u>curses</u>, <u>diseases</u>, or conditions that are part of the target's normal state.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">Add drained and slowed to the list of conditions.</heighten>
      <heighten value="8th">Add stunned to the list of conditions.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Splinter Volley</title> <action or="3">2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Wood</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 or 2 creatures</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You launch a volley of splinters at your foes. Make a ranged spell attack roll against a single creature's AC. On a hit, the splinters deal 4d6 piercing damage. On a critical hit, the splinters deal double damage and 1 persistent bleed damage.</line>
      <line>You can spend a third action while casting this spell to fire splinters at two different targets instead of one. These attacks each increase your multiple attack penalty, but you don't increase your multiple attack penalty until after you make both spell attack rolls for <i>splinter volley</i>.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">Increase the damage dealt to each target by 2d6. For every two ranks, also increase the persistent bleed damage on a critical hit by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sudden Blight</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Void</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <area>20-foot burst</area>
      <save>basic Fortitude</save>

      <line>You accelerate the processes of decay in an area. Each living creature in the area takes 2d10 void damage, with a basic Fortitude save. A creature affected by a disease takes a -2 circumstance penalty to this save.</line>
      <line>You can also direct the blight to rot Small and Tiny non-creature plants in the area, eliminating non-magical undergrowth and any resulting difficult terrain, cover, and concealment. <i>Sudden blight</i> attempts to counteract any magical effect on the plants before withering them.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d10.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sure Footing</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 willing creature</targets>

      <line>You free the target's limbs from ailments that impede mobility. Attempt to counteract an effect of your choice imposing one of these conditions on the target: clumsy, grabbed, or paralyzed.</line>
      <line>If you didn't counteract the effect, but you would have if its counteract rank were 2 lower, instead suppress the effect until the beginning of your next turn. The effect's duration doesn't elapse while it's suppressed.</line>
      <line>This spell can't counteract or suppress <u>curses</u>, <u>diseases</u>, or conditions that are part of the target's normal state.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">Add immobilized, slowed, and restrained to the list of conditions.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">Add petrified to the list of conditions.</heighten>
      <heighten value="8th">Add stunned to the list of conditions.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Water Walk</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>The target can walk on the surface of water and other liquids without falling through. It can go underwater if it wishes, but in that case it must Swim normally. This spell doesn't grant the ability to breathe underwater.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The spell's range increases to 30 feet, the duration increases to 1 hour, and you can target up to 10 creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <!-- <rule>
      <title>Web</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>2</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="3">material, somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>10-foot burst</area>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You create a sticky web in the area that impedes creatures' movement each time they try to move through it. Squares filled with the web are difficult terrain. Each square can be cleared of the web by a single attack or effect that deals at least 5 slashing damage or 1 fire damage. A square has AC 5, and it automatically fails its saving throws.</line>
      <line>Each time a creature in the web begins to use a move action or enters the web during a move action, it must attempt an Athletics check or Reflex save against your spell DC to avoid taking a circumstance penalty to its Speeds or becoming immobilized. A creature that gets out of the web ceases to take the circumstance penalty to its Speed from the web.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected, and it doesn't need to attempt further Athletics checks or saving throws against the web this turn. If it used an Athletics check, it clears the web from every square it leaves after leaving the square.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature is unaffected during its action. If it used an Athletics check, it clears the web from every square it leaves after leaving the square.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speeds until the start of its next turn.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is immobilized until the start of its next turn, after which it takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speeds for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape to remove its immobilized condition.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="4th">The spell's area increases to a 20-foot burst, and its range increases to 60 feet.</heighten>
   </rule> -->
</catalog>
