<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../rule-card.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>Druid Cantrips</category>
      <title>Acid Splash</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Acid</trait> <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>5-foot burst</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>You fling a glob of acid that immediately detonates, spraying nearby creatures. Creatures in the area take acid damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier with a basic Reflex save. On a critical failure, the creature also takes 1 persistent acid damage.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">The initial damage increases by 1d8, and the persistent damage on a critical failure increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Deep Breath</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1">somatic</cast>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>You take an incredibly deep breath and can hold it for the spell's duration. You don't lose breath when hit, but you do lose all the air you inhaled if you speak (including to Cast a Spell). This spell doesn't create air; if you don't have air to breathe when you cast it, you get no benefit.</line>

      <heighten value="2nd">The duration increases to 1 hour, and you lose only 10 minutes of breath if you speak.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">The duration increases to 8 hours, and you lose only 10 minutes of breath if you speak.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Detect Magic</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Detection</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>30-foot emanation</area>

      <line>You send out a pulse that registers the presence of magic. You receive no information beyond the rpesence or absence of magic. You can choose to ignore magic you're fully aware of, such as the magic items and ongoing spells of you and your allies.</line>
      <line>You detect illusion magic only if that magic's effect has a lower level than the level of your <![CDATA[<i>detect magic</i>]]> spell. However, items that have an illusion aura but aren't deceptive in appearance (such as an <![CDATA[<i>invisibility potion</i>]]>) typically are detected normally.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">You learn the school of magic for the highest-level effect within range that the spell detects. If multiple effects are equally strong, the GM determines which you learn.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">As 3rd level, but you also pinpoint the source of the highest-level magic. Like for an imprecise sense, you don't learn the exact location, but you can narrow down the source to within a 5-foot cube (or the nearest if larger than that).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Disrupt Undead</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 undead creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You lance the target with energy. The target takes positive damage equal to 1d6 plus your spellcasting ability modifier with a basic Fortitude save. On a critical failure, the target is also enfeebled 1 for 1 round.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Eat Fire</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="R">somatic</cast> <trigger>You would take fire damage.</trigger>
      <duration>until the end of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You consume and ingest fire, making it less harmful to you. You gain resistance 5 to fire damage until the end of the current turn.</line>
      <line>During the remaining duration of the spell, you can use the Belch Smoke action. The spell ends if you fall unconscious, inhale, or exhale (this includes speaking).</line>
      <block>
         <name>Belch Smoke</name> <action>1</action>
         <part>You exhale what remains of the smoke, ending the spell and creating a smoke cloud in a 5-foot burst within 20 feet. All creatures within the smoke cloud are concealed, and all other creatures are concealed to them. The smoke lasts for 1 minute or until dispersed by a strong wind.</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Electric Arc</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 or 2 creatures</targets>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>An arc of lightning leaps from one target to another. You deal electricity damage equal to 1d4 plus your spellcasting ability modifier.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Frostbite</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>basic Fortitude</save>

      <line>An orb of biting cold coalesces around your target, freezing its body. The target takes cold damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier with a basic fortitude save. On a critical failure, the target also gains weakness 1 to bludgeoning until the start of your next turn.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4 and the weakness on a critical failure increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gale Blast</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>5-foot emanation</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>Wind flows from your outstretched hands and whirls around you in a 5-foot emanation. Each creature in the area takes bludgeoning damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier, with a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage and is pushed 5 feet away from you.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Glass Shield</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1">verbal</cast>
      <save>basic Reflex</save> <duration>until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You summon a layer of glass to keep you from harm. This counts as using the Raise a Shield action, giving you a +1 circumstance bonus to AC until the start of your next turn, but it doesn't require a hand to use.</line>
      <line>While the spell is in effect, you can use the Shield Block reaction with your glass shield. The shield has Hardness 2 and 4 Hit Points. If this shield breaks, you can't cast this spell again for 10 minutes and, if the breaker is within 5 feet, they must succeed at a basic Reflex save or take 1d6 piercing damage from the glass shards.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The shield has a Hardness of 4 and 8 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 2d6.</heighten>
      <heighten value="5th">The shield has a Hardness of 7 and 16 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 3d6.</heighten>
      <heighten value="7th">The shield has a Hardness of 10 and 24 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 4d6.</heighten>
      <heighten value="9th">The shield has a Hardness of 14 and 32 Hit Points, and the damage increases to 5d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gouging Claw</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Morph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You temporarily morph your limb into a clawed appendage. Make a melee spell attack roll against your target's AC. On a hit, you deal your choice of slashing or piercing damage equal to 1d6 plus your spellcasting ability modifier, plus 2 persistent bleed damage. On a critical success, you deal double damage and double bleed damage.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6 and the persistent bleed damage increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Guidance</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1">verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>Until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You ask for divine guidance, granting the target a +1 status bonus to one attack roll, Perception check, saving throw, or skill check the target attempts before the duration ends. The target chooses which roll to use the bonus on before rolling. If the target uses the bonus, the spell ends. Either way, the target is then temporarily immune for 1 hour.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Plaster</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="1">somatic</cast>
      <range>5 feet</range> <targets>a handful of dirt or mud</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>You purify some dirt or mud into a pliable, claylike plaster that can aid in clotting and healing. This restorative substance can be used in lieu of healer's tools for Medicine checks to Administer First Aid or Treat Wounds. If you have the Battle Medicine feat, you can also use the plaster for that action. If the plaster isn't used within the spell's duration, or if you Cast the Spell again before using the plaster, it revers to being non-magical earth.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The plaster grants anyone using it a +1 item bonus to the Medicine check.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Light</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Light</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 object of 1 Bulk or less, either unattended or possessed by you or a willing ally</targets>
      <duration>until the net time you make your daily preparation</duration>

      <line>The object glows, casting bright light in a 20-foot radius (and dim light for the next 20 feet) like a torch. If you cast this spell again on a second object, the <![CDATA[<i>light</i>]]> spell on the first object ends.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The objects sheds bright light in a 60-foot radius (and dim light for the next 60 feet).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Needle Darts</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Metal</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You shape needles out of a piece of metal in your possession and sen them flying in a tight group toward one target. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC. The needles deal 3d4 piercing damage and might cause bleeding.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and 1 persistent bleed damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
      <line>The needles impart any special properties of the metal that forms them; for instance, cold iron needles deal additional damage to creatures with weakness to cold iron. All needles are made of the same metal, and the metal returns to you after the attack.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">You send additional needles, increasing the regular damage by 1d4 and increasing the persistent bleed damage on a critical hit by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Produce Flame</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A small ball of flame appears in the palm of your hand, and you lash out with it. Make a spell attack roll against your target's AC; on a hit, the flame deals fire damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcastint ability modifier. If the target is within your unarmed reach, you can choose to make a melee spell attack with the flame instead of a ranged spell attack, which increases all the spell's damage dice to d6.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage, and 1d4 persistent fire damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">Increase the damage by 1d4 and the persistent damage on a critical hit by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Puff of Poison</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Inhaled</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>5 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You exhale a shimmering cloud of toxic breath at an enemy's face. The target takes poison damage equal to your spellcasting modifier and 2 persistent poison damage, depending on its Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes half initial and persistent damage.</success>
         <fail>The target takes full initial and persistent damage.</fail>
         <critfail>The target takes double initial and persistent damage.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The initial poison damage increases by 1d8 and the persistent poison damage increases by 2.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ray of Frost</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You blast an icy ray. make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC. The ray deals cold damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and takes a -10-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes normal damage.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Rousing Splash</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You cause a splash of cold water to descend on an ally's head, granting some temporary vigor. The target gains 1d4 temporary Hit Points, which last for 1 minute. The target is then temporarily immune to the temporary Hit Points from <![CDATA[<i>rousing splash</i>]]> for 10 minutes.</line>
      <line>The target can also attempt an immediate flat check to recover from a single source of persistent acid or fire damage, with the DC reduction from appropriate assistance.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The amount of temporary Hit Points granted increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scatter Scree</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>two contiguous 5-foot cubes</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You evoke a jumble of rocks in the area. The scattering rocks deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier to creatures in the area, with a basic Reflex save. The ground in the area becomes difficult terrain for the duration. A creature can Interact to clear a square of this scree.</line>
      <line>If you cast this spell again, any previous scree you have scattered ends.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Stabilize</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 dying creature</targets>

      <line>Positive energy shuts death's door. The target loses the dying condition, though it remains unconscious at 0 Hit Points.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tanglefoot</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A vine covered in sticky sap appears from thin air, flicking from your hand and lashing itself to the target. Attempt a ranged spell attack against the taget.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target gains the immobilized condition and takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty and the immobilized condition.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty.</success>
         <fail>The target is unaffected.</fail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="2nd">The effects last for 2 rounds.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">The effects last for 1 minute.</heighten>
   </rule>
</catalog>
