<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../rule-card.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <category>1st-rank Druid Spells</category>
      <title>Briny Bolt</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Concentration</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You hurl a bolt of salt water from your extended hand. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC. The bolt deals 4d6 bludgeoning damage and blinds the target for 1 round as salt water sprays into its eyes. The target can use an Interact action to rub its eyes and end the blinded condition, but not the dazzled condition on a critical hit.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage, and it is dazzled for 1 minute after it is no longer blinded.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Breathe Fire</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>A gout of flame sprays from your mouth. You deal 2d6 fire damage to creatures in the area, with a basic Reflex save.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Buffeting Winds</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Nonlethal</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>You release a quick burst of wind that batters your living opponents without causing them lasting harm, while also blowing undead away. The wind deals 2d4 bludgeoning nonlethal damage, with a basic Reflex save.</line>
      <line>Against undead, the winds are more vicious, and the spell loses the nonlethal trait against such creatures. On a failed save, undead are knocked back 5 feet (or 10 feet on a critical failure).</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Chilling Spray</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>A cone of icy shards bursts from your spread hands and coats the targets in a layer of frost. Creatures in the area take 2d4 cold damage, and must make a Reflex save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess/>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage, and takes a -5-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 2 rounds.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage, and takes a -10-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 2 rounds.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Conductive Weapon</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Metal</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 metal weapon that is unattended or attended by a willing creature</targets>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You channel powerful electric current through a metal weapon, zapping anyone the item hits. The target becomes a <i>+1 shocking</i> weapon. If any target of an attack with the weapon is wearing metal armor is is primarily made of metal, the electricity die from the <i>shock</i> rune is 1d12.</line>
      <line>A weapon with a <i>shock</i> rune deals an extra 1d6 electricity damage on a hit. On a critical hit, electricity arcs out to deal an equal amount of damage to up to two creatures of the attacker's choice within 10 feet of the target.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dehydrate</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>5-foot burst</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You stir the inner fire of all things within the area, driving out moisture. All creatures in the area take 2d4 persistent fire damage with a basic Fortitude save; creatures with the <u>water</u> or <u>plant</u> traits get a result one degree of success worse than they rolled. The spell ends for a creature when its persistent damage ends.</line>
      <line>A creature affected by <i>dehydrate</i> attempts an additional Fortitude save at the end of each of its turns, before rolling to recover from the persistent damage. It can forgo this additional save if it consumed water or similar hydrating liquid within the last round (typically, drinking requires a single action).</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>The creature takes no additional effect.</success>
         <fail>The creature is enfeebled 1 until the end of its next turn.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is enfeebled 2 until the end of its next turn.</critfail>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+2">The range increases by 10 feet, the burst increases by 5 feet, and the persistent fire damage increases by 3d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Fear</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Emotion</trait> <trait>Fear</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Mental</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Will</save> <duration>varies</duration>

      <line>You plant fear in the target; it must attempt a Will save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess/>
         <success>The target is frightened 1.</success>
         <fail>The target is frightened 2.</fail>
         <critfail>The target is frightened 3, and fleeing for 1 round.</critfail>
      </line>
      <heighten value="3rd">You can target up to 5 creatures.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Flourishing Flora</title>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Wood</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>5-foot burst</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>Plants rapidly grow up from the ground. All creatures in the target area take 2d4 damage, with a basic Reflex save. The type of damage depends on the type of plant you choose to grow. On a critical failure, targets experience additional effects, also depending on what you choose to grow. The type of plant and its effects are chosen when you Cast the Spell.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry name="Cacti">Piercing damage, and 1 persistent bleed damage on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Flowers">Poison damage, and dazzled for 2 rounds on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Fruits">Bludgeoning damage, and clumsy 1 for 2 rounds on a critical failure.</entry>
         <entry name="Roots">Bludgeoning damage, and the affected creatures fall prone on a critical failure.</entry>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4, and the persistent bleed damage from cacti increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gentle Landing</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Concentration</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <trigger>A creature within range is falling</trigger>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 falling creature</targets>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You raise a magical updraft to arrest a fall. The target's fall slows to 60 feet per round, and the portion of the fall during the spell's duration doesn't count when calculating falling damage. If the target reaches the ground while the spell is in effect, it takes no damage from the fall. The spell ends as soon as the target lands.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gust of Wind</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <area>60-foot line</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save> <duration>until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>A violent wind issues forth from your palm, blowing from the point where you are when you cast the spell to the line's opposite end. The wind extinguishes small non-magical fires, disperses fog and mist, blows objects of light Bulk or less around, and pushes larger objects. Large or smaller creatures in the area must attempt a Fortitude save. Large or smaller creatures that later move into the gust must attempt the save when entering.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess/>
         <success>The creature can't move against the wind.</success>
         <fail>The creature is knocked prone. If it was flying, it suffers the effects of critical failure instead.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature is pushed 30 feet in the wind's direction, knocked prone, and takes 2d6 bludgeoning damage.</critfail>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Heal</title> <action to="3">1</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Vitality</trait>
      <range>varies</range> <targets>1 willing living creature or 1 undead</targets>

      <line>You channel vital energy to heal the living or damage the undead. If the target is a willing living creature, you restore 1d8 Hit Points. If the target is undead, you deal that amount of vitality damage to it, with a basic Fortitude save.</line>
      <line>The number of actions you spend when Casting this Spell determines its targets, range, area, and other parameters.</line>
      <line action="1">The spell has a range of touch.</line>
      <line action="2" traits="concentrate">The spell has a range of 30 feet. If you're healing a living creature, increase the Hit Points restored by 8.</line>
      <line action="3" traits="concentrate">You disperse vital energy in a 30-foot emanation. This targets all living and undead creatures in the emanation.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The amount of damage or healing increases by 1d8, and the extra healing for the 2-action version increases by 8.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hydraulic Push</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range> <targets>1 creature or unattended object</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You call forth a powerful blat of pressurized water that bludgeons the target and knocks it back, dealing 3d6 bludgeoning damage. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's AC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and is knocked back 10 feet.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage and is knocked back 5 feet.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Jump</title> <action>1</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Move</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <targets>self</targets>

      <line>Your legs surge with strength, ready to leap high or far. You jump 30 feet in any direction without touching the ground. You must land on a space of solid ground, or else you fall after using your next action.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The range becomes touch, the target changes to one touched creature, and the duration becomes 1 minute, allowing the target to jump as described whenever it takes the Leap action.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Leaden Steps</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Metal</trait> <trait>Morph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>Fortitude</defense> <duration>sustained up to 1 minute</duration>

      <line>You partially transform a foe's feet into unwieldy slabs of metal, slowing their steps. The target must attempt a Fortitude saving throw.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess/>
         <success>The target is encumbered and has weakness 2 to electricity until the end of your next turn. The spell can't be sustained.</success>
         <fail>The target is encumbered and has weakness 2 to electricity.</fail>
         <critfail>The target is encumbered and has weakness 4 to electricity.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>An encumbered creature is clumsy 1 and takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to all its Speeds.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Mud Pit</title> <action>3</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range> <area>squares on the ground in a 15-foot burst</area>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>Thick, clinging mud covers the ground, 1 foot deep. The mud is difficult terrain.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Pummeling Rubble</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>A spray of heavy rocks flies through the air in front of you. The rubble deals 2d4 bludgeoning damage to each creature in the area. Each creature must attempt a Reflex save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage and is pushed 5 feet away from you.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you.</critfail>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shocking Grasp</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You shroud your hands in a crackling field of lightning. Make a melee spell attack roll against the target's AC. On a hit, the target takes 2d12 electricity damage.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
      <line>If the target is wearing metal armor or is made of metal, you gain a +1 circumstance bonus to your attack roll with <i>shocking grasp</i>, and the target also takes 1d4 persistent electricity damage on a hit. This persistent damage is not doubled on a critical hit.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d12, and the persistent electricity damage increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Shockwave</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <save>Reflex</save>

      <line>You create a wave of energy that ripples through the earth. Terrestrial creatures in the affected area must attempt a Reflex save to avoid stumbling as the shockwave shakes the ground.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature is flat-footed until the start of its next turn.</success>
         <fail>The creature falls prone.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature falls prone, and takes 1d6 damage.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The area increases by 5 feet (to a 20-foot cone at 2nd spell rank, and so on).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Snowball</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You throw a magically propelled and chilled ball of dense snow. The target takes 2d4 cold damage and potentially other effects, depending on the result of your ranged spell attack roll.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and a -10-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage and a -5-foot status penalty to its Speeds for 1 round.</success>
         <fail>No effect.</fail>
      </line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 2d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spider Sting</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You magically duplicate a spider's venomous sting. You deal 1d4 piercing damage to the touched creature and afflict it with spider venom. The target must attempt a Fortitude save against your spell DC.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes 1d4 poison damage.</success>
         <fail>The target is afflicted with spider venom at stage 1.</fail>
         <critfail>The target is afflicted with spider venom at stage 2.</critfail>
      </line>
      <block>
         <name>Spider Venom</name>
         <part>(poison)</part>
         <part><name>Level</name>1</part>
         <part><name>Maximum Duration</name>4 rounds</part>
         <part linebreak=""><name>Stage 1</name>1d4 poison damage and enfeebled 1 (1 round)</part>
         <part><name>Stage 2</name>1d4 poison damage and enfeebled 2 (1 round)</part>
      </block>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tailwind</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <duration>1 hour</duration>

      <line>The wind at your back pushes you to find new horizons. You gain a +10-foot status bonus to your Speed.</line>

      <heighten value="2nd">The duration increases to 8 hours.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Thunderstrike</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Sonic</trait>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>You call down a tendril of lightning that cracks with thunder, dealing 1d12 electricity damage and 1d4 sonic damage to the target with a basic Reflex save. A target wearing metal armor or made of metal takes a -1 circumstance penalty to its save and, if damaged by the spell, is clumsy 1 for 1 round.</line>
      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d12 electricity and 1d4 sonic.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Weaken Earth</title> <action>2</action>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature, unattended object, or hazard or structure made of stone or earth</targets>
      <defense>Fortitude</defense>
      <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You weaken the bonds that hold earth and stone together. If your target has Hardness, you can affect one contiguous object, up to 5 5-foot cubes, or one creature, decreasing the Hardness by 5 to a minimum of 5. If the target lacks Hardness, it gains weakness 3 to physical. A target with a Fortitude modifier can attempt a Fortitude saving throw, negating the effect on a success.</line>

      <heighten value="+2">Hardness decreases by 5, the size of a contiguous object increases by one 5-foot cube, and the weakness increases by 3.</heighten>
   </rule>
</catalog>
