<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Warforged</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Built for a war that has ended, searching for purpose</shortfluff>

	<height>6'0" - 6'6"</height>
	<weight>270 - 300</weight>

	<ability>Strength</ability> <ability>Constitution</ability> <ability>Intelligence</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Normal</vision>

	<language>Common</language>

	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
		<description>+2 Endurance, +2 Intimidate</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Living Construct</name>
		<description>You are a living construct. You do not need to eat, drink, breath, or sleep.</description>
		<description>You never make Endurance checks to resist the effect of starvation, thirst, or suffocation. All other conditions and effects affect you normally.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Unsleeping Watcher</name>
		<description>You do not sleep and instead enter a state of inactivity for 4 hours to gain the benefits of an extended rest.</description>
      <description>While in this state, you are fully aware of your surroundings and notice approaching enemies and other events as normal.</description>
	</trait>
   <trait>
      <name>Warforged Mind</name>
      <description>You have a +1 racial bonus to your Will.</description>
   </trait>
   <trait>
      <name>Warforged Resilience</name>
      <description>You have a +2 racial bonus to saving throws against ongoing damage.</description>
      <description>Also, when you make a death saving throw, you can take the better result of your die roll or 10.</description>
   </trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Warforged Racial Power</name>
		<description>You have the <![CDATA[<i>warforged resolve</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>

	<fluff>Created as soldiers for the Last War, warforged are artificial humanoids who are intelligent and selfaware. Without a war to fight, freed of their creators, and with no heritage or culture of their own, warforged are searching for a place in the world.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a warforged if you want: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be strong, tough, and built for battle.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be a creature searching for the meaning of your existence.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be a member of a race that can add modifications to your body.</fluff>

	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Warforged Resolve</title>
			<class>Warforged</class> <category>Utility</category>
			<fluff>It's difficult to take you down, even when you're faltering</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You gain a number of temporary hit points equal to 3 + one-half your level, and can make a saving throw against one effect on you that deals ongoing damage.</text>
				</section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <text>If you are bloodied, this power gains the Healing keyword and you also regain a number of hit points equal to 3 + one-half your level.</text>
            </section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Warforged are bulky humanoids covered in plates of metal and stone. A skeleton of these materials supports woody fiber bundles that comprise a warforged's muscular system. Warforged bodies have an internal network of tubes filled with bloodlike fluid that nourishes and lubricates their systems. Their powerful arms end in hands that each have two fingers and one thumb, and each of their feet has two broad toes.</benefit>
		<benefit>Warforged heads have simple humanlike features. They have heavy brows, hinged toothless jaws, and no noses. A warforged's eyes sometimes glow when he or she experiences certain emotions. The forehead of each warforged bears a unique rune called a ghulra. The ghulra help give a warforged a sense of individuality.</benefit>
		<benefit>Warforged possess and artificial and relatively sexless shape. They don't reproduce like other humanoids. A warforged can modify its body, adding and removing limbs as necessary. A warforged feels pain only from real injury. These physical modifications allow warforged to vary in appearance as much as any other humanoids.</benefit>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Warforged</name>
		<benefit>Warforged have a straightforward emotional range. Although they experience pain, fear, hatred, and anger like other aces, they are reserved and pensive, hiding emotions behind expressionless metal faces. Some warforged lack introspection and are dangerously naïve or emotionally stunted. Many warforged are the opposite, though. They question the purpose of their existence and consider whether or not they have souls.</benefit>
		<benefit>A few warforged develop sophisticated philosophies about what they perceive and learn. Many warforged fall in with humanoids of similar mindsets, working passionately for an organization or a religion. A warforged typically forms a strong emotional attachment to a small group of comrades.</benefit>
		<benefit>A warforged often has limited experiences in the world, having spent its existence assigned to one specific duty. Warforged enjoy working, and many create endless lists of goals and chores. They take pride in their jobs, and they dislike idleness and failure more than most races do. A warforged's sensibilities give it a single-minded efficiency with any task, particularly in combat. War and military conditioning color warforged behavior. Warforged intuitively understand duty, conflict, the chain of command, and other elements of war and soldierly life.</benefit>
		<benefit>Because most warforged have bodies that resemble males, they identify themselves as males and prefer to be called “he” rather than “it.” Some warforged adopt female names, though. Most warforged have simple names related to their jobs, abilities, or military positions. Warforged often accept the names or the nicknames that their comrades give them, although some search long for particular names that define them. Many simply take names common within another race, especially those of humans.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Warforged Charasteristics:</b>]]> Aggressive, alert, brave, curious, fortright, industrious, loyal, methodical, naïve, practical, reserved, simple</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Warforged Names:</b>]]> Azm, Book, Bulwark, Cart, Cutter, Falchion, Graven, Hammer, Mark, Morg, Nameless, Pierce, Pious, Relic, Rune, Steeple, Three, Titan, Unsung, Victor, Watcher, Zealot</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Sample Warforged Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Null, Warforged Warlock</name>
			<benefit>In her hunger for individuality, Null rejected warforged and human norms and communed with unfathomable entities beyond the world. She has engraved her body and belongings with mystical and maddening sigils, and she savors the fear her appearance evokes in her enemies.</benefit>
			<benefit>Although gloomy, taciturn, and darkly canded, Null enjoys the grudging admiration that heroics garner. Thus, she prefers to use her power to punish those whom she believes are evil.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Rune, Warforged Artificer</name>
			<benefit>Created in the final days of the Last War, Rune never reached the frontlines, which caused him to question his purpose. As he helped collect the dead husks of fallen warforged, he swore to dedicate his existence to making sure no more of their kind would suffer the fate.</benefit>
			<benefit>Rune now travels the lands, helping damaged warforged mend their bodies and communities strengthen their defenses. When he comes across battlefields from days past, he always takes his time to go over them in search of lost warforged parts he can use to help those still living.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Thunderstruct, Warforged Cleric</name>
			<benefit>Thunderstruck sees warforged as Dol Dorn's (the god of war in Eberron) chosen people, and he believes that his race exists to bring glory to themselves and to the god of battle. With this philosophy, he willingly takes up any just cause that requires his trength and skill.</benefit>
			<benefit>Thunderstruck also openly seeks personal renown, which he believes also honors Dol Dorn. Against his enemies, he is a fearless storm of steel, an expression of what he believes is the warforged ideal.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A warforged can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>

		<power>
			<title>Inexorable Movement</title>
			<class>Warforged</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>You push forward despite adversity</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section shade="true">
					<name style="bold">Effect:</name>
					<text>You move up to your speed + 2. For this movement, you ignore the immobilized and slowed conditions, and difficult terrain.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Invigorating Resolve</title>
			<class>Warforged</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>Your steel mind allows your body to keep going</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Healing</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name style="bold">Requirement:</name>
					<text>You must have temporary hit points.</text>
				</section>
				<section shade="true">
					<name style="bold">Effect:</name>
					<text>You regain a number of hit points equal to the temporary hit points you have, and then lose those temporary hit points.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Immutable Body</title>
			<class>Warforged</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>Seemingly through your determination alone, your artificial body proves inviolate</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
					<text>You are subject to an effect that a save can end</text>
				</section>
				<section shade="true">
					<name style="bold">Effect:</name>
					<text>You are not affected by the triggering effect.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Warforged Fortification</title>
			<class>Warforged</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>You're so tough, sometimes even the worst hits don't daunt you</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name style="bold">Trigger:</name>
					<text>A creature scores a critical hit against you</text>
				</section>
				<section shade="true">
					<name style="bold">Effect:</name>
					<text>The triggering attack is a normal hit instead of a critical hit.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

   </feature>
</race>
