<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Dwarf</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Stout warriors, dauntless and unyielding lords of the mountain peaks</shortfluff>

	<height>4'3" - 4'9"</height>
	<weight>160 - 220</weight>

	<ability>Wisdom</ability>
    <ability>Strength</ability>
    <ability>Constitution</ability>
	<speed>5</speed>
	<vision>Low-light Vision</vision>

	<language>Common</language> <language>Dwarven</language>

	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
        <description>+2 Dungeoneering, +2 Endurance</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Cast-Iron Stomach</name>
		<description>You gain a +5 racial bonus to saving throws against Poison effects.</description>
	</trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
        <description>You can use your <![CDATA[<i>second wind</i>]]> as a minor action.</description>
    </trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Dwarven Weapon Proficiency</name>
		<description>You gain proficiency with the throwing hammer and the warhammer.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Encumbered Speed</name>
		<description>You move at your normal speed even when it would be reduced by armor or a heavy load.</description>
		<description>Other effects that limit speed, such as difficult terrain or magic, affect you normally.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Stand Your Ground</name>
		<description>When an effect pushes, pulls, or slides you, you can reduce the maximum distance by 1 square. This means that an effect that normally pushes, pulls, or slides a target 1 square does not force you to move unless you want to.</description>
		<description>In addition, when an attack would knock you prone, you can make a saving throw to avoid falling prone.</description>
	</trait>

	<fluff>Carved from the bedrock of the universe, dwarves endured an age of serviture to giants before winning their freedom. Their mighty mountain fortress-cities testify to the power of their ancient empires. Even those who live in human cities are counted among the staunchest defenders against the darkness that threatens to engulf the world.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a dwarf if you want to: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be tough, gruff, and strong as bedrock.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to bring glory to your ancestors or serve as your god's right hand.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be able to take as much punishment as you dish out.</fluff>

	<feature>

	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Dwarves average about 4½ feet in height and are very broad, weighing as much as an adult human. Dwarves have the same variety of skin, eye, and hair colors as humans, although dwarf skin is sometimes gray or sandstone red and red hair is more common among them. Male dwarves are often bald and braid their beards into elaborate patterns. Female dwarves braid their hair to show clan and ancestry. Dwarven attire and equipment, including weapons and shields, are decorated with bold geometric shapes, natural gems, and ancestral faces.</benefit>
		<benefit>Although they reach physical maturity at roughly the same age as humans, dwarves age more slowly and remain vigorous well past 150 years of age, often living to see 200.</benefit>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Dwarf</name>
		<benefit>Proudly proclaiming they were made from the earth itself, dwarves share many qualities with the rock they love. They are strong, hardy, and dependable. They value their ancestral traditions, which they preserve through the ages as fiercely as they defend the carved structures of their mountain homes.</benefit>
		<benefit>Dwarves believe in the importance of clan ties and ancestry. They deeply respect their elders, and they honor long-dead clan founders and ancestral heroes. They place great value on wisdom and the experience of years, and most are polite to elders of any race.</benefit>
		<benefit>More so than most other races, dwarves seek guidance and protection from the gods. They look to the divine for strength, hope, and inspiration, or they seek to propitiate cruel or destructive gods. Individual dwarves might be impious or openly heretical, but temples and shrines of some sort are found in almost every dwarven community. Dwarves revere Moradin as their creator, but individual dwarves honor those deities who hold sway over their vocations; warriors pray to Bahamut or Kord, architects to Erathis, and merchants to Avandra -or even Tiamat, if a dwarf is consumed by the dwarven taste for wealth.</benefit>
		<benefit>Dwarves never forget their enemies, either individuals who have wronged them or entire races of monsters who have done ill to their kind. Dwarves harbor a fierce hatred for orcs, which often inhabit the same mountainous areas that dwarves favor and which wreak periodic devastation on dwarf communities. Dwarves also despise giants and titans, because the dwarf race once labored as the giants' slaves. They feel a mixture of pity and disgust towards those corrupted dwarfkin who still have not freed themselves from the giants' yoke -azers and galeb duhrs among them.</benefit>
		<benefit>To a dwarf, it is a gift and a mark of deep respect to stand beside an ally in battle, and a sign of deepest loyalty to shield an ally from enemy attack. Dwarven legends honor many heroes who gave their lives to save their clans or their friends.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Dwarf Charasteristics:</b>]]> Acquisitive, brave, hard-working, loyal, organized, stern, stubborn, tenacious, vengeful</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Adrik, Baern, Berend, Darrak, Eberk, Fargrim, Gardain, Harbek, Kildrak, Morgran, Orsik, Rangrim, Thoradin, Thorfin, Tordek, Travok, Vondal</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Artin, Bardryn, Diesa, Eldeth, Falkrunn, Gurdis, Helja, Kathra, Kristryd, Mardred, Riswynn, Torbera, Vistra</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Sample Dwarf Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Travok, Dwarf Paladin</name>
			<benefit>Travok is committed to the service of Kord. Wearing shining plate armor crafted and proudly worn by his great-grandfather, Travok presents an impenetrable line of defense, defying his enemies to get past him to reach his allies.</benefit>
			<benefit>True to god and the honor of his ancestors, Travok relishes his physical strength and endurance, vowing that nothing will mave him from his place. He is fiercely loyal to his friends, and if the need arises, he will lay down his life to ensure that they live.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Kathra, Dwarf Cleric</name>
			<benefit>Kathra is devoted to Moradin, the Great Carver who formed the dwarves out of stone and liberated them from their servitude to the giants. Swinging a warhammer engraved with the hammer-and-anvil symbol of her god, Kathra stands next to her fighter companion, trusting in divine power, the chainmail she made herself, and her own natural resilience to protect her from her enemies.</benefit>
			<benefit>Her dearest hope is to craft a legacy that will last through the ages, as beautiful and enduring as the finest dwarven jewelry -a legacy of peace and justice in this troubled world.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Tordek, Dwarf Fighter</name>
			<benefit>Tordek is the last in a line of noble warriors. Three generations ago, his family's ancestral fortress was overrun by orcs and laid to waste, leaving Tordek with nothing but a signet ring and tales of ancient glory as his birthright.</benefit>
			<benefit>He has sworn that he will rebuild the fortress one day, and that oath drives his every action. In the meantime, his adventuring companions know they can rely on him completely, and someday he will rely on them to help him reclaim his kingdom.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A dwarf can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>

		<power>
			<title>Avalanche Rush</title>
			<class>Dwarf</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>The mountain's strength helps you shove an enemy from your path</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You either successfully <![CDATA[<i>bull rush</i>]]> a target or use a melee attack to push a target</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>If you used <![CDATA[<i>bull rush</i>]]>, you increase the push by a number of squares up to your Strength modifier or your Constitution modifier, shifting into each square your target leaves.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>If you used a melee attack to push a target, you increase the push by a number of squares up to one-half your Strength modifier or your Constitution modifier and can shift into each square your target leaves for these additional squares.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Dwarven Pride</title>
			<class>Dwarf</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>Nobody tosses a dwarf and gets away with it</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You are pulled, pushed, or slid</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Until the end of your next turn, you gain a +1 cumulative power bonus to damage rolls for each square of the triggering forced movement.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>You also gain a +1 power bonus to the first attack roll you make against the triggering creature before the end of your next turn.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Stone Stubborn</title>
			<class>Dwarf</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>You steel your mind to the onslaught, determined to go about your business</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An effect would dominate or stun you</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>The triggering effect makes you dazed instead of dominated or stunned.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Mountainborn Tenacity</title>
			<class>Dwarf</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>Just as no mountain fell from a single strike, no dwarf has fallen from a single blow</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Healing</keyword>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You drop to 0 hit points or fewer</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your healing surge value.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Until the start of the acting creature's next turn, you gain resist all equal to twice your Constitution modifier.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>

</race>
