<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
	<name>Vampire</name>
	<subname>Bloodhaunt</subname>
	<role>Striker</role>
	<source>Shadow</source>
	<shortfluff>Infused with the power of darkness and having already experienced death, you are a lethal creature of the night. As your power rises, your supernatural nature comes to the fore - but will your humanity pay the price?</shortfluff>
	<keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
	<keyability>Strength</keyability>
	<keyability>Charisma</keyability>

	<proficiency>
		<type>Armor</type>
		<name>Cloth</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Weapon</type>
		<name>Simple melee</name>
		<name>Simple ranged</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Implement</type>
		<name>Holy symbol</name>
		<name>Ki focus</name>
	</proficiency>

   <defense>
      <name>Fort</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
	<defense>
		<name>Will</name>
		<value>+1</value>
	</defense>

	<hpbase>12</hpbase>
	<hpgain>5</hpgain>
	<surges>2</surges>

	<skills>
		<trained>Athletics, Diplomacy, or Stealth</trained>
		<number>3</number>
	</skills>

	<fluff>A Vampire is a monster, fated and infected by a vile curse that transformed him or her into a creature of nightmare. Normal emotions have become alien, and only a cold, gnawing hunger remains.</fluff>
	<fluff>Most of those who become Vampires are victims of monstrous attacks, created by a callous hunter who drained them dry of blood and life force, then cast them aside. Others seek out this path from their own fear of infirmity and death, discovering the forbidden rites and alchemical formulas that promise dark power. In some cases, a character finds his or her vampirism invoked by an ancient family curse, or that he or she is a member of an extended clan of vampires who pass their blood down to those they deem worthy - whether by choice or not.</fluff>
	<fluff>Whatever their origins, Vampire characters are not slaves to their creaters. Even those beholden to an older vampire retain free will, and have a chance to avoid sinking into the bestial depravity so common among their kind. Bloodhaunt characters are the most exceptional examples of those who carry this dark curse, using their powers not solely to murder and for personal gain. Some become the greatest of heroes, but even those Vampires are aware that few among the common folk have the ability to see part the frightening reality of their dark nature.</fluff>
	<fluff>Avoiding scrutiny of superstitious folk and disguising his or her needs and abilities serves a Vampire best. Trusted companions, enemies to slay and feast upon, and reasons to avoid civilized areas for extended times make an adventuring life the perfect choice for such characters.</fluff>

	<feature>
		<name>Level 1: Child of the Night</name>
		<benefit>You have been reborn into darkness, claiming the ancient power that will mark you for all time. You gain strength in the night even as you curse the sun, for its unwavering radiance is a bitter fire that drains your strength and power.</benefit>
		<benefit>You gain the following benefits and weaknesses:</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; You are an Undead creature. You are unaffected by anything that only affects living creatures. You don't need to breathe, which means you are immune to suffocation. You also don't age. Unlike more undead, you do need to sleep.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; You have darkvision.</benefit>
      <benefit>You have resist 5 necrotic. This increases to resist 10 necrotic at 11th level, and to resist 15 necrotic at 21st level.</benefit>
      <benefit>You have vulnerable 5 radiant. This increases to resist 10 radiant at 11th level, and to resist 15 radiant at 21st level.</benefit>
      <benefit>If you end you your turn in direct sunlight and lack a protective covering such as a cloak or other heavy clothing, you take 5 radiant damage (plus additional damage from your vulnerable radiant) from the sunlight, and you are weakened (save ends). If you drop to 0 hit points or fewer from this damage, you are instantly destroyed instead of becoming dying.</benefit>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 1: Blood is Life</name>
      <benefit>As an undead creature, you gain power and strength when you drain the life essence of other creatures. A gnawing hunger thus burns within your body and spirit, tempting you to descend into feral madness. Some Vampires embrace this impulse, becoming savage beasts with a thirst for blood. Others strive to control it, turning their hunger into a weapon they can unleash against their enemies.</benefit>
   </feature>
</class>
