<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
	<name>Vampire</name>
	<subname>Bloodhaunt</subname>
	<role>Striker</role>
	<source>Shadow</source>
	<shortfluff>Infused with the power of darkness and having already experienced death, you are a lethal creature of the night. As your power rises, your supernatural nature comes to the fore - but will your humanity pay the price?</shortfluff>
	<keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
	<keyability>Strength</keyability>
	<keyability>Charisma</keyability>

	<proficiency>
		<type>Armor</type>
		<name>Cloth</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Weapon</type>
		<name>Simple melee</name>
		<name>Simple ranged</name>
	</proficiency>
	<proficiency>
		<type>Implement</type>
		<name>Holy symbol</name>
		<name>Ki focus</name>
	</proficiency>

   <defense>
      <name>Fort</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
	<defense>
		<name>Will</name>
		<value>+1</value>
	</defense>

	<hpbase>12</hpbase>
	<hpgain>5</hpgain>
	<surges>2</surges>

	<skills>
		<trained>Athletics, Diplomacy, or Stealth</trained>
		<number>3</number>
	</skills>

	<fluff>A Vampire is a monster, fated and infected by a vile curse that transformed him or her into a creature of nightmare. Normal emotions have become alien, and only a cold, gnawing hunger remains.</fluff>
	<fluff>Most of those who become Vampires are victims of monstrous attacks, created by a callous hunter who drained them dry of blood and life force, then cast them aside. Others seek out this path from their own fear of infirmity and death, discovering the forbidden rites and alchemical formulas that promise dark power. In some cases, a character finds his or her vampirism invoked by an ancient family curse, or that he or she is a member of an extended clan of vampires who pass their blood down to those they deem worthy - whether by choice or not.</fluff>
	<fluff>Whatever their origins, Vampire characters are not slaves to their creaters. Even those beholden to an older vampire retain free will, and have a chance to avoid sinking into the bestial depravity so common among their kind. Bloodhaunt characters are the most exceptional examples of those who carry this dark curse, using their powers not solely to murder and for personal gain. Some become the greatest of heroes, but even those Vampires are aware that few among the common folk have the ability to see part the frightening reality of their dark nature.</fluff>
	<fluff>Avoiding scrutiny of superstitious folk and disguising his or her needs and abilities serves a Vampire best. Trusted companions, enemies to slay and feast upon, and reasons to avoid civilized areas for extended times make an adventuring life the perfect choice for such characters.</fluff>

	<feature>
		<name>Level 1: Child of the Night</name>
		<benefit>You have been reborn into darkness, claiming the ancient power that will mark you for all time. You gain strength in the night even as you curse the sun, for its unwavering radiance is a bitter fire that drains your strength and power.</benefit>
		<benefit>You gain the following benefits and weaknesses:</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; You are an Undead creature. You are unaffected by anything that only affects living creatures. You don't need to breathe, which means you are immune to suffocation. You also don't age. Unlike most undead, you do need to sleep.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658; You have darkvision.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658;You have resist 5 necrotic. This increases to resist 10 necrotic at 11th level, and to resist 15 necrotic at 21st level.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658;You have vulnerable 5 radiant. This increases to vulnerable 10 radiant at 11th level, and to vulnerable 15 radiant at 21st level.</benefit>
      <benefit>&#9658;If you end you your turn in direct sunlight and lack a protective covering such as a cloak or other heavy clothing, you take 5 radiant damage (plus additional damage from your vulnerable radiant) from the sunlight, and you are weakened (save ends). If you drop to 0 hit points or fewer from this damage, you are instantly destroyed instead of becoming dying.</benefit>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 1: Blood is Life</name>
      <benefit>As an undead creature, you gain power and strength when you drain the life essence of other creatures. A gnawing hunger thus burns within your body and spirit, tempting you to descend into feral madness. Some Vampires embrace this impulse, becoming savage beasts with a thirst for blood. Others strive to control it, turning their hunger into a weapon they can unleash against their enemies.</benefit>
      <benefit>You have a limited number of healing surges, and unlike most classes, you do not add your Constitution modifier to your number of healing surges. You start play with two healing surges, and gain the Durable feat as a bonus feat, for a total of four healing surges.</benefit>
      <benefit>Many of your Vampire class powers allow you to either gain healing surges, or to expend them to enhance those powers. You gain the <![CDATA[<i>blood drinker</i>]]> attack power as your 1st-level encounter attack. This power allows you to draw on the life force of other creatures, whether is consists of blood, ichor, or the unseen energy of life itself.</benefit>
      <benefit>Once during a short rest, an ally adjacent to you can willingly lose one healing surge to allow you to regain hit points equal to your bloodied value.</benefit>
      <benefit>If you end a short rest with more healing surges than your usual number of healing surges for the day, you lose any healing surges beyond that number but regain all your hit points. If you were already at full hit points, you gain a +5 power bonus to Endurance checks until the end of your next extended rest.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Blood Drinker</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
         <fluff>When your attack strikes true, you sweep past your foe's defenses to consume the essence of its life</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
            <keyword>Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
            <type>Special</type>
            <section>
               <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You hit an enemy with a Vampire melee at-will attack power</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>The triggering enemy</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>The target takes +1d8 extra damage from the triggering attack, and you gain a healing surge.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 13:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>When you reach 13th level, this power becomes your level 13 encounter attack power, and the extra damage increases to +2d10.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 27:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>When you reach 27th level, this power becomes your level 27 encounter attack, and the extra damage increases to +3d12.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 1: Enduring Soul</name>
      <benefit>Your body is undead, but the lingering presence of your soul is infused into the shadow magic that grants you power. When you have taken grievous injuries, that energy heals and sustains you.</benefit>
      <benefit>While you are bloodied, you gain regeneration, meaning you regain hit points at the start of your turn. If you take radiant damage, your regeneration does not function until the end of your next turn.</benefit>
      <benefit>Your regeneration equals your Strength modifier or your Charisma modifier, whichever is higher. It increases by +3 at 11th level, and by +6 at 21st level.</benefit>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 1: Vampiric Bloodline</name>
      <benefit>Different Vampires exhibit different sets of vampiric traits, creating a set of abilities that are often referred to as vampiric bloodlines. Some bloodlines work through cunning, while others cultivate the bestial nature within all creatures of the night.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose either the Beguiler Bloodline or the Stalker Bloodline.</benefit>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Beguiler Bloodline</name>
         <benefit>You prefer the company of mortals and the benefits of being a part of society. Through the magic of blood and shadow, your mastery of your appearance and your subtle hunting methods have made you the most attractive of predators. Your enemies believe your lies even as they overlook your strangeness.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain a bonus to the damage rolls of your Vampire powers equal to your Charisma modifier. If you take Beguiler Noble paragon path, this bonus also applies to damage rolls for that paragon path's powers.</benefit>
         <benefit>This bonus to damage increases to 2 + your Charisma modifier at 5th level, to 5 + your Charisma modifier at 15th level, and to 8 + your Charisma modifier at 25th level.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>dark beckoning</i>]]> 1st-level at-will attack power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Dark Beckoning</title>
            <class>Vampire</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
            <fluff>Your mesmerizing presence draws your enemies closer</fluff>
            <part>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Charm, Implement, Psychic, Shadow</keyword>
               <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
               <type>Ranged</type> <range>5</range>
               <section>
                  <indent>4</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text><![CDATA[<b>Ranged</b>]]> 7</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <indent>4</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text><![CDATA[<b>Ranged</b>]]> 10</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>One creature that can see you</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>Dexterity vs. Will</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>1d6 + Dexterity modifier psychic damage, and you pull the target up to a number of squares equal to 2 + one-half your Charisma modifier.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>2d6 + Dexterity modifier psychic damage.</text>
               </section>
            </part>
         </power>
      </subfeature>

      <subfeature>
         <name>Stalker Bloodline</name>
         <benefit>The dark curse that made you a vampire took little toll on your physical form. However, in your heart and soul, you have become a beast more terrifying than any monster you had known of in mortal life. You live for the chase and the kill, though hold on to what little humanity you have left. The monster within you is your connection between the world of mortals and the world of shadow, and it makes you strong.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain a bonus to the damage rolls of your Vampire powers equal to your Strength modifier. If you take Stalker Noble paragon path, this bonus also applies to damage rolls for that paragon path's powers.</benefit>
         <benefit>This bonus to damage increases to 2 + your Strength modifier at 5th level, to 5 + your Strength modifier at 15th level, and to 8 + your Strength modifier at 25th level.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>hungry pounce</i>]]> 1st-level at-will attack power.</benefit>

         <power>
            <title>Hungry Pounce</title>
            <class>Vampire</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
            <fluff>Like the beast within you, you crouch low as you move in for a powerful strike at your foe</fluff>
            <part>
               <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
               <keyword>Implement, Shadow</keyword>
               <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
               <type>Melee</type> <range>1</range>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You shift 2 squares. If you were hidden when you used this power, you remain hidden until it has been resolved.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Shift 3 squares.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>One creature</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>Dexterity vs. Reflex</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>1d8 + Dexterity modifier damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>2d8 + Dexterity modifier damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <name>Miss:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>If the target is bloodied, you deal the additional damage from your Stalker bloodline.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You can use this power in place of a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]> when you charge. If you do, you can choose to either move your speed +2 or shift your speed as part of the charge instead of the normal movement effect for this power.</text>
               </section>
            </part>
         </power>
      </subfeature>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 1: Vampiric Reflexes</name>
      <benefit>You move with uncanny grace that makes it difficult for foes to strike you.</benefit>
      <benefit>While you are wearing cloth armor or no armor and aren't using a shield, you gain a +2 shield bonus to AC.</benefit>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 1: At-Will Attack Powers</name>
      <benefit>Vampires are know for their mythic strength that and thirst for blood - attributes that you wield as weapons when you enter combat.</benefit>
      <benefit>You have the <![CDATA[<i>taste of life</i> and <i>vampire claws</i>]]> powers as your 1st-level at-will attack powers.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Taste of Life</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
         <fluff>Your dread touch burns your foe with dark power, even as your own energy is temporarily restored</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
            <keyword>Implement, Necrotic, Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Melee</type> <range>touch</range>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>One creature</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Dexterity vs. Fortitude</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>1d8 + Dexterity modifier necrotic damage, and you gain temporary hit points. The temporary hit points equal 2 + your Strength modifier or your Charisma modifier.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>5 + your Strength modifier or your Charisma modifier temporary hit points.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>2d8 + Dexterity modifier necrotic damage, and 8 + your Strength modifier or your Charisma modifier temporary hit points.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <text>If the target is grabbed by you, or restrained, stunned or unconscious, you gain an additional 5 temporary hit points.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>

      <power>
         <title>Vampire Claws</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
         <fluff>You use the full force of your undead strength to drive your foe around</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
            <keyword>Implement, Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Melee</type> <range>touch</range>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>One creature</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Dexterity vs. Reflex</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>1d10 + Dexterity modifier damage, and you can slide the target 1 square.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>2d10 + Dexterity modifier damage, and slide 2 squares.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You can use this power as a <![CDATA[<i>melee basic attack</i>]]>.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 1: Daily Attack Power</name>
      <benefit>Your mortal body is merely a vessel for the magic that sustains you in your state of undeath. You can manipulate your mortal body with growing ease, transforming into a cluster of shadows that bite and slash at your foes, then let you secretly re-form in their mids to press the attack.</benefit>
      <benefit>You have the <![CDATA[<i>swarm of shadows</i>]]> power as your 1st-level daily attack power.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Swarm of Shadows</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
         <fluff>Your body becomes a swarm of batlike shadows that let you harry your enemies, then fade from sight</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>Daily</frequency>
            <keyword>Implement, Shadow, Teleportation</keyword>
            <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Close</type> <range>blast 3</range>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Each enemy in the blast</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Dexterity vs. Fortitude</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>2d8 + Dexterity modifier damage, and ongoing 5 damage (save ends).</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Miss:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Half damage.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You become invisible until the end of your next turn, and teleport to a square in the blast.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <text>If you are not adjacent to any enemies, you can make a Stealth check to hide as part of this teleportation.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 2: Utility Power</name>
      <benefit>You gain a 2nd-level Vampire utility power.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Charming Gaze</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
         <fluff>Your compelling demeanor throws your prey off its guard, lulling it into a false sense of security</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
            <keyword>Charm, Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>5</range>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <text>Using this power does not provoke <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i>]]></text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>One creature that can see you</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Until the end of your next turn, the target cannot take opportunity actions or immediate actions.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <text>In addition, you gain a +4 bonus to the first Bluff check or Diplomacy check you make against the target before the end of the encounter.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <text>If you used this power outside of combat, the target is not aware of the effect.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>

      <power>
         <title>Hunter's Gaze</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
         <fluff>As you focus on your foe, your predatory presence leaves it open to attack</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
            <keyword>Fear, Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>5</range>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <text>Using this power does not provoke <![CDATA[<i>opportunity attacks</i>]]></text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>One creature that can see you</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Until the end of your next turn, the target grants combat advantage while you are adjacent to it.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <text>In addition, you gain a +4 bonus to the first Intimidate check you make against the target before the end of the encounter.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 3: Encounter Attack Power</name>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>feral assault</i>]]> power as your 3rd-level encounter attack power.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Feral Assault</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>3</level>
         <fluff>You howl like a beast as you strike, your hunger and fury driving you to make a brutal attack</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
            <keyword>Implement, Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Melee</type> <range>touch</range>
            <section>
               <name>Blood is Life</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You can expend a healing surge to either target two creatures or to deal an extra +2d8 damage.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>One creature</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Attack:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>Dexterity vs. Reflex</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Hit:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>2d12 + Dexterity modifier damage.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Miss:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>2 + your Dexterity modifier + your implement's enhancement bonus damage if you expended a healing surge.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Level 4: Strength of Blood</name>
      <benefit>When your dark curse first claimed you, you consumed the life force of other creatures simply to survive. Now, you reinvest that spirit energy into a surge of physical strength on the battlefield.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>strength of blood</i>]]> class power.</benefit>

      <power>
         <title>Strength of Blood</title>
         <class>Vampire</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <fluff>You draw on the life force you have consumed to grant yourself a sudden burst of strength</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
            <keyword>Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Personal</type>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You gain a +5 power bonus to the next Athletics check, Endurance check, or Strength check you make before the end of your current turn.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Blood is Life:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You can expend a healing surge to to increase the power bonus to +10.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>
</class>
