<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Human</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Ambitios explorers, driven leaders, eager to master the world</shortfluff>

	<height>5'6" - 6'2"</height>
	<weight>135 - 220</weight>

	<ability>one ability score of your choice</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Normal</vision>

	<language>Common</language> <language>choice of one other</language>

	<trait>
		<name>Bonus Feat</name>
		<description>You gain a bonus feat at 1st level. You must meet the feat's prerequisites as normal.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Bonus Skill</name>
		<description>You gain training in one additional skill from your class skill list.</description>
		<description>You also gain one 1st-level skill power for that skill. This is in addition to the one you normally gain at 1st level.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Human Defense Bonus</name>
		<description>You gain a +1 racial bonus to Fortitude, Reflex, and Will.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Human Power Selection</name>
		<description>Choose an option for your character:</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Bonus At-Will Power:</i>]]> You know one extra 1st-level at-will attack power from your class.</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Heroic Effect:</i> You have the <i>heroic effort</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>

	<fluff>Of all the civilized races, humans are the most adaptable and diverse. Human settlements can be found almost anywhere, and human morals, customs, and interests vary greatly.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a human if you want: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be a decisive, resourceful hero with enough determination to face any challenge.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to have the most versatility and flexibility of any race.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be able to excel at any class you choose.</fluff>

	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Heroic Effort</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category>
			<fluff>Your grim focus and unbridled energy means that failure is not an option</fluff>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You miss with an attack or fail a saving throw</text>
				</section>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You gain a +4 racial bonus to the triggering attack roll or saving throw.</text>
				</section>
		</power>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Humans come in a wide variety of heights, weights, and colors. Some humans have black or dark brown skin, others are as pale as snow, and they cover the whole range of tans and browns in between. Their hais is black, brown, or a range of blonds and reds. Their eyes are most often brown, blue, or hazel.</benefit>
		<benefit>Human attire varies wildly, depending on the environment and society in which they live. Their clothing can be simple, ostentatious, or anything in between. It's not unusual for several distinct human cultures to live side by side in a particular area and mingle, so human armor, weaponry, and other items incorporate a variety of designs and motifs.</benefit>
		<benefit>Humans average life spans of about 75 years, though some venerable members of the race live as long as 90 or more years.</benefit>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Playing a Human</name>
		<benefit>Humans are decisive and sometimes rash. They explore the darkest reaches of the world in search of knowledge and power. They hurl themselves into danger, dealing with consequences as they arise. They act first and ponder later, trusting their will to prevail and their native resourcefulness to see them through perilous situations.</benefit>
		<benefit>Humans always look to the horizon, seeking to expand their influence and their territory. They chase power and want to change the world, for good or for ill. Their settlements are among the brightest lights in a dark and untamed world, and humans constantly seek to explore new lands and settle new frontiers.</benefit>
		<benefit>Their self-reliance and bravery inclines humans toward martial classes. They often prefer to find hidden reserves of strength in themselves rather than trust magic.</benefit>
		<benefit>That said, humans tend to be a pious race, worshiping the whole pantheon of gods. Their myths name no god as the creator of the race. Some tales say the gods worked together to create them, infusing them with the best qualities of each race that had come before. Other tales say that humans were the creation of a god whose name is no longer known, a god killed in the war against the primordials or perhaps assassinated by another deity (Asmodeus and Zehir are often accused of the deed).</benefit>
		<benefit>Humans are tolerant of other races, different beliefs, and foreign cultures. Most human settlements are diverse places where different races live together in relative peace. The human empire of Nerath, the last great world power, united many different peoples. Most of the human towns that have survived the empire's fall are fortified bastions against the encroaching darkness. When elven forests are razed or dwarven mines overrun, the survivors often flee to the nearest human town for protection.</benefit>
		<benefit>Despite the far reach and power of Nerath, humans in the present day are a scattered and divided people. Dozens of small kingdoms, fiefdoms, and free cities have arisen from Nerath's ruins, and many of these reams are petty, weak, or isolated. Tensions and misunderstandings among them often precipitate skirmishes, espionage, betrayal, and even open warfare.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Human Charasteristics:</b>]]> Adaptable, ambitious, bold, cocrruptible, creative, driven, hardy, pragmatic, resourceful, territorial, tolerant</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Alain, Alek, Benn, Brandis, Donn, Drew, Erik, Gregg, Kris, Marc, Mikal, Pieter, Regdar, Quinn, Samm, Thom, Wil</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Ana, Cassi, Eliza, Gwenn, Jenn, Kat, Keira, Luusi, Mari, Mika, Miri, Stasi, Shawna, Zanne</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Sample Human Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Brandis, Human Fighter</name>
			<benefit>Brandis is a mercenary who has sold his sword arm to every baronet, duke, and princeling from the mountains to the coast. His armor is practical, lacking any decoration, and his sword is intended only for battle, not as a mark of prestige. He prays daily to the Raven Queen -not out of devotion but because he knows that death is inevitable and he hopes to postpone it as long as possible.</benefit>
			<benefit>He began adventuring after a mission ended in disaster. His soldier companions were all dead, and he was captured by hobgoblins and held for ransom that no one cared enough to pay. He joined the band of adventurers that slew the hobgoblins. He has since found adventuring both more lucrative and more satisfying than his previous life.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Mari, Human Ranger</name>
			<benefit>Mari's eyes are always on the horizon. She is driven by a passion for exploration and a love of new places. She dreams of ultimately establishing a new settlement in a place where people can live in peace and freedom. She prays to Avandra for protection in her wandering and to Erathis for help in achieving her dreams.</benefit>
			<benefit>She is aware of her life's contradiction: She is a creature of the wilderness, but her dream is to tame and cultivate it. A part of her wonders whether she would be able to settle in the village she dreams of founding.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Thom, Human Wizard</name>
			<benefit>Thom's one desire is for power. He adventures in search of arcane lore and ancient artifacts that will increase his mastery of magic.</benefit>
			<benefit>He prays to Ioun because he sees knowledge as the key to power, but he is also drawn to Vecna, wondering what power the god of secrets might offer him in exchange for his devotion.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>A human can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>

		<power>
			<title>Extra Effort</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>You dig deep to find the strength to overcome an affliction</fluff>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You make a saving throw and dislike the result</text>
				</section>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You reroll the saving throw with a +2 power bonus, and must use the new result.</text>
				</section>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Rapid Move</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>You move with surprising swiftness, accomplishing more than most would think possible</fluff>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You take a move action.</text>
				</section>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Flush with Success</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>You feel your confidence build with each attack that hits home</fluff>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You hit with an attack on your turn</text>
				</section>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You gain 10 temporary hit points, and can then shift up to half your speed.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
					<text>15 temporary hit points.</text>
				</section>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Courageous Determination</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>Your enemy's success pales before your stalwart resolve as you refuse to give up</fluff>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Healing</keyword>
				<action>Immediate</action> <subaction>Reaction</subaction>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>An enemy bloodies you with an attack or hits you while you are bloodied</text>
				</section>
				<section personal=""/>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You can spend a healing surge to regain hit points equal to your healing surge value. You can then shift up to your speed.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Until the start of your next turn, you gain a +2 power bonus to all defenses.</text>
				</section>
		</power>
	</feature>

</race>
