<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Human</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Natural</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Ambitios explorers, driven leaders, eager to master the world</shortfluff>
	
	<height>5'6" - 6'2"</height>
	<weight>135 - 220</weight>
	
	<ability>one ability score of your choice</ability>
	<speed>6</speed>
	<vision>Normal</vision>
	
	<language>Common</language> <language>choice of one other</language>
	
	<trait>
		<name>Bonus Feat</name>
		<description>You gain a bonus feat at 1st level. You must meet the feat's prerequisites as normal.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Bonus Skill</name>
		<description>You gain training in one additional skill from your class skill list.</description>
		<description>You also gain one 1st-level skill power for that skill. This is in addition to the one you normally gain at 1st level.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Human Defense Bonus</name>
		<description>You gain a +1 racial bonus to Fortitude, Reflex, and Will.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Human Power Selection</name>
		<description>Choose an option for your character:</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Bonus At-Will Power:</i>]]> You know one extra 1st-level at-will attack power from your class.</description>
		<description><![CDATA[<i>Heroic Effect:</i> You have the <i>heroic effort</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>
	
	<fluff>Of all the civilized races, humans are the most adaptable and diverse. Human settlements can be found almost anywhere, and human morals, customs, and interests vary greatly.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play a human if you want to: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be a decisive, resourceful hero with enough determination to face any challenge.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to have the most versatility and flexibility of any race.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be able to excel at any class you choose.</fluff>
	
	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Heroic Effort</title>
			<class>Human</class> <category>Utility</category>
			<fluff>Your grim focus and unbridled energy means that failure is not an option</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You miss with an attack or fail a saving throw</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You gain a +4 racial bonus to the triggering attack roll or saving throw.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>
	
	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Humans come in a wide variety of heights, weights, and colors. Some humans have black or dark brown skin, others are as pale as snow, and they cover the whole range of tans and browns in between. Their hais is black, brown, or a range of blonds and reds. Their eyes are most often brown, blue, or hazel.</benefit>
		<benefit>Human attire varies wildly, depending on the environment and society in which they live. Their clothing can be simple, ostentatious, or anything in between. It's not unusual for several distinct human cultures to live side by side in a particular area and mingle, so human armor, weaponry, and other items incorporate a variety of designs and motifs.</benefit>
		<benefit>Humans average life spans of about 75 years, though some venerable members of the race live as long as 90 or more years.</benefit>
	</feature>
	
</race>
