<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../race.xsl"?>

<race>
	<name>Elf</name>
	<size>Medium</size>
	<origin>Fey</origin>
	<type>Humanoid</type>
	<shortfluff>Unmatched archers, cunning explorers, protectors of the wild forests</shortfluff>

	<height>5'4" - 6'0"</height>
	<weight>130 - 170</weight>

	<ability>Wisdom</ability>
  <ability>Dexterity</ability>
  <ability>Intelligence</ability>
	<speed>7</speed>
	<vision>Low-light Vision</vision>

	<language>Common</language> <language>Elven</language>

	<trait>
		<name>Skill Bonuses</name>
		<description>+2 Nature, +2 Perception</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Elven Weapon Proficiency</name>
		<description>You gain proficiency with the longbow and the shortbow.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Fey Origin</name>
		<description>Your ancestors were native to the Feywild, so your origin is fey instead of a natural.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Group Awareness</name>
		<description>You grant non-elf allies within 5 squares of you a +1 racial bonus to Perception checks.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Wild Step</name>
		<description>When you shift, you ignore the first square of difficult terrain you enter during that movement.</description>
		<description>This increases to the first 2 squares at 11th level, and to the first 3 squares at 21st level.</description>
	</trait>
	<trait>
		<name>Elf Racial Power</name>
		<description>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>elven accuracy</i>]]> racial power.</description>
	</trait>

	<fluff>Wild and free, elves guard their forested lands using stealth and deadly arrows from the trees. They build their homes in close harmony with the forest, so perfectly joined that travelers often fail to notice that they have entered an elven community until it is too late.</fluff>
	<fluff>Play an elf if you want: </fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to be quick, quiet, and wild.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to lead your companions through the deep woods that you know like the back of your hand.</fluff>
	<fluff>&#9658; to use deadly precision and swift hands to pepper your enemies with arrows.</fluff>

	<feature>
		<power>
			<title>Elven Accuracy</title>
			<class>Elf</class> <category>Utility</category>
			<fluff>With an instant focus, you take careful aim at your foe and strike with the legendary accuracy of the elves</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You make an attack roll and dislike the result</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You reroll the triggering attack roll and use the second result, even if it is lower.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Physical Qualities</name>
		<benefit>Elves are slender, athletic folk about as tall as humans. They have the same range of complexions as humans, tending more toward tan or brown hues. A typical elf's hair color is dark brown, autumn orange, mossy green, or deep gold. Elves' ears are long and pointed, and their eyes are vibrant blue, violet, or green. Elves have little body hair, but they favor a wild and loose look to their hair.</benefit>
		<benefit>Elves mature at about the same rate as humans, but show few effects of age past adulthood. The first sign of an elf's advancing age is tapically a change in hair color -sometimes graying but usually darkening or taking on more autumnal hues. Most elves live to be well over 200 years old and remain vigorous almost to the end.</benefit>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Playing an Elf</name>
		<benefit>Elves are people of deeply felt but short-lived passions. They are easily moved to delighted laughter, blinding wrath, or mournful tears. They are inclined to impulsive behavior, and members of other races sometimes see elves as flighty or impetuous, but elves do not shirk responsibility or forget commitments. Thanks in part to their long life span, elves sometimes have difficulty taking certain matters as seriously as other races do, but when genuine threats arise, elves are fierce and reliable allies.</benefit>
		<benefit>Elves revere the natural world. Their connection to their surroundings enables them to perceive much. They never cut living trees, and when they create permanent communities, they do so by carefully growing or weaving arbors, tree houses, and catwalks from living branches. They prefer the primal power of the natural world to the arcane magic their eladrin cousins employ. Elves love to explore new forests and new lands, and it's not unusual for individuals or small bands to wander hundreds of miles from their homelands.</benefit>
		<benefit>Elves are loyal and merry friends. They love simple pleasures -dancing, singing, footraces, and contests of balance and skill- and rarely see a reason to tie themselves down to dull or disagreeable tasks. Despite how unpleasant war can be, a threat to their homes, families, or friends can make elves grimly serious and prompt them to take up arms.</benefit>
		<benefit>At the dawn of creation, elves and eladrin were a single race dwelling both in the Feywild and in the world, and passing freely between the two. When the drow rebelled against their kin, under the leadership of the god Lolth, the resulting battles tore the fey kingdoms asunder. Ties between the peoples of the Feywild and the world grew tenuous, and eventually the elves and eladrin grew into two distinct races. Elves are descended from those who lived primarily in the world, and they no longer dream of the Feywild. They love the forests and wilds of the world that they have made their home.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Elf Charasteristics:</b>]]> Agile, friendly, intuitive, joyful, perceptive, quick, tempestous, wild</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Male Names:</b>]]> Adran, Aelar, Beiro, Carric, Erdan, Gennal, Heian, Lucan, Peren, Rolen, Theren, Varis</benefit>
			<benefit><![CDATA[<b>Female Names:</b>]]> Adrie, Birel, Chaedi, Dara, Enna, Faral, Irann, Keyleth, Lia, Mialee, Shava, Thia, Valna</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Sample Elf Adventurers</name>
		<benefit>Three sample adventurers are described below. You can use these as inspiration for your own character.</benefit>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Varis, Elf Ranger</name>
			<benefit>Varis is a devout worshiper of Melora, the god of the wilds. When a goblin army forced his people from their woodland, the elves took refuge in the nearest human town, walled and guarded by soldiers. Varis now leads other elves and some human townsfolk in raids against the goblins.</benefit>
			<benefit>Although he maintains a cheerful disposition, he frequently stares into the distance, listening. He is expecting at any moment to hear signs of approaching foes.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Lia, Elf Rogue</name>
			<benefit>Lia's ancestral forest burned to the ground decades ago. She grew up on the wasteland's fringes in a large human city, unable to quite fit in.</benefit>
			<benefit>Her dreams called her to the forests, while her waking hours were spent in the dirtiest parts of civilization. She joined a group of adventurers after trying to cut a warlock's purse, and she fell in love with the wide world beyond the city.</benefit>
		</subfeature>

		<subfeature>
			<name>Heian, Elf Cleric</name>
			<benefit>Heian is a follower of Sehanine, the god of the moon. The elven settlement where he was born still thrives in a forest untouched by the darkness spreading through the world, but he left home years ago, in search of new horizons and adventures.</benefit>
			<benefit>His travels laterly have brought rumors to his ears that danger might be brewing in the ancient forest, and he is torn between a desire to seek his own way in the world and a sense of duty to his homeland.</benefit>
		</subfeature>
	</feature>

	<feature>
		<name>Racial Utility Powers</name>
		<benefit>An elf can choose any of the following powers instead of a class utility power of the same level.</benefit>

		<power>
			<title>Long View</title>
			<class>Elf</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>2</level>
			<fluff>You scan the battlefield for your target, and when you find it, you know your next shot will strike true</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must have the Elven Weapon Proficiency racial trait.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>Choose one creature that you can see.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<text>Until the end of your next turn, you gain combat advantage against the chosen creature for Weapon attacks using either a longbow or a shorbow.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Leave No Trace</title>
			<class>Elf</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>6</level>
			<fluff>You use instinct and training to avoid showing signs of your passage and hide all signs of your approach</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<keyword>Stance</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You assume the Leave no Trace stance.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>Until the stance ends, the DC of any Perception checks to find your tracks or the tracks of up to eight allies who travel with you are increased by +10. If the tracks are found, identifying them requires a Nature check against the same DC.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<text>In addition, you and allies adjacent to you gain a +2 power bonus to Stealth checks.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>This stance ends after 8 hours, when you roll initiative, or when you end it as a minor action, whichever comes first.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Determined Accuracy</title>
			<class>Elf</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>10</level>
			<fluff>Resolved to not put a lie to the legendary accuracy of elves, you call all your powers of focus to the fore</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Daily</frequency>
				<action>Free</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
				<type>Personal</type>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Prerequisite:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must have the <![CDATA[<i>elven accuracy</i>]]> racial power.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You use your <![CDATA[<i>elven accuracy</i>]]> racial power and dislike the second roll</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You reroll the triggering attack roll with a +2 power bonus to the attack roll. You must use this new result, even if it is lower.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>

		<power>
			<title>Fey Communion</title>
			<class>Eladrin</class> <category>Utility</category> <level>16</level>
			<fluff>You touch your ally and set your own heart to beat in time, unleashing the healing power of emotional connections</fluff>
			<part>
				<frequency>Encounter</frequency>
				<keyword>Healing, Primal</keyword>
				<action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
				<type>Melee</type> <range>1</range>
				<section>
					<name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You must have at least one healing surge remaining.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You, and one ally adjacent to you</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade>
					<name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
					<text>You expend a healing surge to gain the following effects:</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<text>&#9658; You gain temporary hit points equal to one-half your healing surge value.</text>
				</section>
				<section>
					<shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
					<text>&#9658; The target ally regains a number of hit points equal to his or her healing surge value.</text>
				</section>
			</part>
		</power>
	</feature>

</race>
