<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Acid Splash</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Acid</trait> <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You splash a glob of acid that splatters on your target and nearby creatures. Make a ranged spell attack against your target's AC. If you hit, you deal 1d6 acid damage plus 1 splash acid damage. On a critical success, the target also takes 1 persistent acid damage.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The initial damage increases to 1d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, and the persistent damage increases to 2.</heighten>
      <heighten value="5th">The initial damage increases to 2d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, the persistent damage increases to 3, and the splash damage increases to 2.</heighten>
      <heighten value="7th">The initial damage increases to 3d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, the persistent damage increases to 4, and the splash damage increases to 3.</heighten>
      <heighten value="9th">The initial damage increases to 3d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier, the persistent damage increases to 5, and the splash damage increases to 4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Approximate</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Detection</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>10 feet</range> <area>1 cubic foot</area>

      <line>Your magic quickly flows over an area to help you count and catalog. Name a particular type of object you are looking for within the area. You gain an instant estimate of the quantity of the chosen objects that are clearly visible within the target area. The number is rounded to the largest digit. For example, you could look at a pile of 180 copper coins, and you would learn that it held about 200 coins, but you couldn't determine where were exactly 180 coins.</line>
      <line>The type of object you name can be as specific or general as you like -"dented copper coins" is as viable as "coins"- but the distinguishin features must be obvious at a glance, and the spell is automatically fooled by objects disguised as other objects. For instance, the spell would register cooper coins plated in gold as gold coins, not copper coins.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Dancing Lights</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Light</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range>
      <duration>sustained</duration>

      <line>You create up to four floating lights, no two of which are more than 10 feet apart. Each sheds light like a torch (bright light in a 20-foot radius, and dim light to the next 20 feet). When you Sustain the Spell, you can move any number of lights up to 60 feet. Each light must remain within 120 feet of you and within 10 feet of all others, or it winks out.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Detect Magic</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Detection</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>30-foot emanation</area>

      <line>You send out a pulse that registers the presence of magic. You receive no information beyond the rpesence or absence of magic. You can choose to ignore magic you're fully aware of, such as the magic items and ongoing spells of you and your allies.</line>
      <line>You detect illusion magic only if that magic's effect has a lower level than the level of your <![CDATA[<i>detect magic</i>]]> spell. However, items that have an illusion aura but aren't deceptive in appearance (such as an <![CDATA[<i>invisibility potion</i>]]>) typically are detected normally.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">You learn the school of magic for the highest-level effect within range that the spell detects. If multiple effects are equally strong, the GM determines which you learn.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">As 3rd level, but you also pinpoint the source of the highest-level magic. Like for an imprecise sense, you don't learn the exact location, but you can narrow down the source to within a 5-foot cube (or the nearest if larger than that).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Disrupt Undead</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 undead creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You lance the target with energy. You deal 1d6 positive damage plus your spellcasting ability modifier. The target must attempt a basic Fortitude save. If the creature critically fails the save, it is also enfeebled 1 for 1 round.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Electric Arc</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Electricity</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 or 2 creatures</targets>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>An arc of lightning leaps from one target to another. You deal electricity damage equal to 1d4 plus your spellcasting ability modifier.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gale Blast</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Air</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <area>5-foot emanation</area>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>Wind flows from your outstretched hands and whirls around you in a 5-foot emanation. Each creature in the area takes bludgeoning damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier, with a Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The creature takes half damage.</success>
         <fail>The creature takes full damage and is pushed 5 feet away from you.</fail>
         <critfail>The creature takes double damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The damage increases by 1d6.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Gouging Claw</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Morph</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You temporarily morph your limb into a clawed appendage. Make a melee spell attack roll against your target's AC. If you hit, you deal your choice of slashing or piercing damage equal to 1d6 plus your spellcasting ability modifier. On a critical success, you deal double damage plus 1d4 persistent bleed damage.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d6 and the persistent bleed damage on a critical increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Guidance</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1">verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <duration>Until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You ask for divine guidance, granting the target a +1 status bonus to one attack roll, Perception check, saving throw, or skill check the target attempts before the duration ends. The target chooses which roll to use the bonus on before rolling. If the target uses the bonus, the spell ends. Either way, the target is then temporarily immune for 1 hour.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Healing Plaster</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="1">somatic</cast>
      <range>5 feet</range> <targets>a handful of dirt or mud</targets>
      <duration>10 minutes</duration>

      <line>You purify some dirt of mud into a pliable, claylike plaster that can aid in clotting and healing. This restorative substance can be used in lieu of healer's tools for Medicine checks to Administer First Aid or Treat Wounds. If the plaster isn't used within the spell's duration, or if you Cast the Spell again before using the plaster, it reverts to being normal non-magical earth.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The plaster grants anyone using it to Administer First Aid or Treat Wounds a +1 item bonus to the Medicine check.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Know Direction</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Detection</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>

      <line>In your mind's eye, you see a path northward. You immediately know which direction is north (if it exists at your current location).</line>

      <heighten value="7th">You can instead know the direction to a familiar location, such as a previous home or a favorite tavern.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Light</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Light</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 object of 1 Bulk or less, either unattended or possessed by you or a willing ally</targets>
      <duration>until the net time you make your daily preparation</duration>

      <line>The object glows, casting bright light in a 20-foot radius (and dim light for the next 20 feet) like a torch. If you cast this spell again on a second object, the <![CDATA[<i>light</i>]]> spell on the first object ends.</line>

      <heighten value="4th">The objects sheds bright light in a 60-foot radius (and dim light for the next 60 feet).</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Prestidigitation</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>10 feet</range> <targets>1 object (cook, lift, or tidy only)</targets>
      <duration>sustained</duration>

      <line>The simplest magic does your bidding. You can perform simple magical effects for as long as you Sustain the Spell. Each time you Sustain the Spell, you can choose one of four options.</line>
      <line list="">
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Cook</b>]]> Cool, warm, or flavor 1 pound of nonliving material.</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Lift</b>]]> Slowly lift an unattended object of light Bulk or less 1 foot off the ground.</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Make</b>]]> Create a temporary object of negligible Bulk, made of congealed magical substance. The object looks crude and artificial and is extremely fragile; it can't be used as a tool, weapon, or spell component.</entry>
         <entry><![CDATA[<b>Tidy</b>]]> Color, clean, or soil an object of light Bulk or less. You can affect an object of 1 Bulk with 10 rounds of concentration, and a larger object a 1 minute per Bulk.</entry>
      </line>
      <line><![CDATA[<i>Prestidigitation</i>]]> can't deal damage or cause adverse conditions. Any actual change to an object (beyond what is noted above) persists only as long as you Sustain the Spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Produce Flame</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A small ball of flame appears in the palm of your hand, and you lash out with it either in melee or at range. Make a spell attack roll against your target's AC. This is normally a ranged attack, but you can also make a melee attack against a creature in your unarmed reach. The flame deals fire damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcastint ability modifier.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage, and 1d4 persistent fire damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">Increase the damage by 1d4 and the persistent damage on a critical hit by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Protect Companion</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Abjuration</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="1">verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>your eidolon, or a creature with the minion trait under your control</targets>
      <duration>until the start of your next turn</duration>

      <line>You extend your aura, as a magical shield that protects your eidolon or minion. The target gains a +1 circumstance bonus to AC until the start of your next turn. You gain the following reaction; after using the reaction, the spell ends and you can't cast <![CDATA[<i>protect companion</i>]]> again for 10 minutes.</line>

      <block>
         <name>Life Block</name> <action>R</action>
         <part><name>Trigger</name>The spell's target would take damage</part>
         <part><name>Effect</name>Reduce the triggering damage by 10, but you lose 5 Hit Points. Even if this reduces the damage to 0, the target still takes any effects that would come with the damage, such as the poison on a viper's fangs Strike.</part>
      </block>

      <heighten value="+2">The reaction reduces the damage by another 10, and you lose 5 more Hit Points. If you want to lose fewer Hit Points, you can choose to lower the damage and HP lost to what any lower-level version of the spell could do without lowering the spell's actual level.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Puff of Poison</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Inhaled</trait> <trait>Poison</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>5 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <save>Fortitude</save>

      <line>You exhale a shimmering cloud of toxic breath at an enemy's face. The target takes poison damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier and 2 persistent poison damage, depending on its Fortitude save.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The creature is unaffected.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes half initial and persistent damage.</success>
         <fail>The target takes full initial and persistent damage.</fail>
         <critfail>The target takes double initial and persistent damage.</critfail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+2">The initial poison damage increases by 1d8 and the persistent poison damage increases by 1.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ray of Frost</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Cold</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>120 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>You blast an icy ray. Make a ranged spell attack roll. The ray deals cold damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage and takes a -10-foot status penalty to its Speed for 1 round.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes normal way.</success>
      </line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Read Aura</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Detection</trait> <trait>Divination</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast>1 minute (somatic, verbal)</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 object</targets>

      <line>You focus on the target object, opening your mind to perceive magical auras. When the casting is complete, you know whether that item is magical, and if it is, you learn the school of magic.</line>
      <line>If the object is illusory, you detect this only if the effect's level is lower than the level of your <![CDATA[<i>read aura</i>]]> spell.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">You can target up to 10 objects.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">You can target any number of objects.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Scatter Scree</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Earth</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>two contiguous 5-foot cubes</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>You evoke a jumble of rocks in the area. The scattering rocks deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier to creatures in the area, with a basic Reflex save. The ground in the area becomes difficult terrain for the duration. A creature can Interact to clear a square of this scree.</line>
      <line>If you cast this spell again, any previous scree you have scattered ends.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sigil</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Transmutation</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>touch</range> <targets>1 creature or object</targets>
      <duration>unlimited (see below)</duration>

      <line>You harmlessly place your unique magical sigil, which is about 1 square inch in size, on the target creature or object. The mark can be visible or invisible, and you can change it from one state to another by using an Interact action to touch the target. The mark can be scrubbed or scraped off with 5 minutes of work. If it's on a creature, it fades naturally over the course of a week.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The sigil instead fades on creature after 1 month.</heighten>
      <heighten value="5th">The sigil instead fades on a creature after 1 year.</heighten>
      <heighten value="7th">The sigil never fades on a creature.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spout</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Evocation</trait> <trait>Primal</trait> <trait>Water</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <area>a 5-foot cube (see below)</area>
      <save>basic Reflex</save>

      <line>Water blasts upward, coming out of the ground, rising from a pool, or even manifesting from thin air. Any creatures in the area take bludgeoning damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier, with a basic Reflex save.</line>
      <line>You can change this spell's area to a 5-foot burst, provided you center the burst in a body of water. This body of water can be as small as a pond or creek, but not as small as a puddle or bathtub.</line>

      <heighten value="+1">The damage increases by 1d4.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Stabilize</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Healing</trait> <trait>Necromancy</trait> <trait>Positive</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 dying creature</targets>

      <line>Positive energy shuts death's door. The target loses the dying condition, though it remains unconscious at 0 Hit Points.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tame</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Auditory</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Enchantment</trait> <trait>Mental</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>10 feet</range> <targets>1 non-hostile domesticated animal</targets>
      <save>Will</save> <duration>1 minute</duration>

      <line>As you make comforting sounds and gestures, you approach the target in a friendly manner. You improve the target's attitude to you by one step (from unfriendly to neutral, neutral to friendly, or friendly to helpful) for the duration of the spell unless it succeeds at a Will save. Afterwards, the target is temporarily immune for 1 day.</line>
      <line>This spell works only on domesticated animals; for example, you could use it on guard dogs or stray dogs, but not feral dogs or wolves. If the socialization of the animal is in question, the decision is up to the GM.</line>

      <heighten value="3rd">The duration becomes 10 minutes.</heighten>
      <heighten value="6th">The duration becomes 1 hour.</heighten>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Tanglefoot</title>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Conjuration</trait> <trait>Plant</trait> <trait>Primal</trait>
      <cast action="2">somatic, verbal</cast>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>

      <line>A vine covered in sticky sap appears from thin air, flicking from your hand and lashing itself to the target. Attempt a ranged spell attack against the taget.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target gains the immobilized condition and takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty and the immobilized condition.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes a -10-foot circumstance penalty to Speed for 1 round. It can attempt to Escape against your spell DC to remove the penalty.</success>
         <fail>The target is unaffected.</fail>
      </line>

      <heighten value="2nd">The effects last for 2 rounds.</heighten>
      <heighten value="4th">The effects last for 1 minute.</heighten>
   </rule>

</catalog>
