<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Nephilim</title>
      <type>Heritage</type>
      <uncommon/><trait>Nephilim</trait><trait>Versatile</trait>

      <line>Your nature is influenced by celestials, fiends, or monitors. This manifests as a combination of features that belie your heritage, such as golden eyes, a halo, horns, or a tail. You gain the <u>nephilim</u> trait, in addition to the traits from your ancestry. You gain low-light vision, or you gain darkvision if your ancestry already has low-light vision.</line>
      <line>You can choose from nephilim feats and feats from your ancestry whenever you gain an ancestry feat.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Low-Light Vision</title>
      <type>Sense</type>

      <line>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the concealed condition due to dim light.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Hellspawn</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Lineage</trait> <trait>Tiefling</trait>

      <line>Your lineage descends from devils, the conniving schemers of Hell's malevolent hierarchy. You're as skilled at noticing lies and twisted words as you are at constructing them.</line>
      <line>You are trained in Deception and Legal Lore. If you were already trained in Deception (from your background or class, for example), you instead become trained in a skill of your choice. You also gain the Lie to Me skill feat.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Lie to Me</title>
      <type>Feat</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait> <trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Deception</prereq>

      <line>You can use Deception to weave traps to trip up anyone trying to deceive you. If you can engage in conversation with someone trying to Lie to you, use your Deception DC if it's higher than your Perception DC to determine whether they succeed. This doesn't apply if you don't have a back-and-forth dialogue, such as when someone attempts to Lie during a long speech.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Lie</title>
      <type>Deception</type>
      <trait>Auditory</trait><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Linguistic</trait><trait>Mental</trait><trait>Secret</trait>

      <line>You try to fool someone with an untruth. Doing so takes at least 1 round, or longer if the lie is elaborate. You roll a single secret Deception check and compare it against the Perception DC of every creature you are trying to fool. The GM might give them a circumstance bonus based on the situation and the nature of the lie you are trying to tell. Elaborate or highly unbelievable lies are much harder to get a creature to believe than simpler and more believable lies, and some lies are so big that it's impossible to get anyone to believe them.</line>
      <line results="">
         <success>The target believes your lie.</success>
         <fail>The target doesn't believe your lie and gains a +4 circumstance bonus against your attempts to Lie for the duration of the conversation. The target is also more suspicious of you in the future.</fail>
      </line>
      <line>At the GM's discretion, if a creature initially believes your lie, it might attempt a Perception check later to Sense Motive against your Deception DC to realize it's a lie. This usually happens if the creature discovers enough evidence to counter your statements.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Oddity Identification</title>
      <type>Feat</type><level>1</level>
      <trait>General</trait><trait>Skill</trait>
      <prereq>trained in Occultism</prereq>

      <line>When you become aware of a magical effect or see a spell being cast, you can immediately determine if it twists minds (with the <u>mental</u> trait), fights against fortune (with the <u>fortune</u> or <u>misfortune</u> trait), or reveals secrets (with the <u>detection</u>, <u>prediction</u>, <u>revelation</u>, or <u>scrying</u> traits). At the GM’s discretion, similar effects can also fall into these categories. When you Identify Magic or Recall Knowledge to learn more about these effects, you can always use Occultism without penalty and gain a +2 circumstance bonus.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Diabolic Bloodline</title>
      <type>Class Feature</type>

      <line>Your bloodline gives you your spellcasting talent. Devils are evil with a silver tongue, and one of your ancestors dallied in darkness or made in infernal pact.</line>
      <line>You cast spells of the divine tradition.</line>
      <line name="Bloodline Skills">Deception, Religion</line>
      <line name="Sorcerous Gifts">cantrip: <i>ignition</i>, 1st: <i>charm</i></line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sorcerous Potency</title>
      <type>Class Feature</type>

      <line>Because of the magical power inherent in your blood, your spells that hurt or cure are stronger than those of other spellcasters. When you Cast a Spell from your spell slots that either deals damage or restores Hit Points, you gain a status bonus to that spell's damage or healing equal to the spell's rank. This applies only to the initial damage or healing the spell deals when cast. An individual creature takes this damage or benefits from this healing only once per spell, even if the spell would damage or heal that creature multiple times.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Sorcerer Spellcasting</title>

      <line>Your bloodline provides you with incredible magical power. You are a spellcaster and can cast spells of of a tradition determined by your bloodline using the Cast a Spell activity. As a sorcerer, you draw your power from within, and the gestures and incantations you use to shape your power might evoke the nature of your bloodline.</line>
      <line>Each day, you can cast up to a certain number of spells. You must know spells to cast them, and you learn them via the Spell Repertoire class feature. The number of spells you can cast each day is called your spell slots.</line>
      <line>Some of your spells require you to attempt a spell attack roll to see how effective they are, or have your enemies roll against your spell DC (typically by attempting a saving throw). Your spell attack rolls and spell DCs use your Charisma modifier.</line>
      <!--line name="Heighening Spells">You can fill spell slots of 2nd rank or higher with stronger versions of lower-rank spells. This increases the spell's rank, heightening it to match the spell slot. Many spells have specific improvements when they are heightened to certain ranks.</line-->
      <line name="Cantrips">Some of your spells are cantrips. A cantrip is a special type of spell that doesnt use spell slots. You can cast a cantrip at will, any number of times per day. A cantrip is automatically heightened to half your level rounded up.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Spell Repertoire</title>

      <line>The collection of spells you can cast is called your spell repertoire. At 1st level, you learn two 1st-rank spells of your choice and four cantrips of your choice, as well as an additional spell and cantrip from your bloodline You choose these from the common spells from the tradition corresponding to your bloodline, or from other spells from that tradition to which you have access. You can cast any spell in your spell repertoire by using a spell slot of an appropriate spell rank.</line>
      <line>Though you gain them at the same rate, your spell slots and the spells in your spell repertoire are separate. If a feat or other ability adds a spell to your spell repertoire, it wouldn't give you another spell slot or vice versa.</line>
      <line name="Swapping Spells in Your Repertoire">As you gain new spells in your spell repertoire, you might want to replace some of the spells you previously learned. Each time you gain a level and learn new spells, you can swap out one of your old spells for a different spell of the same rank. This spell can be a cantrip, but you can't swap out bloodline spells. You can also swap out spells by retraining during downtime.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Bloodline Spells</title>
      <line>Your bloodline grants you bloodline spells, special spells unique to your lineage. Bloodline spells are a type of focus spell. It costs 1 Focus Point to cast a focus spell, and you start with a focus pool of 1 Focus Point. You refill your focus pool during your daily preparations, and you can regain 1 Focus Point by spending 10 minutes using the Refocus activity. Unlike other characters, you don't need to do anything specific to Refocus, as the power flowing through your veins naturally replenishes your focus pool.</line>
      <line name="Diabolic Bloodline">You gain the <i>diabolic edict</i> bloodline spell.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Blood Magic</title>
      <line>Whenever you cast a Bloodline spell using a Focus Point or a Sorcerous Gift spell using a spell slot, you choose one blood magic effect you know to benefit from.</line>
      <line name="Diabolic Bloodline - Tongue of Flame">Your tongue becomes laced with the fires of Hell, and you can either lash out at a foe with it or swallow it to make your lies more palatable. Either a target takes 1 fire damage per spell rank (if the spell already deals fire damage, combine this with the spell's initial damage) or you gain a +2 status bonus to Deception checks for 1 round.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Diabolic Edict</title> <action>1</action>
      <type>Focus</type><level>1</level>
      <uncommon/><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Focus</trait><trait>Sorcerer</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range><targets>1 willing living creature</targets>
      <duration>1 round</duration>

      <line>You issue a diabolic edict, demanding the target perform a particular task and offering rewards for its fulfillment. It gains a +1 status bonus to attack rolls and skill checks related to performing the task. If it refuses to perform the task you proclaimed, it instead takes a -1 status penalty to all attack rolls and skill checks.</line>
   </rule>

</catalog>
