<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../rule.xsl"?>
<catalog>

   <rule>
      <title>Daze</title><action>2</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type><level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait><trait>Mental</trait><trait>Nonlethal</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range><targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>basic Will</defense>

      <line>You push into the target's mind and daze it with a mental jolt. The jolt deals 1d6 mental damage with a basic Will save. If the target critically fails its save, it is also <br/>stunned 1.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Divine Lance</title><action>2</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type><level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait><trait>Cantrip</trait><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait><trait>Sanctified</trait><trait>Spirit</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range><targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You unleash a beam of divine energy. Make a ranged spell attack against the target's AC, dealing 2d4 spirit damage on a hit.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Forbidding Ward</title><action>2</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type><level>1</level>
      <trait>Cantrip</trait><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range><targets>1 ally and 1 enemy</targets>
      <duration>sustained up to 1 minute</duration>

      <line>You ward an ally against the attacks and hostile spells from the target enemy. The target ally gains a +1 status bonus to Armor Class and saving throws against the target enemy's attacks, spells, and other effects.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Haunting Hymn</title><action>2</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type><level>1</level>
      <trait>Auditory</trait><trait>Cantrip</trait><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait><trait>Sonic</trait>
      <area>15-foot cone</area>
      <defense>basic Fortitude</defense>

      <line>You echo a jarring hymn that only creatures in the area can hear. the hymn deals 1d8 sonic damage, with a basic Fortitude save. If a target critically fails the save, it's also deafened for 1 minute.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Ignition</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Cantrip</type> <level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait> <trait>Cantrip</trait> <trait>Concentrate</trait> <trait>Divine</trait> <trait>Fire</trait> <trait>Manipulate</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range> <targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>You snap your fingers and point at a target, which begins to smolder. Make a ranged spell attack roll against your target's AC, dealing 2d4 fire damage on a hit. If the target is within your melee reach, you can choose to make a melee spell attack with the flame instead of a ranged spell attack, which increases all the spell's damage dice to d6s.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage, and 1d4 persistent fire damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Admonishing Ray</title><action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type><level>1</level>
      <trait>Attack</trait><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait><trait>Nonlethal</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range><targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>AC</defense>

      <line>A ray of energy bludgeons your target into submission without causing lasting harm. When you cast this spell, you choose whether the ray feels like a strong punch or slap. Make a spell attack roll against the target's AC, dealing 2d6 bludgeoning damage on a hit.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Charm</title><action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type><level>1</level>
      <trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Emotion</trait><trait>Incapacitation</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait><trait>Mental</trait><trait>Subtle</trait>
      <range>30 feet</range><targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>Will</defense><duration>1 hour</duration>

      <line>To the target, your words are honey and your visage seems bathed in a dreamy haze. It must attempt a Will save, with a +4 circumstance bonus if you or your allies recently threatened it or used hostile actions against it.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target is unaffected and aware you tried to charm it.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target is unaffected but thinks your spell was something harmless instead of <i>charm</i> unless it identifies the spell.</success>
         <fail>The target's attitude becomes friendly towards you. If it was friendly, it becomes helpful. It can't use hostile actions against you.</fail>
         <critfail>The target's attitude becomes helpful towards you, and it can't use hostile actions against you.</critfail>
      </line>
      <line>You can Dismiss the spell. If you use hostile actions against the target, the spell ends. When the spell ends, the target doesn't necessarily realize it was charmed unless its friendship with you or the actions you convinced it to take clash with its expectations, meaning you could potentially convince the target to continue being your friend via mundane means.</line>
   </rule>

   <rule>
      <title>Purifying Icicle</title> <action>2</action>
      <type>Spell</type><level>1</level>
      <uncommon/><trait>Attack</trait><trait>Cold</trait><trait>Concentrate</trait><trait>Divine</trait><trait>Manipulate</trait><trait>Vitality</trait>
      <range>60 feet</range><targets>1 creature</targets>
      <defense>Fortitude</defense>

      <line>You evoke life essence into the form of water and freeze it, then launch the icicle at a foe. Make a ranged spell attack roll against the target's Fortitude DC, dealing 2d6 piercing damage and 1d6 cold damage on a hit. If the target is undead, the icicle deals an additional 1d4 vitality damage on hit.</line>
      <line results="">
         <critsuccess>The target takes double damage, and takes a –10-foot circumstance penalty to its Speeds for 1 round as the icicle lodges inside them before melting away.</critsuccess>
         <success>The target takes full damage.</success>
      </line>
   </rule>

</catalog>
