<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="condition.xsl"?>
<catalog>
   <collection>List of Standard Conditions</collection>
   <intro>The following definitions specify the effects of each basic condition where a creature is subject to it. Some conditions include other conditions within their effects. For instance, an unconscious creature is also helpless and prone.</intro>

   <condition>
      <title>Blinded</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't see, which means its targets have total concealment against it.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature takes a -10 penalty to Perception checks.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't flank.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature cannot have combat advantage against anyone.</line>
      <line>This condition applies to creatures that have been temporarily blinded, such as by exposure to brilliant light or a magical darkness clouding their eyes. It doesn't apply to creatures that are naturally blind (such as oozes).</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Dazed</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature doesn't get its normal complement of actions on its turn; it can take either a standard, a move, or a minor action. The creature can still take free actions.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't take immediate actions or opportunity actions.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't flank.</line>
      <line>The dazed condition is a common way of representing a general state of stupor. Dazed creatures don't act as quickly as normal or respond to danger as readily. A creature might be dazed because it took a hard blow to the head, a spell assaulted its mind, or a prayer called forth a clap of thunder around it.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Deafened</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't hear.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature takes a -10 penalty to Perception checks.</line>
      <line>This condition applies to creatures that have temporarily lost their normal sense of hearing, not to creatures that normally can't hear. The game effects of the condition are relatively minor, but being deafened can be a flavorful result of a <key>Thunder</key> power.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Dominated</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't take actions voluntarily. Instead, the dominator chooses a single action for the creature to take on the creature's turn: a standard, a move, a minor, or a free action. The only powers and other game features that the dominator can make the creature use are ones that can be used at-will.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't flank.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature's allies remain its allies, and its enemies remain its enemies.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>If the dominator tries to force the creature to throw itself into a pit or move into some other form of hindering terrain, the creature gets a saving throw to resist entering the terrain. A successful save in this instance does not end the effect.</line>
      <line>A wide variety of creatures and powers can impose this condition. Just as in myth and legend, vampires and fey creatures are adept at controlling the minds of others, but the specific limitations of this condition prevent such creatures from forcing player characters to expend their best powers.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Dying</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature is unconscious.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature must make death saving throws.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>This condition ends immediately on the creature when it regains hit points.</line>
      <line>Being reduced to 0 hit points or fewer automatically subjects an adventurer to this condition. Monsters normally die when they are reduced to 0 hit points, so this condition applies to them only in exceptional situations. See the Dying and Death rules for additional details.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Grabbed</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature is immobilized.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>Maintaining this condition on the creature occupies whatever appendage, object, or effect the grabber used to initiate the grab.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>This condition ends immediately on the creature if the grabber is subjected to an effect that prevents it from taking actions, or if the creature ends up outside the range of the grabbing power or effect.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The grabber can <i>drag</i> the grabbed creature.</line>
      <line>A grabbed creature can take the <i>escape</i> action to try and get away. Other common tactics for escaping a grab are to teleport away or to be pulled, pushed, or slid out of the grabber's reach.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Helpless</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The condition is a precondition for certain things, such as the <i>coup de grace</i> action.</line>
      <line>Normally, a creature is affected by this condition because it is unconscious, but the DM might rule that a creature is so firmly bound that it is effectively helpless.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Immobilized</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't move, unless it teleports or is pulled, pushed, or slid.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can still stand from prone, pull an item from a backpack, or attack normally.</line>
      <line>The creature might have taken a seriour but temporary to the legs, be rooted by fear, or it could be stuck to the ground by a huge cobweb.</line>
      <line>Restrained is a similar but more restricting condition. A creature that is actually paralyzed might have the stunned condition rather than being immobilized or restrained.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Marked</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls for any attack that doesn't include the marking creature as a target.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>A creature can be subjected to only one mark at a time, and a new mark supersedes an old one.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>A mark ends immediately when the marking creature dies or falls unconscious.</line>
      <line>This condition reflects the ability of some creatures to claim the attention of a chosen target in battle. When a target is marked, it has a hard time ignoring the creature that marked it. Most marking effects have a very short duration, or else they require the marking creature to remain a threat to the marked target.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Petrified</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature is unconscious.</line>
      <line indent="2"><bullet/>While a creature normally falls prone when it becomes unconscious, a petrified creature usually remains standing as a statue.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature has resist 20 to all damage.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature doesn't age.</line>
      <line>Usually a creature is subject to this condition when it is turned to stone, such as by a medusa. Often the only way to end this condition is by using a magical ritual.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Prone</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature is lying down, or similarly disoriented.</line>
      <line indent="2"><bullet/>A climbing or flying creature that is knocked prone falls.</line>
      <line indent="2"><bullet/>This condition can affect limbless creatures, such as fish and snakes, as well as amorphous creatures, such as oozes. Such a creature is writhing or unsteady, rather than literally lying down.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The only way the creature can move is by crawling, teleporting, or being pulled, pushed, or slid.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage to attackers making melee attacks against it, but gains a +2 bonus to all defenses against ranged attacks from attackers that aren't adjacent to it.</line>
      <line>A creature can end this condition on itself by standing up. A creature can drop prone as a minor action.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Removed from Play</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't take actions.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature has neither line of sight nor line of effect to anything, and nothing has line of sight or line of effect to it.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature's turns start and end as normal.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>An effect that removes a creature from play specifies where the creature reappears when it returns to play. Typically the creature reappears in the space it left, or in the nearest unoccupied space if that space is now occupied.</line>
      <line>A creature is normally subject to this condition because it has been transported to another plane of existence or is engulfed or swallowed.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Restrained</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't move, unless it teleports. It can't even be pulled, pushed, or slid.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature takes a -2 penalty to attack rolls.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage.</line>
      <line>This condition is similar to the immobilized condition, but it puts more restriction on the creature's ability to attack or defend itself.</line>
      <line>This condition usually results from being held in place by something: vines, tentacles, manacles attached to a wall, or a monster's gaping jaws. Whatever is holding the creature in place interferes with its ability to move around freely.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Slowed</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature's speed becomes 2 if it was higher than that. This applies to all of the creature's movement modes (walking, flying, and so on), but it does not apply to forced movement against it or teleportation.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>If the creature moves without using its speed, the maximum distance is halved (to a minimum of 2 squares).</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature cannot benefit from bonuses to speed, although it can benefit from powers and actions, such as the <i>run</i> action, that allow it to move farther than its speed.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>If the creature is subjected to this condition while it is moving, it must stop if it has already moved as far as its new movement maximum.</line>
      <line>A variety of different effects can cause a creature to become slowed. A creature subject to this condition might have taken an injury to the legs, or it might be entangled in something. The creature could be poisoned, beset by wracking pain that hampers movement, encased in frost, or slowly turning to stone.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Stunned</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't take actions.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't flank.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature falls if it is flying, unless it can hover.</line>
      <line>Usually a creature is subjected to this condition because of significant physical or mental trauma. It might be on the brink of succumbing to a deadly poison, completely paralyzed by a ghoul's bite, reeling under mental assault, or bettered by an extremely powerful blow.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Surprised</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't take actions.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature grants combat advantage.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't flank.</line>
      <line>Normally a creature is subjected to this condition only during a surprise round, at the end of which the condition ends.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Unconscious</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature is helpless.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't take actions.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature takes a -5 penalty to all defenses.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature is unaware of its surroundings.</line>
      <line indent="2">A creature that has fallen asleep naturally —as opposed to being knocked unconscious— is not totally deprived of awareness; it can use its passive Perception to hear things, with a -5 penalty.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature falls prone, if possible.</line>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature can't flank.</line>
      <line>This condition applies when a creature is knocked out, cast into a magical slumber, or otherwise incapacitated totally.</line>
   </condition>

   <condition>
      <title>Weakened</title>
      <line indent="1"><bullet/>The creature's attacks deal half damage.</line>
      <line indent="2"><bullet/>Two kinds of damage are not affected: ongoing damage, and damage that isn't the result of an attack roll.</line>
      <line>When a creature is weakened, it can't exert force as well as normal. Not only physical attacks are affected; the creature's magical powers are hampered just as much. The creature's might is diminished in every way, usually as a result of a life-sapping effect or a numbing blow.</line>
   </condition>
</catalog>
