<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../power.xsl"?>

<catalog>
   <collection>Assassin Lvl 1 Encounter Attack Hexes</collection>

   <power>
      <title>Gloom Thief</title>
      <class>Assassin</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
      <fluff>As you slash your foe, you seize a part of its shadow, which you use to hide yourself from your enemies' eyes</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Illusion, Shadow, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section><name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type><range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target><text>Dexterity vs. AC</text></section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Hit:</name>
            <text>2[W] + Dexterity modifier damage.</text>
         </section>
         <section shade="">The gloom distance is a number of squares equal to to 1 + the number of your shrouds on the target.</section>
         <section shade="">If you were hidden when you used this attack, you can make a Stealth check to remain hidden, though you take a -10 penalty to the check as if you were running.</section>
         <section>
            <name>Miss:</name><text>The gloom distance is a number of squares equal to one-half the number of your shrounds on the target (minimum 1 square, adjacent).</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Effect:</name>Until the end of your next turn, you are invisible while within within the gloom distance of the target.
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Nightmare Shades</title>
      <class>Assassin</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
      <fluff>The darkness in the corner of your foe's eyes shifts and moves, causing it to glance about in terror that causes it to forget the true threat to its life</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Fear, Implement, Psychic, Shadow</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section><name>Attack:</name><type>Ranged</type><range>5</range><target>one creature</target>Dexterity vs. Will</section>
         <section shade=""><name>Hit:</name><text>2d8 + Dexterity modifier psychic damage, and the target grants combat advantage to you until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section><name>Effect:</name><text>Until the end of your next turn, you gain a power bonus to damage rolls against the target equal to the number of your shrouds on it.</text>
         </section>
         <section><indent>1</indent><name>Night Stalker:</name><text>While you have this bonus, the target also counts as being adjacent to none of your enemies for the purposes of your additional damage.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Shadow Darts</title>
      <class>Assassin</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You launch a volley of chilling darts made of shadow energy at your foe</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Cold, Implement, Shadow</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Attack:</name><type>Ranged</type> <range>5/10</range><target>one creature</target>
            <text>Dexterity vs. Reflex</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <text>Make three attack rolls and resolve them as a single hit, the power only counts as missing if all of them miss, and counts as a critical hit if at least one of them is a critical</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Hit:</name><text>1d4 + Dexterity modifier cold damage if one attack hits, 2d4 + Dexterity modifier cold damage if two attack rolls hit, or 3d4 + Dexterity modifier cold damage if three attacks hit.</text>
         </section>
   </power>

   <power>
      <title>Smothering Shadow</title>
      <class>Assassin</class> <category>Attack</category> <level>1</level>
      <fluff>You stab at your foe and channel shadow energy into its body, causing its own shadow to become so heavy to be a hindrance</fluff>
         <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
         <keyword>Shadow, Weapon</keyword>
         <action>Standard</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
         <section>
            <name>Attack:</name><type>Melee</type> <range>weapon</range><target>one creature</target>
            <text>Dexterity vs. AC</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <shade>true</shade>
            <name>Hit:</name><text>2[W] + Dexterity damage.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <name>Effect:</name><text>The target is slowed until the end of your next turn.</text>
         </section>
         <section>
            <indent>1</indent>
            <name>Bleak Disciple:</name><text>While slowed, the target also counts as being nonbloodied for the purposes of your additional damage. If it is already nonbloodied, it counts as being at full hit points instead.</text>
         </section>
   </power>
</catalog>
