<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
   <name>Assassin</name>
   <subname>Stalker</subname>
   <role>Striker</role>
   <source>Shadow</source>
   <shortfluff>You are the ghost in the night and the whisper on the wind - barriers are worthless against you, and you strike your foes with sudden, precise force.</shortfluff>
   <keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
   <keyability>Constitution</keyability>
   <keyability>Charisma</keyability>
   
   <proficiency>
      <type>Armor</type>
      <name>Cloth</name>
      <name>Leather</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Weapon</type>
      <name>Simple one-handed melee</name>
      <name>Simple ranged</name>
      <name>Military heavy blade</name>
      <name>Military light blade</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Implement</type>
      <name>Ki focus</name>
      <name>any proficient weapon for Assassin powers</name>
   </proficiency>
   
   <defense>
      <name>Fortitude</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
   <defense>
      <name>Will</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
   
   <hpbase>12</hpbase>
   <hpgain>5</hpgain>
   <surgebase>6</surgebase>
   
   <skills>
      <trained>Stealth</trained>
      <number>4</number>
   </skills>
   
   <fluff>Few creatures embrace shadow magic without both a compelling reason and a measure of desperation. Not many visit the Shadowfell willingly, let alone pledge a shard of their souls to it. Yet that is exactly what Assassins, and other practitioners of shadow magic, do to gain their power.</fluff>
   <fluff>As an Assassin, you cede a portion of yourself to the Shadowfell, replacing a fundamental part of your being with a dark reflection of your true self. At times, you can manifest this twisted image in place of your body so that you can face attacks with little cause for concern. Also, the infusion of shadow magic allows you to spot the weakest points in a victim's defenses. With a few moments of study, you can reduce even the stoutest warrior to a corpse.</fluff>
   <fluff>An Assassin usually keeps his or her profession a secret, since few trust those who regularly deal in death. Assassins' guilds provide some measure of protection, especially in those regions where the study of shadow magic and assassination as an art form are banned.</fluff>
   <fluff>As a Stalker, you are an outcast. You traded away part of your soul for the power of death. Perhaps you seek justice against a powerful enemy, or maybe you had no other way to preserve yourself in the face of a bleak, uncaring world. Whatever drew you onto the Stalker's path, you are an avatar of death and a trained killer from whom few can escape unharmed.</fluff>
   
   <feature>
      <name>Assassin's Shroud</name>
      <benefit> The dark magic of the Shadowfell courses through your veins, tainting your soul but granting you the ability to subject an enemy to invisible shrouds that reveal its weakest points. The more of your shrouds there are on a target, the deadlier a blow you can strike against it.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>assassin's shroud</i>]]> class power that allows you to place your shrouds on a target. Other benefits can also allow you to place your shrouds on a target. You can have your shrouds on only one creature, and one creature can have up to four of your shrouds on it. A creature can have shrouds from multiple assassins on it.</benefit>
      <benefit>If a creature is not aware of your presence, it is not aware of your shrouds being on it either.</benefit>
      <benefit>Before you make an attack roll against the target, you choose to invoke either all your shrouds on it or none of them. If you invoke your shrouds and the attack hits, the attack deals +1d6 damage for each shroud. If the attack misses, you deal damage for one less shroud, even if the attack normally deals half or no damage on a miss. After the attack has been resolved, all your shrouds vanish from the target.</benefit>
      <benefit>The damage per shroud increases to 1d8 + 2 at 11th level, and to 1d10 + 4 at 21st level.</benefit>
      
      <power>
         <title>Assassin's Shroud</title>
         <class>Asassin</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <fluff>You cause invisible shrouds to settle on your foe that reveal the target's weak points to your keen gaze</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
            <keyword>Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Free</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <text>Using this power does not trigger opportunity attacks</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>One enemy you can see</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You place your shrouds on the target, or increase your number of shrouds on it by one. The shrouds lasts until the end of the encounter, or until you place them on another target.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You can only use this power once per turn.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>
</class>
