<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../class.xsl"?>

<class>
   <name>Assassin</name>
   <subname>Stalker</subname>
   <role>Striker</role>
   <source>Shadow</source>
   <shortfluff>You are the ghost in the night and the whisper on the wind - barriers are worthless against you, and you strike your foes with sudden, precise force.</shortfluff>
   <keyability>Dexterity</keyability>
   <keyability>Constitution</keyability>
   <keyability>Charisma</keyability>
   
   <proficiency>
      <type>Armor</type>
      <name>Cloth</name>
      <name>Leather</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Weapon</type>
      <name>Simple one-handed melee</name>
      <name>Simple ranged</name>
      <name>Military heavy blade</name>
      <name>Military light blade</name>
   </proficiency>
   <proficiency>
      <type>Implement</type>
      <name>Ki focus</name>
      <name>any proficient weapon for Assassin powers</name>
   </proficiency>
   
   <defense>
      <name>Fortitude</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
   <defense>
      <name>Will</name>
      <value>+1</value>
   </defense>
   
   <hpbase>12</hpbase>
   <hpgain>5</hpgain>
   <surgebase>6</surgebase>
   
   <skills>
      <trained>Stealth</trained>
      <number>4</number>
   </skills>
   
   <fluff>Few creatures embrace shadow magic without both a compelling reason and a measure of desperation. Not many visit the Shadowfell willingly, let alone pledge a shard of their souls to it. Yet that is exactly what Assassins, and other practitioners of shadow magic, do to gain their power.</fluff>
   <fluff>As an Assassin, you cede a portion of yourself to the Shadowfell, replacing a fundamental part of your being with a dark reflection of your true self. At times, you can manifest this twisted image in place of your body so that you can face attacks with little cause for concern. Also, the infusion of shadow magic allows you to spot the weakest points in a victim's defenses. With a few moments of study, you can reduce even the stoutest warrior to a corpse.</fluff>
   <fluff>An Assassin usually keeps his or her profession a secret, since few trust those who regularly deal in death. Assassins' guilds provide some measure of protection, especially in those regions where the study of shadow magic and assassination as an art form are banned.</fluff>
   <fluff>As a Stalker, you are an outcast. You traded away part of your soul for the power of death. Perhaps you seek justice against a powerful enemy, or maybe you had no other way to preserve yourself in the face of a bleak, uncaring world. Whatever drew you onto the Stalker's path, you are an avatar of death and a trained killer from whom few can escape unharmed.</fluff>
   
   <feature>
      <name>Assassin's Shroud</name>
      <benefit> The dark magic of the Shadowfell courses through your veins, tainting your soul but granting you the ability to subject an enemy to invisible shrouds that reveal its weakest points. The more of your shrouds there are on a target, the deadlier a blow you can strike against it.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>assassin's shroud</i>]]> class power that allows you to place your shrouds on a target. Other benefits can also allow you to place your shrouds on a target. You can have your shrouds on only one creature, and one creature can have up to four of your shrouds on it. A creature can have shrouds from multiple assassins on it.</benefit>
      <benefit>If a creature is not aware of your presence, it is not aware of your shrouds being on it either.</benefit>
      <benefit>Before you make an attack roll against the target, you choose to invoke either all your shrouds on it or none of them. If you invoke your shrouds and the attack hits, the attack deals +1d6 damage for each shroud. If the attack misses, you deal damage for one less shroud, even if the attack normally deals half or no damage on a miss. After the attack has been resolved, all your shrouds vanish from the target.</benefit>
      <benefit>The damage per shroud increases to 1d8 + 2 at 11th level, and to 1d10 + 4 at 21st level.</benefit>
      
      <power>
         <title>Assassin's Shroud</title>
         <class>Asassin</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <fluff>You cause invisible shrouds to settle on your foe that reveal the target's weak points to your keen gaze</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
            <keyword>Shadow</keyword>
            <action>Free</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Ranged</type> <range>10</range>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <text>Using this power does not trigger opportunity attacks</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>One enemy you can see</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You place your shrouds on the target, or increase your number of shrouds on it by one. The shrouds lasts until the end of the encounter, or until you place them on another target.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Special:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You can use this power only once per turn.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>
   
   <feature>
      <name>Guild Training</name>
      <benefit>Assassins gain their abilities by following a training regimen developed by a particular guild. Even an assassin taught by an individual master studies a set of teachings that were once developed by a guild.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose either Bleak Disciple, Martial Executioner, or Night Stalker as your method of training.</benefit>
      
      <subfeature>
         <name>Bleak Disciple</name>
         <benefit>The tradition of the Bleak Disciple teaches its adherents to forge the stuff of shadow into a weapon they can use against their foes. Its strictest followers keep a white cloth that they dab in the blood of each slain foe, and before they attack a chosen target, they reflect on this memento of the foes they have defeated.</benefit>
         <benefit>Against a nonbloodied target, you deal additional damage equal to your number of shrouds on the target. If the target is at full hit points or it has been bloodied but regained hit points to become unbloodied, you add your Constitution modifier to this damage.</benefit>
         <benefit>This additional damage increases to twice your number of shrouds at 11th level, and to three times your number of shrouds at 21st level. Also at 21st level, you add twice your Constitution modifier to the damage instead of once, when applicable.</benefit>
         <benefit>Also, whenever you kill a creature with a shadow power, you gain a bonus to the first assassin damage roll you make before the end of your next turn. This bonus equals your Constitution modifier, and increases to 4 + your Constitution modifier at 11th level, and to 8 + your Constitution modifier at 21st level.</benefit>
      </subfeature>
      
      <subfeature>
         <name>Martial Executioner</name>
         <benefit>The training for Martial Executioners focuses on speed and effectiveness with weapons. This culminates in learning a single, deadly technique instead of a variety of applications for shadow magic.</benefit>
         <benefit>You count as a martial class in addition to shadow class for the purposes of qualifying for feats. If such a feat has benefits related to martial powers, you gain those benefits with your assassin powers.</benefit>
         <benefit>Also, you gain the <![CDATA[<i>assassin's strike</i>]]> class power, but do not gain any assassin encounter attacks. You can only recover your <![CDATA[<i>assassin's strike</i>]]> with a long rest, a short rest, or another effect that allows you to regain all your expended encounter attacks.</benefit>
         
         <power>
            <title>Assassin's Strike</title>
            <class>Assassin</class> <category>Attack</category>
            <fluff>You strike with precision at the exact right moment, landing an attack that can be instantly lethal</fluff>
            <part>
               <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
               <keyword>Martial</keyword>
               <action>Nonaction</action> <subaction>Interrupt</subaction>
               <type>Special</type>
               <section>
                  <name>Trigger:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You hit a creature within 5 squares of you with an at-will Weapon attack</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <name>Target:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>The triggering creature</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effec:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>The target takes +1d10 additional damage from the triggering attack.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 3:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>+2d10 additional damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 7:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>+4d10 additional damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 13:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>+6d10 additional damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 17:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>+8d10 additional damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 23:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>+10d10 additional damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 27:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>+12d10 additional damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>If the target is helpless, it takes the maximum amount of additional damage you can deal with this power.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>If the target is not helpless but is unaware of your presence, you can reroll any 1 on the additional damage until the die's result is anything else than a 1.</text>
               </section>
            </part>
         </power>
      </subfeature>
      
      <subfeature>
         <name>Night Stalker</name>
         <benefit>Night Stalker instructors claim that fear and misdirection are as deadly as a poisoned blade. This tradition teaches how best to draw on shadow magic to terrorize and deceive enemies.</benefit>
         <benefit>Against a target that is adjacent to none of your enemies, you deal additional damage equal to your number of shrouds on the target. If you use a Fear power or the target is unaware of your presence, you add your Charisma modifier to this additional damage.</benefit>
         <benefit>This additional damage increases to twice your number of shrouds at 11th level, and to three times your number of shrouds at 21st level.</benefit>
         <benefit>Also, whenever you bloody a a creature with a shadow power, that creature takes a penalty to all attack rolls until the start of your next turn. The penalty equals one-half your Charisma modifier (minimum -1). This is a Fear effect, and allows you to trigger adding your Charisma modifier to the above additional damage.</benefit>
      </subfeature>
   </feature>
   
   <feature>
      <name>Infused Form</name>
      <benefit>When a Stalker gives part of his or her soul to the Shadowfell, the power of that dark realm fuses with his or her material form.</benefit>
      <benefit>Choose either Black Flame Form or Shade Form to determine how this fusion manifests for you.</benefit>
      
      <subfeature>
         <name>Black Flame Form</name>
         <benefit>A few Stalkers feed the infusion with raw fury and hatred, stoking it as one might a bonfire. When manifest, black flames dance across the Stalker's form, doing no harm to him or her, but rather turning away attacks and burning those who get too close.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>black flame form</i>]]> class power.</benefit>
         
         <power>
            <title>Black Flame Form</title>
            <class>Assassin</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>The shadows nearby deepen as dark flames erupt from your body, enveloping and protecting you</fluff>
            <part>
               <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
               <keyword>Fire, Necrotic, Shadow</keyword>
               <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
               <type>Personal</type>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You assume a dark, fiery form that lasts until the end of your next turn. The power immediately ends if you make an attack.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>If you make an at-will attack against a target with at least two of your shrouds on it which you invoke, you can make a saving throw. On a success, this power does not end.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>If you make an at-will attack against a target with four of your shrouds on it, you can make a saving throw. On a success, this power does not end.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <text>If you make an at-will attack against a target with at least two of your shrouds on it which you invoke, this power does not end.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>While in this form, you gain resist 5 to all damage, and any creature that hits you with a melee attack takes 5 fire and necrotic damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Resist 10, and 10 fire and necrotic damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Resist 15, and 15 fire and necrotic damage.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>When you assume this form, you can use your <![CDATA[<i>assassin's shroud</i>]]> class power if you have it, without spending an action. This does not count against your one use of the power per turn.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Sustain Minor:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>The form persists until the end of your next turn.</text>
               </section>
            </part>
         </power>
      </subfeature>
      
      <subfeature>
         <name>Shade Form</name>
         <benefit>Most Stalkers can use the infusion to assume a shadowy form that allows him or her to pass through cracks and evade enemies. When assuming this form, the Stalker blurs, his or her skin becomes gray, and all the gear you carried and the clothes worn adopt similarly dull colors. His or her eyes lose their pupils, becoming blank, white orbs.</benefit>
         <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>shade form</i>]]> class power.</benefit>
         
         <power>
            <title>Shade Form</title>
            <class>Assassin</class> <category>Utility</category>
            <fluff>You transform yourself into a being of shadow, becoming more difficult to notice or to harm</fluff>
            <part>
               <frequency>Encounter</frequency>
               <keyword>Shadow</keyword>
               <action>Minor</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
               <type>Personal</type>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>You assume a shadowy form until the end of your next turn. The power immediately ends if you make an attack.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>While in this form, you are insubstantial, and you gain vulnerable 5 radiant. While squeezing, you move at your full speed, and you can use any movement mode you wish.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Vulnerable 7 radiant.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Vulnerable 10 radiant.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade>
                  <text>In addition, you can make Stealth checks to become hidden if you have any cover or concealment, and you can use cover granted by your allies to become hidden and to remain hidden.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>You also gain a +2 power bonus to checks to become hidden.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>You also gain a +4 power bonus to checks to become hidden.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <name>Sustain Minor:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
                  <text>The form persists until the end of your next turn.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>1</indent>
                  <text>If you used this power outside of combat, you can sustain it for up to 1 hour. If you have sustained the form for more than five minutes and combat starts, the power ends at the start of your first turn.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>2</indent>
                  <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Up to 4 hours outside of combat, and the power ends at the end of your first turn if you have sustained it for more than 5 minutes and combat starts.</text>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <shade>true</shade> <indent>2</indent>
                  <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
                  <text>Up to 8 hours outside of combat. You can always sustain the power for up to 1 hour, and the power ends at the end of your first turn if you have sustained it for more than 1 hour and combat starts.</text>
               </section>
            </part>
         </power>
      </subfeature>
   </feature>
   
   <feature>
      <name>Shadow Step</name>
      <benefit>The shadow energy surrounding every creature touches the Shadowfell slightly, for the realm of death is a creature's eventual destination. A Stalker has the ability to walk the shadow pathways from one creature to another.</benefit>
      <benefit>You gain the <![CDATA[<i>shadow step</i>]]> class power.</benefit>
      
      <power>
         <title>Shadow Step</title>
         <class>Assassin</class> <category>Utility</category>
         <fluff>You step into the shadow energy around one creature and then step out of it near another creature</fluff>
         <part>
            <frequency>At-Will</frequency>
            <keyword>Shadow, Teleportation</keyword>
            <action>Move</action> <subaction>Action</subaction>
            <type>Personal</type>
            <section>
               <shade>true</shade>
               <name>Requirement:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You must be adjacent to a creature.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <name>Effect:</name> <name-style>bold</name-style>
               <text>You teleport up to 3 squares to a space adjacent to another creature.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>Up to 4 squares.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>Up to 5 squares.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <text>If you are bloodied, you can teleport 1 additional square.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 11:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>If the creature adjacent to you and the creature you teleport adjacent to are both bloodied, you can also teleport 1 additional square.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
               <indent>1</indent>
               <name>Level 21:</name> <name-style>italic</name-style>
               <text>If either the creature adjacent to you or the creature you teleport adjacent to is bloodied, you can also teleport 1 additional square, or 2 additional squares if both are bloodied.</text>
            </section>
         </part>
      </power>
   </feature>
   
   <feature>
      <name>Assassin Implement Powers</name>
      <benefit>The shadow magic wielded by Assassins is crude. But that also makes it easier to control. An Assassin does not necessarily need a specially prepared implement, instead harnessing magical power from a weapon.</benefit>
      <benefit>When you use an assassin Implement power, you can use any weapon you are proficient with as an implement.</benefit>
      <benefit>You do not count as having implement proficiency in the weapon for any other purposes.</benefit>
   </feature>
   
   <feature>
      <name>Optional Feature: Expert Poisoner</name>
      <benefit>Some Assassins learn to use shadow magic for alchemical shortcuts, allowing them to brew a limited amount of short-lived but potent poisons.</benefit>
      <benefit>You do not gain assassin daily attacks. Instead, you learn to create assassin poisons.</benefit>
      <benefit>At first level, you learn the recipes for two heroic-tier Assassin Poisons. When you finish an extended rest, you can prepare one vial of a heroic-tier Assassin Poison whose recipe you know.</benefit>
      <benefit>You must have a poisoner's kit to prepare Assassin Poisons. A prepared poison expires when you begin your next extended rest. You can apply only one Assassin Poison to an item. You are immune to an Assassin Poison you have prepared yourself, though not to the same poison prepared by a different Assassin.</benefit>
      <benefit>At fifth level, you learn the recipe for another heroic-tier Assassin Poison. When you finish an extended rest, you can now prepare two vials of heroic-tier Assassin Poisons whose recipe you know. You can prepare the same poison in multiple vials.</benefit>
      <benefit>At ninth level, you learn the recipe for another heroic-tier Assassin Poison. When you finish an extended rest, you can now prepare three vials of heroic-tier Assassin Poisons whose recipe you know.</benefit>
      <benefit>At fifteenth level, you learn the recipes for two paragon-tier Assassin Poisons. When you prepare your Assassin poisons, one of them can be paragon-tier.</benefit>
      <benefit>At nineteenth level, you learn the recipe for another paragon-tier Assassin Poison. When you prepare your Assassin Poisons, two of them can be paragon-tier.</benefit>
      <benefit>At twenty-fifth level, you learn the recipes for two epic-tier Assassin Poisons. When you prepare your Assassin Poisons, one of them can be epic-tier and the rest can be paragon-tier.</benefit>
      <benefit>At twenty-ninth level, you learn the recipe for another epic-tier Assassin Poison. When you prepare your Assassin Poisons, two of them can be epic-tier, and the last can be paragon-tier.</benefit>
      <benefit>Some paragon paths let you learn the recipes for additional Assassin Poisons, and your DM might let you learn additional Assassin Poisons if the story calls for it.</benefit>
   </feature>
</class>
